<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="CT_Overview">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Overview</emphasis></title>

  <para>This manual contains documentation for the set of Client Tools for use
  with the LexisNexis HPCC. These tools include:</para>

  <informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec align="left" colwidth="122.40pt" />

      <colspec />

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECLPlus</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL execution tool to facilitate automation of
          ECL Code execution.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECL</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL tool.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECL Compiler</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL Compiler</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">DFUPlus</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line Distributed File Utility management tool,
          facilitate automation of data file spray, despray, and other common
          file handling tasks.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

  <sect1 id="Documentation_Conventions">
    <title>Documentation Conventions</title>

    <sect2 id="ECL_Language">
      <title><emphasis>ECL Language</emphasis></title>

      <para>Although ECL is not case-sensitive, ECL reserved keywords and
      built-in functions in this document are always shown in ALL CAPS to make
      them stand out for easy identification.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Example Code</title>

        <para>All example code in this document appears in the following
        font:</para>

        <programlisting>MyECLFileName := COUNT(Person);
// MyECLFileName is a user-defined ECL file
// COUNT is a built-in ECL function
// Person is the name of a dataset</programlisting>

        <para>ECL file names and record set names are always shown in example
        code as mixed-case. Run-on words may be used to explicitly identify
        purpose in examples.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Actions</title>

        <para>In step-by-step sections, there will be explicit actions to
        perform. These are all shown with a bullet to differentiate action
        steps from explanatory text, as shown here:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Keyboard and mouse actions are shown in small caps, such
              as: DOUBLE-CLICK, or press the ENTER key. word.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>On-screen items to select are shown in boldface, such as:
              press the <emphasis role="bold">OK </emphasis>button.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Installation">
      <title><emphasis>Installation</emphasis></title>

      <para>The installation program installs all client tools, including the
      ECLPlus, DFUPlus, and RoxieConfig. The installation program provides the
      option to select which tools to install.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para>From the CD, your Build Server, or your download:</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run <emphasis role="bold">setup.msi </emphasis>, then follow
          the prompts</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis>System Requirements</emphasis></para>

      <para>The recommended system configuration is:</para>

      <para>A Pentium III processor (or higher) and at least 128 megabytes
      (MB) of RAM.</para>

      <para>Microsoft Windows 2000, Windows XP, Windows Server 2003, Windows
      Vista, Windows 7, or higher.</para>

      <para>A full installation requires less than 16 MB of disk space.<!-- --></para>

      <para>The optional Tutorial Data File is 100 MB.</para>

      <para>In addition, you will need Internet Explorer 8 and have Active
      Scripting support enabled (Javascript). If browser security is set to
      High, you should add the ECLWatch IP (or DNS name) as a Trusted
      Site.</para>

      <para>Adobe Reader 5 (or higher) is required to view the documentation
      PDF files.</para>

      <para>GVC Viewer is used to display graphs in ECL Watch, and RoxieConfig
      GUI. It is installed automatically.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
