<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="CT_Overview">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Overview</emphasis></title>

  <para>This manual contains documentation for the set of Client Tools for use
  with the LexisNexis HPCC. These tools include:</para>

  <informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec align="left" colwidth="122.40pt" />

      <colspec />

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECLPlus</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL execution tool to facilitate automation of
          ECL Code execution.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECL</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL tool.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ECL Compiler</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line ECL Compiler</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><emphasis role="bold">DFUPlus</emphasis></entry>

          <entry>Command line Distributed File Utility management tool,
          facilitate automation of data file spray, despray, and other common
          file handling tasks.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

  <sect1 id="Documentation_Conventions">
    <title>Documentation Conventions</title>

    <sect2 id="ECL_Language">
      <title><emphasis>ECL Language</emphasis></title>

      <para>Although ECL is not case-sensitive, ECL reserved keywords and
      built-in functions in this document are always shown in ALL CAPS to make
      them stand out for easy identification.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Example Code</title>

        <para>All example code in this document appears in the following
        font:</para>

        <programlisting>MyECLFileName := COUNT(Person);
// MyECLFileName is a user-defined ECL file
// COUNT is a built-in ECL function
// Person is the name of a dataset</programlisting>

        <para>ECL file names and record set names are always shown in example
        code as mixed-case. Run-on words may be used to explicitly identify
        purpose in examples.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Actions</title>

        <para>In step-by-step sections, there will be explicit actions to
        perform. These are all shown with a bullet or a numbered step to
        differentiate action steps from explanatory text, as shown
        here:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Keyboard and mouse actions are shown in all caps, such as:
              DOUBLE-CLICK, or press the ENTER keyword.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>On-screen items to select are shown in boldface, such as:
              press the <emphasis role="bold">OK </emphasis>button.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Installation" role="brk">
      <title>Installation</title>

      <para>The installation program installs all client tools, including the
      ECLPlus, DFUPlus, and the ECL Command line tools.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the HPCC Systems download page, <ulink
          url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/client-tools">http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/client-tools</ulink></para>

          <para>Download the appropriate Client Tools for your Operating
          System. (available for RPM-Based systems, Debian-Based systems, Mac
          OSX, or Windows)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the client tools software to your machine.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows: </emphasis></para>

          <para>Run the executable file, for example:
          hpccsystems-clienttools_community-4.X.X-XWindows-i386.exe on your
          machine. Follow the prompts to complete the installation.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">RPM-Based Systems (CentOS/RedHat):
          </emphasis></para>

          <para>An RPM installation package is provided. Install RPM with the
          -Uvh switch, the U or upgrade will perform an upgrade if a previous
          version is already installed. <programlisting>sudo rpm -Uvh &lt;rpm file name&gt;</programlisting></para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Debian-Based Systems
          (Ubuntu):</emphasis></para>

          <para>For Ubuntu installations a Debian package is provided. To
          install the package, use:</para>

          <programlisting>sudo dpkg -i &lt;deb filename&gt;</programlisting>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Mac OSX:</emphasis></para>

          <para>Open the Apple disk image file (.dmg) and then run the
          installation package (.pkg). Follow the prompts to complete the
          installation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Other_Installs">
      <title>Multiple Version Installations</title>

      <para>It is possible to install multiple versions of the client tools if
      you need to work with multiple versions of the platform.</para>

      <para>To install the client tools, obtain the appropriate installation
      package for your operating system and the version to match your HPCC
      Systems server:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Download the appropriate Client Tools for your Operating
          System and version.</para>

          <para>Client tools can be found at the HPCC Systems download
          page:</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/client-tools">http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/client-tools</ulink></para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NOTE:</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>There is a link at the bottom of the list "<emphasis
                role="blue">view older downloads</emphasis>" if you are
                looking for previous versions.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the Client Tools on to your system. Take note of the
          following considerations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Client tool packages starting with 4.2 have built in logic to
      allow for multiple installations. Prior versions of the client tools
      package would just overwrite the existing components. The default
      behavior is that the client tools will use the last one installed,
      except if you are working directly on the platform. If you are working
      directly on the platform then it would use the client tools package that
      gets installed with the platform.</para>

      <para>If you install a version other than the delivered client tools you
      will have a folder in /opt/HPCCSystems that corresponds to the set of
      client tools. So you could have a client tools 4.0.x, 4.2.x, 4.4.x, etc.
      </para>

      <para>Client tools for Windows installs in a directory such as:
      C:\Program Files (x86)\HPCCSystems\4.2.0\clientools where the number
      (4.2.0 for example) will correspond to the version of the client tools.
      </para>

      <para>For older versions, download the package(s), and install. Install
      the one you want to use last. Copy to a different folder or Rename the
      client tools found in /opt/HPCCSystems after installing the older
      version and before installing the newer version. This is to prevent the
      newer client tools from overwriting the older one. Windows clients will
      prompt you to delete the previous version during installation. </para>

      <para>To use the Client tools for the various version number(s)
      explicitly call the client tool you wish to use, or set up an alias to
      call the client tool using the proper path or name for the version you
      intend to use. This would depend on how you chose to save off the older
      client tools you installed.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">For example</emphasis>, if you wanted to run
      eclplus:</para>

      <programlisting>eclplus action=view wuid=W12345678</programlisting>

      <para>To run eclplus for an older or another version of client tools,
      for instance 4.0.x:</para>

      <para><programlisting>/opt/HPCCSystems/4.0.x/clienttools/bin/eclplus action=view wuid=W12345678</programlisting></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
