<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book xml:base="../">
  <title>Using ECL Watch</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>Using ECL Watch</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email> Please include
      <emphasis role="bold">Documentation Feedback</emphasis> in the subject
      line and reference the document name, page numbers, and current Version
      Number in the text of the message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license. Other products,
      logos, and services may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their
      respective companies. All names and example data used in this manual are
      fictitious. Any similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="FooterInfo"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="DateVer"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <corpname>HPCC Systems</corpname>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="Copyright"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introducing ECL Watch</title>

    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>ECL Watch is a service that runs on the Enterprise Services
      Platform (ESP), a middleware component on the HPCC Platform.</para>

      <para>ECL Watch provides an interface to the HPCC system and allows you
      to view information and interrogate nodes to confirm all expected
      processes are running. It is a plug-in that is useful for Systems
      Administrators to check processes, examine topology, and view logs. It
      is useful to ECL Programmers to monitor the status of jobs and files,
      and other pertinent information. This provides a simple view into the
      system and a means to perform Workunit and data files
      maintenance.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>ECL Watch Home</title>

    <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">ECL Watch home</emphasis> link in
    the navigation bar at the top of the ECL Watch page to find the <emphasis
    role="bold">Activity</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="bold">Scheduler</emphasis> links. These links provide access to the
    respective pages you need to be able to perform the related tasks.</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>HPCC Platform link</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA010.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>Activity</title>

      <para>The Activity page displays activity on all clusters in the
      environment. The Activity page provides access to Cluster Job Queue
      administration tasks such as: monitoring progress, setting priority,
      moving a job up or down in the queue, pausing a job, aborting a job, and
      pausing or resuming a queue.</para>

      <!--***Note specific Activity task details have been REMOVED (to DocShare/WKSPCE/ECLWa400)***-->

      <para>When ECL Watch starts it defaults to the Activity page. To access
      the Activity page from any other page in ECL Watch click on the HPCC
      Platform image at the top of any page, as indicated the preceding
      image.</para>

      <para>Activity related tasks can also be initiated from the workunit tab
      for the specific job in question.</para>

      <sect2 id="cluster_Info" role="brk">
        <title>Cluster Information</title>

        <para>You can access more information about your clusters from the
        main Activity page. Select the target cluster from the main <emphasis
        role="bold">Activity</emphasis> tab, by checking the box next to it.
        <figure>
            <title>Open Cluster</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA002.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>This enables the <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis> action
        button. Press the Open action button to open a new tab for that
        cluster. You can also double-click on the target cluster.</para>

        <para>The cluster tab displays the groups on that cluster.
        Double-click on a group, or check the box next to the cluster group,
        and press the open button. <figure>
            <title>Open Cluster Groups</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA003.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Open up the cluster group tab (for example, mythor), and select
        the group from the Groups tab to see the activity information on that
        cluster group. <figure>
            <title>Cluster Activity tabs</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA004.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>On that cluster group tab, you can access the information about
        that cluster. There are three tabs on that cluster group tab. The
        <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> tab provides a snapshot of
        that group. The <emphasis role="bold">Usage</emphasis> tab provides
        access to a usage graph, and other information. The <emphasis
        role="bold">Log File</emphasis> tab is where you can view that cluster
        group's log. <figure>
            <title>Cluster Log File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA005.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Global Search</title>

        <para>On the navigation bar at the top of the ECL Watch page, about
        half way across the page is the search box. <figure>
            <title>Search box</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA008.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>You can search for workunits, users, files, or even ECL, using
        the search box. The search box supports wild cards.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>ECL Event Scheduler</title>

      <para>The Event Scheduler page provides an interface to the ECL
      Scheduler. The ECL Scheduler interface allows you to see a list of
      scheduled workunits. It can also trigger an event. An Event is a
      case-insensitive string constant naming the event to trap.</para>

      <para>ECL Scheduling provides a means of automating processes within ECL
      code or to chain processes together to work in sequence. For example,
      you can write ECL code that watches a landing zone for the arrival of a
      file, and when it arrives, sprays it to Thor, processes it, builds an
      index, and then adds it to a superfile.</para>

      <para>ECL Scheduling is event-based. The ECL Scheduler monitors a
      Schedule list containing registered Workunits and Events and executes
      any Workunits associated with an Event when that Event is
      triggered.</para>

      <para>Your ECL Code can execute when an Event is triggered, or can
      trigger an Event. If you submit code containing a <emphasis
      role="bold">WHEN </emphasis>clause, the Event and Workunit registers in
      the Schedule list. When that Event triggers, the Workunit compiles and
      executes. When the Workunit completes, ECL Scheduler removes it from the
      Schedule list.</para>

      <para>For example, if you submit a Workunit using <emphasis
      role="bold">WHEN(‘Event1’,’MyEvent’, COUNT(2)) </emphasis>in the
      appropriate place, it will execute twice (the value of <emphasis
      role="bold">COUNT</emphasis>) before the ECL Scheduler removes it from
      the Schedule list and the Workunit is marked as completed.</para>

      <para>For more details about both <emphasis id="WHEN"
      role="bold">WHEN</emphasis> or <emphasis id="NOTIFY"
      role="bold">NOTIFY</emphasis> or any ECL Language functions or keywords
      please see the ECL Language reference. A copy of which can be found
      online at <ulink
      url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/docs/learning-ecl">http://hpccsystems.com/download/docs/learning-ecl</ulink>
      on the HPCC Systems web site.</para>

      <!--***NOTE: Be sure to UPDATE these images when they find a home in ECLWATCH***-->
    </sect1>

    <xi:include href="ECLScheduler/ECLSched-Mods/ECLSchedComp.xml"
                xpointer="ECLSched_Interface"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>ECL Workunits</title>

    <para>ECL Watch provides information about ECL jobs and workunits. Links
    to pages that contain information about ECL workunits appear in the
    navigation bar along top of the ECL Watch page. There you will find links
    to ECL Workunits, simply labelled as Workunits, and you will also find the
    link to the ECL Playground. Not only can you find information about
    workunits there, but you can perform operations on workunits.</para>

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="ECLWorkunits"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLPlayground/ECLPlay-Mods/ECL_Playground.xml"
                xpointer="ECL_Playground"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Files</title>

    <para>This chapter contains sections dealing with HPCC Platform Files,
    found on the <emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis> link in ECL
    Watch.</para>

    <para>In an HPCC platform, data files are partitioned across nodes. The
    file parts, referenced using Logical Filenames, are stored in the
    Distributed File Utility. This allows the collection of file parts to be
    referenced as a single entity.</para>

    <!--  Might this be chapter for Xref?***-->

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="ECLWatchLogicalFiles"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="DFUWorkunits"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="Landing_Zones"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <sect1 id="spray_and_despray">
      <title>Spray/Despray</title>

      <para>This section details how to Spray and Despray a Data file to your
      Thor cluster using ECL Watch. The spray function is integrated into the
      Landing Zone page as detailed in the <link linkend="Upload_Files">Upload
      Files</link> section .</para>

      <para>In order to spray a file to your Thor cluster you must first
      upload the file to your landing zone. The file upload steps are detailed
      in the preceding section.</para>

      <para>With the file successfully uploaded to the landing zone you can
      choose the file to spray from the Landing Zone page. Once selected the
      Spray buttons become enabled.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Landing Zone Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA440.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Spray Data to Thor</title>

        <para>With the <emphasis role="bold">Spray:</emphasis> Action buttons
        enabled, you press the appropriate button for the Spray you wish to
        perform. Fill in the appropriate values when prompted to complete the
        spray.</para>

        <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                    xpointer="Spray_Fixed"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

        <?hard-pagebreak ?>

        <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                    xpointer="Spray_Delimited"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

        <?hard-pagebreak ?>

        <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                    xpointer="Spray_XML"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>XRef</title>

      <para>Under the <emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis> Icon on the
      navigation sub-menu there is a link for XRef. This link will take you to
      the XRef Clusters page. On the XRef clusters page you can run the XREF
      utility.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>XRef Clusters page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA435.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The XREF utility provides the ability to find "orphaned" and "lost
      and found" files. These "orphan" are files which are found on the nodes
      but not registered in the Distributed File System.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Found File</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A found file has partial file parts on disk that are not
            referenced in the Dali server. All the file parts are accounted
            for so they can be added back to the Dali server. They can also be
            deleted from the cluster, if required.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Orphan File</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An orphan file has partial file parts on disk. However, a
            full set of parts is not available to construct a complete logical
            file. These partial file parts, therefore, do not have a reference
            in the Dali server.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Lost File</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A logical file that is missing at least one file part on
            both the primary and replicated locations in storage. The logical
            file is still referenced in the Dali server. Deleting the file
            removes the reference from the Dali server and any remaining parts
            on disk.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
        <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

          <colspec />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/tip.jpg" /></entry>

              <entry><para>On a large system, we suggest limiting the number
              of users who can Generate XREF reports by setting DfuXrefAccess
              access to FULL for only those users.</para><para>
              </para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>To generate a list:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Generate</emphasis>
          button.</para>

          <informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

              <colspec />

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/tip.jpg" /></entry>

                  <entry><para>Sasha Server typically runs Xref at the times
                  scheduled when deployed.</para><para> </para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To view results:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on one of the hyperlinks (Found Files, Orphan Files,
          Lost Files, Directories, or Errors/Warnings).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect2>
        <title>Working with XREF results:</title>

        <para>After XRef completes you will see a list of available reports.
        Click on one of the links to see the results page of each type.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>XRef Errors</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA435b.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The Orphan and Lost Files pages list any Orphan or Lost files.
        Orphan and Lost files are difficult to recover, unless you have copies
        of missing parts needed to reconstruct the file (for example, if a
        missing part is on a hard drive that was replaced.)</para>

        <figure>
          <title>XRef: Delete Lost Files</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA436.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Typically, these files are deleted. To Delete, check the boxes
        next to files you want to delete, then press the Delete button.</para>

        <para>Found files can and usually are reattached. <figure>
            <title>XRef: Attach Found Files</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA437.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Check the boxes next to files you want to reattach, then press
        the Attach button.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Queries</title>

    <para>The link for the Published Queries (icon) header provides more
    information and details about queries on available targets.</para>

    <!-- <para>Include ROXIE (RDDE). List of Clusters.</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; Thor</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; Roxie</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; hThor</para>

    <para>I. Dynamic</para>

    <para>II. Clusters</para> -->

    <para>Click on the Published Queries (icon) hyperlink to display the
    published queries and package maps on that cluster.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Query Link</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA00Q.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect1 id="Queries_Page" role="nobrk">
      <title>Queries Page</title>

      <para>The Queries page lists published queries for each target cluster.
      On this page you can see the published queries . You can also perform
      some actions on the selected queries.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Browse Query Sets</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA432.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The Queries interface provides some information at a glance, there
      are three columns on the left side of each listed query. These three
      columns provide information about these queries.</para>

      <!--Per Miguel: The Icons are very likely to be removed from the Main Queries page, 
can probably just move the table here to the query detail page... 
depending on where they wind up.-->

      <para><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
          <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

            <colspec />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="images/ECLWA-pause.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates a paused query</para><para>
                </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="images/ECLWA-active.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates an activated query</para><para>
                </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="images/ECLWA-suspend.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates a query suspended by the
                system</para><para> </para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>

      <para>The queries page also provides other information at a
      glance:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the query ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the query name</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the target</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the workunit id (WUID)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the dll</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Published by</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>All the above available at a glance on the main queries
      page, with further actions that can be performed from the action buttons
      along the top of the tab. You can sort a column by clicking on the
      column heading. Click once for ascending, click again to toggle to
      descending. The direction of the arrow indicates the sort order.</para>

      <!--VERIFY THAT THIS BEHAVIOR APPLIES HERE: YES, was not implemented but added when I brought this up.***-->

      <para>To see the details page for a particular query, or to perform some
      action on it you must select it. You can select a query or queries by
      checking the check box. You can also open a particular query by double
      clicking on it.</para>

      <sect2 id="QueryDetails" role="brk">
        <title>Query Details</title>

        <para>To examine the Query Details page, you select and open the query
        or queries. This opens a tab containing the query details. From the
        query details page you can get more information about the specific
        query. You can also perform some actions on that query. There are
        several tabs with additional information about the selected
        query.</para>

        <sect3 id="QuerySummaryTab">
          <title>Query Summary Tab</title>

          <para>The default query tab opened when you select a query is the
          Summary tab. The summary tab shows you some detail information about
          the query.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Query detail page</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLW006.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>There are a few actions that you can perform on the query
          from this tab. Press the action buttons for the desired activity for
          the selected query.</para>

          <para><variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Refresh</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Refreshes the information displayed for the selected
                  query.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Saves the selected query (or queries).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Delete</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Deletes the selected query (or queries).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="ErrorsTab">
          <title>Errors Tab</title>

          <para>For each selected query there is an Errors tab. The Errors tab
          displays any errors that may have been encountered during the
          compiling and publishing of that query. If there aren't any errors
          the errors tab will be blank. If there are errors, you can further
          examine any specific error by checking the box and selecting it, and
          then press the open action button. You could also just double click
          on the selected error. <figure>
              <title>Query Error</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA006E.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="GraphsTab">
          <title>Graphs Tab</title>

          <para>The graphs tab provides access to graphical interpretations of
          the query. This can be helpful in visualizing how the query ran. The
          graphs tab displays a list of any graphs generated by the selected
          query, along with some additional information like timing. To
          display a specific graph, you must select it, and choose to open it,
          or you can double click on listed graph.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Graphs list</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA006G.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Opening a graph will open a new tab showing the selected
          graph(s).</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Graphs</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA006G1.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>When you open a graph the visible area splits into three
          smaller sections each displaying some relevant component of the
          query graph. Notice the myriad of graph controls, and tabs in the
          border area of each tab. Manipulate these controls to view different
          aspects of the graphs.</para>

          <para>The Advanced action button on the main graph control area,
          provides access to even more advanced graphing options.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Logical Files Tab</title>

          <para>The Published queries details page provides a link to the
          queries Logical Files tab. The Logical Files tab shows all logical
          files that are used by the query. To view the logical file details
          for any file listed, select one or more files by checking the
          checkbox and press the Open action button. Tabs for each file
          selected opens where you can view and make changes to the file(s)
          without the need to go back to the logical files page.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Queries:Logical Files Tab</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA006L.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The above image shows the list of Logical files on the Logical
          Files tab. To view more detail about a logical file listed here,
          check the box next to the file, and then press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Open</emphasis> action button. You can also just double
          click on the logical file you want to view.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="Test_Pages">
          <title>Test Pages</title>

          <para>The Test Pages tab provides a number of resources you can use
          to test your query including SOAP/JSON/WSDL and the legacy WS-ECL
          form, as well as other tabs showing useful information or sample
          details about the query.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Test Pages tab</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA012.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>Information available from the Test pages tab.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">SOAP</emphasis> This tab provides an
              interactive interface to submit the query (with input data) and
              see the response in XML format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">JSON</emphasis> This tab provides an
              interactive interface to submit the query (with input data) and
              see the response in JSON format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">WSDL</emphasis> This tab provides a
              WSDL definition describing the functionality offered by the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Request Schema </emphasis>This tab
              provides a schema in XSD format describing a request for the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Response Schema</emphasis> This tab
              provides a schema in XSD format describing a response from the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Sample Request </emphasis>This tab
              provides a sample request for the query (web service) in XML
              Format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Sample Response</emphasis> This tab
              provides a sample response from the query (web service) in XML
              Format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Parameter XML</emphasis> This tab
              provides Parameterized XML representation of the query
              interface.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Legacy Form</emphasis> This tab
              provides a form that can be used to submit a query and get a
              response. This is similar to the WsECL form.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Links</emphasis> Provides a list of
              useful links such as: the Form, a sample REST URL, sample
              request, sample response, parameter XML, SOAP POST, WSDL, XSD,
              and the result schema.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="QueriesWorkUnits">
          <title>The Workunits link</title>

          <para>The Published queries details page provides a link to to the
          workunits, page. This tab is a shortcut that takes you to the same
          workunits tab you can get to through the ECL workunits menu.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Queries Workunit</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA006W.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>This is the same as the <emphasis role="bold">ECL
          Workunits</emphasis> page from the navigation sub-menu Workunits
          link. You can perform the same operations here. Notice that there
          are some other familiar tabs here as well, for example the Graphs
          tab, both from the Queries details page, and from the workunit tab
          nested here.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="Package_Maps">
        <title>Package Maps</title>

        <para>From the Queries icon link, you can access the package maps
        page. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Package Maps</emphasis> button
        on the navigation sub-menu bar, to access to the Package Maps on your
        cluster. <figure>
            <title>Package Maps</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA470.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>The package maps page, displays all the package maps loaded on
        your cluster. You can Add, Activate, Deactivate, Delete, or Open a
        package map. To examine a package map, select a package map from the
        list.</para>

        <para>You can select the <emphasis role="bold">Validate Package
        Map</emphasis> tab to validate a package map.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Validate Package Maps</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWaPkMgr.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Choose the <emphasis role="bold">Target</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">Process</emphasis> from the drop lists on the Validate
        Package Map tab.</para>

        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Validate</emphasis> button to
        validate the package map. The result is shown on the <emphasis
        role="bold">Validate Active Package Map</emphasis> tab. You can also
        Validate the package content, on the V<emphasis role="bold">alidate
        Package Content</emphasis> tab.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Operations</title>

    <para>The Operations link provides access to several components useful for
    the day-to-day operation of your system, and some system administration
    access as well. <figure>
        <title>Operations Menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA460.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>There are links to Target Clusters, Cluster Processes, and System
    Servers. These links open pages with more information about the specific
    topology for the selected clusters. These pages are helpful in certifying
    that your system is up and running properly.</para>

    <para>There are also some system administration type links such as, Users,
    Groups, Permissions, and Resources. These links allow you to perform some
    system administration tasks through ECL watch.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Disk Usage</title>

      <para>When you click on the Operations link, it opens the Disk Usage
      page by default. The Disk Usage page provides information about the
      available space on your system, and what is using that space. <figure>
          <title>Disk Usage</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA462.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>You can search or filter the results, using the <emphasis
      role="bold">Filter</emphasis> action button.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Operations: Target Clusters</title>

      <para>The Target Clusters link from the navigation sub-menu bar, on the
      Operations page, opens the link to the Target Clusters page. This page
      provides machine information on the clusters you have set up on your
      machine. <figure>
          <title>Target Clusters</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA461.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </sect1>

    <xi:include href="HPCCCertify/Cert-Mods/CertPreflight.xml"
                xpointer="Preflight_system_servers"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="HPCCCertify/Cert-Mods/CertPreflight.xml"
                xpointer="Preflight_Data_Refinery"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <!--
    /*commented whole sect out*/
    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>Users</title>
      /*PROBABLY NOT NEEDED - AND CAN BE DELETED*/
      <para>There are User Administration features available through ECL
      Watch. Common system administration tasks are accessible through the
      Operations menu in ECL Watch. The links to Users, Groups, Permissions,
      and Resources allow you to manage these components of your HPCC system
      from the ECL Watch interface.</para>

      <xi:include href="Installing_and_RunningTheHPCCPlatform/Inst-Mods/UserSecurityMaint.xml"
                  xpointer="Sec_Adm_w_ECLWatch"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1> 
 -->
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="User_Permissions_Chapter">
    <title>Users Permissions</title>

    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>User Administration</title>

      <para>There are User Administration features available through ECL
      Watch.</para>

      <xi:include href="Installing_and_RunningTheHPCCPlatform/Inst-Mods/UserSecurityMaint.xml"
                  xpointer="Sec_Adm_w_ECLWatch"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Account_Info">
    <title>Advanced Menu</title>

    <para>There is a section at the top right on the navigation bar with some
    useful information and features. This section shows you who you are logged
    in as (if your system has authentication enabled). The Advanced menu is
    located on the right hand side of the navigation bar. There are several
    items that you can access from the advanced menu.</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>Advanced menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA007b.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>There may be a number displayed on the menu link. A number displayed
    next to it indicates how many errors and warnings have been generated
    during your session. Click on the advanced menu to display a list of
    features.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Access the Advanced menu</title>

      <para>You access the advanced menu items from the advanced menu link at
      the top right corner of ECL Watch.<!--Removed some content stashed in GitStash : ECLWA-1115.xml others culled stored in git-br H8872-NewestECLfor50 **--></para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Set Banner</emphasis> link allows you to
      set a custom banner message at the top of your browser window when you
      open ECL Watch. You can use this feature to send messages to
      users.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Error/Warning(s)</emphasis> link
      displays a tab showing you Errors, Warnings, and Information messages.
      You can filter this page by checking the boxes at the bottom of the tab.
      A copy facility is also provided.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Open Legacy ECL Watch</emphasis> link
      opens a tab to the previous version of ECL Watch. The legacy version of
      ECL Watch is deprecated; this link is only available for a limited time
      to help in the transition.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Additional Resources</emphasis> link
      opens a tab to the HPCC Systems download page, where you can browse and
      download additional HPCC resources: documentation, white papers,
      training videos, wiki pages, the red book and other HPCC related source
      code.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Release Notes</emphasis> link opens a
      tab with the relevant release notes for the version of HPCC that you are
      using. Read the release notes for more information specific to the
      release you are working on.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Configuration</emphasis> link opens for
      viewing the xml version of the configuration file in use on your
      system.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">About</emphasis> link opens a dialog to
      display some information about the version of the HPCC platform and
      graph controls installed on your server.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>User Details</title>

      <para>The LOGGED IN AS link shows information about the current user on
      a cluster configured for authentication.</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
            role="bold">LOGGED IN AS:</emphasis></emphasis> link.</para>

            <para>The User Details window opens. The default window opens on
            the Summary tab.</para>

            <para><figure>
                <title>User Details window</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA474.jpg" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From The User Details page Summary tab, you can Confirm the
            User Name that you are logged in as.</para>

            <para>You can change your password.</para>

            <para>Note that Administrator rights are needed to manage users
            and permissions.</para>

            <para>Ensure you are using an account with Administrator rights if
            you intend to manage users or permissions.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Verify the password expiration date, or if password is set
            to expire.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <sect2 role="nobrk">
        <title>Change Password</title>

        <para>If authentication is enabled on your HPCC system, you can change
        your password, right from the User Details window. <!--***? is this still valid : don't see where this is in new ECLWatch ***--><orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
              role="bold">LOGGED IN AS:</emphasis></emphasis> link.</para>

              <para>The User Details window opens. The default window opens on
              the Summary tab. There are fields on the Summary tab where you
              can change your password.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Enter your desired new password.</para>

              <para>Make sure it meets whatever criteria your system may have
              for passwords.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Confirm your new password.</para>

              <para>Make sure that it matches the password you entered in the
              previous field.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Press the Save button. It is in the upper left portion of
              the window.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Permission groups</title>

        <para>The second tab on the User Details window labelled Member Of,
        displays a list of groups. The groups your account belongs to, are
        indicated with a checkmark.</para>

        <para>You must be an administrator to modify any of group
        settings.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>User Permissions tab</title>

        <para>The third tab on the User Details window labelled <emphasis
        role="bold">User Permissions</emphasis>, displays a list of permission
        settings. Note that Administrator rights are needed to manage users
        and permissions. Ensure you are using an account with Administrator
        rights if you intend to manage users or permissions.</para>

        <para>This is where you can access the user permissions area. A more
        detailed description of the user permissions settings is covered in
        the <link linkend="User_Permissions_Chapter">User Permissions</link>
        section.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Resources">
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>The resources link can be found under the Operations Icon link. The
    resources link in ECL Watch provides a link to the HPCC Systems web
    portal. Visit the HPCC Systems Web Portal at <ulink
    url="http://hpccsystems.com/">http://hpccsystems.com/</ulink> for software
    updates, plug-ins, support, documentation, and more. This is where you can
    find resources useful for running and maintaining HPCC on the web
    portal.</para>

    <para>You can also get to the resources link on the HPCC Systems web
    portal page, by clicking on the <emphasis role="bold">Additional
    Resources</emphasis> link found on the sub-menu of at the top right hand
    side of navigation bar.</para>

    <para>ECL Watch provides a link to the HPCC portal's download page: <ulink
    url="http://hpccsystems.com/download">http://hpccsystems.com/download</ulink>.
    This is the page where you can download Installation packages, virtual
    images, source code, documentation, and tutorials.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
