<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en_US" xml:base="../">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Rapid Data Delivery Engine Reference</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email> Please include
      <emphasis role="bold">Documentation Feedback</emphasis> in the subject
      line and reference the document name, page numbers, and current Version
      Number in the text of the message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license. Other products,
      logos, and services may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their
      respective companies. All names and example data used in this manual are
      fictitious. Any similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="FooterInfo"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="DateVer"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <corpname>HPCC Systems</corpname>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="Copyright"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Roxie engine - also known as the Rapid Data Delivery Engine or
    RDDE - uses a combination of technologies and techniques that produce
    extremely fast throughput for queries on indexed data housed in a
    dedicated High Performance Computing Cluster (HPCC).</para>

    <para>Roxie queries can exceed several thousand a second, compared to Thor
    queries which tend to take from a few seconds to a few minutes each (from
    end to end) depending on the complexity of the query.</para>

    <para>To fully understand this concept, it is best to look at the purpose
    for which each of these processes is designed:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>The Thor platform is designed to perform operations on every
        record (or most records) in a massive dataset.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Queries can be run on the hThor platform if they can quickly
        pinpoint small sets of records within the data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Roxie queries are typically used to quickly pinpoint small sets
        of records over and over again.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you think of all your data as an ocean, Thor would be used to
    perform operations on the entire ocean.</para>

    <para>An hThor query might be used to find a single fish within that sea
    of data.</para>

    <para>The query would be deployed to a Roxie cluster to be used to find
    hundreds or thousands of individual fish-one after another.</para>

    <para>Roxie queries are deployed to a Roxie cluster, which pre-loads all
    queries into memory and prepares them to be ready to execute as soon as a
    query is received.</para>

    <para>Queries are sent to Roxie via XML, SOAP, or JSON, and the results
    are returned in the same format. A client can communicate directly with
    the Roxie cluster by opening a socket to one of the servers in the
    cluster, or it can communicate via an ESP service such as WsECL.</para>

    <sect1 id="Roxie_Overview">
      <title>Roxie Overview</title>

      <para>There are typically four aspects to using Roxie:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para>Creating indexes on datasets</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using indexes in queries</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compiling and Deploying queries to the Roxie Cluster</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Providing access to those queries to client-facing interfaces
          via SOAP or HTTP.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect2>
        <title>When to Use Indexes</title>

        <para>The Thor platform is designed to perform operations quickly on
        massive datasets without indexes, where the entire dataset (or almost
        all of it) is to be used. However, if only a few records are needed,
        an index can access them more efficiently. In the ECL language, an
        index behaves just like a dataset that happens to be able to implement
        certain functions (typically filter and count functions) much more
        quickly than a standard flat file or CSV dataset can.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Payload_INDEXes">
      <title>Payload INDEXes</title>

      <para>In conventional database systems, an index is used together with a
      data file to locate records in that data file. You can do the same in
      ECL by storing file positions in the index and using them in a FETCH
      function to retrieve the corresponding data rows from the original
      file.</para>

      <para>However, because you can store whatever fields you wish in an
      index, it is more common in Roxie queries to design indexes that store
      both the search fields and the information you want to look up. This
      eliminates an extra disk read for the FETCH. Since indexes are
      compressed, this can also save disk space if the original data file does
      not need to be stored on the Roxie cluster.</para>

      <para>Any field in an index that does not need to be searched for can be
      specified as being in the "payload" - such fields are stored only at the
      leaf nodes of the index tree which can save some space and performance
      in the lookups. The fields in the payload may simply be additional
      fields from the base dataset, but they may also contain the result of
      some preliminary computation (computed fields).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Roxie_Superfiles">
      <title>Roxie Superfiles</title>

      <para>A superfile used in Roxie may not contain more than a single
      sub-file (a superkey, however, may contain multiple payload indexes).
      This restriction makes using superfiles in Roxie just an exercise in
      file redirection. By writing queries that use superfiles (even though
      they contain only a single sub-file) you have the advantage of being
      able to update your Roxie by simply deploying new data without needing
      to re-compile the queries that use that data simply because the sub-file
      name changed. This saves compilation time, and in a production
      environment (which a Roxie typically is) where a data file is used by
      many queries, this savings can be a significant.</para>

      <para>See the <emphasis>ECL Programmer's Guide</emphasis> for more
      details.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="How-Roxie-Works">
      <title>How Roxie Works</title>

      <para>Roxie clusters consist of a number of machines connected together
      to function as a single entity. ECL source code for one or more queries
      is compiled and published to the cluster. Once published, queries can
      process data rapidly.</para>

      <para>Each machine in the cluster acts in two distinct roles - these
      roles execute in the same process and share a lot of code - including
      the compiled query code - but can be thought of as logically
      distinct.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis> process accepts
      incoming queries from a client, evaluates the ECL code of the query
      given the input that is provided in the client query, and returns the
      result to the client. When the Server evaluates an ECL function that
      requires data from disk, it determines the slave node or nodes that may
      have the appropriate data, and sends a request to those slave nodes to
      retrieve any matching data. Results from multiple slave nodes are
      collated and become the input for further ECL functions evaluated on the
      Server node. Typically, requesting applications use some form of load
      balancing to distribute requests evenly to the available Servers.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Slave</emphasis> process accepts
      requests only from other Server nodes in the cluster. These requests
      correspond to a single ECL function such as a filtered index read or a
      disk fetch. Results are sent back to the Server that originally
      requested them. In order to balance performance and manage hardware
      failures, slaves receive the requests over multicast, and there will
      typically be at least two slave nodes that will receive each request
      from a server. The slave nodes communicate with each other to avoid
      duplicating effort, so that whichever slave is first able to handle the
      request tells the others not to bother. Each node in a cluster typically
      handles Slave requests on two or more multicast channels, usually one
      channel per disk drive. If any Slave node is not responding, the
      requests on that channel are handled by the other peer Slave nodes
      responsible for that channel.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-02.jpg" /></para>

      <para>This example shows a 5-node Roxie Cluster with each node
      configured to be both a <emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis> and a
      <emphasis role="bold">Slave</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Queries that have been compiled with the target platform specified
      as a Roxie cluster may be published to a QuerySet using EclWatch.</para>

      <para>Each Roxie cluster loads queries from one or more QuerySet
      lists.</para>

      <para>When a query is added to the QuerySet that a Roxie is watching,
      Roxie will preload the query .so (or .DLL) and prepare the execution
      context as far as it can, so that it is ready to execute incoming
      requests to execute that query as soon as they arrive. This may includes
      loading the .so (or .DLL), resolving file references, and opening files
      (if there are sufficient file handles available), preloading data into
      memory if requested, and evaluating ECL code in the query that has been
      marked as : ONCE.</para>

      <para>Depending on the configuration, Roxie may read data remotely from
      a Thor cluster where it was prepared, or if preferred, it may be copied
      to the Roxie for local access.</para>

      <para>Typically a development system might refer to data in situ on the
      Thor cluster, while a production system may prefer the performance
      benefits of copying data locally to the Roxie.</para>

      <para>Roxie can read data remotely while it is being copied and switch
      to the local copy once the copy operation is complete. This provides the
      benefit of quick availability because the query can be active before the
      data is copied, while still taking advantage of the performance benefits
      of local data.</para>

      <xi:include href="RDDERef/RDDE_Mods/RoxieCopySettings.xml"
                  xpointer="element(/1)"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Roxie-Data-Backup">
      <title>Roxie Data Backup</title>

      <para>Roxie data is protected by three forms of redundancy:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para>Original Source Data File Retention: When a query is deployed,
          the data is typically copied from a Thor cluster's hard drives.
          Therefore, the Thor data can serve as backup, provided it is not
          removed or altered on Thor. Thor data is typically retained for a
          period of time sufficient to serve as a backup copy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Peer-Node Redundancy: Each Slave node typically has one or
          more peer nodes within its cluster. Each peer stores a copy of data
          files it will read.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sibling Cluster Redundancy: Although not required, Roxie
          deployments may run multiple identically-configured Roxie clusters.
          When two clusters are deployed for Production each node has an
          identical twin in terms of data and queries stored on the node in
          the other cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><?dbfo-need height="8.75in"?>This configuration provides multiple
      redundant copies of data files. In this example, there are six copies of
      each file at any given time; eliminating the need to use traditional
      backup procedures for Roxie data files.</para>

      <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-03.jpg" /></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Developing_Roxie_Queries">
    <title>Developing Roxie Queries</title>

    <sect1 id="Development_Path" role="nobrk">
      <title>Development Path</title>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Determine the need.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Evaluate data and determine fields to index.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Build Index(es).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create a hThor query.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Test and fine-tune the query (using hThor).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Publish the Query to a Roxie cluster.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Test and certify (compare results to expected results).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: These steps are explained
      in detail in the HPCC Data Tutorial and the Programmer's Guide.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Methods-to-Submit-Jobs-to-a-Roxie-Cluster">
      <title>Methods to Submit Jobs to a Roxie Cluster</title>

      <para>After a query is compiled and deployed, there are several methods
      to submit jobs that use the query. While the most common usage is via
      custom applications using the XML or SOAP interface, the other methods
      have valid uses, too.</para>

      <para>A direct socket connection can communicate directly with the Roxie
      cluster, eliminating all other intermediate components. This provides a
      means of certifying the Roxie cluster, its configuration, the deployment
      of the query, and the query itself.</para>

      <para>SOAPCALL allows a Thor query to make calls to a Roxie query (See
      the <emphasis>ECL Language Reference </emphasis>for details). This
      provides the capability of combining Roxie results with other data
      processing tasks performed during ETL.</para>

      <para>Conducting queries via an ESP service using HTTP or HTTPS allows
      access to queries directly from a browser. Web-based access allows you
      to provide easy access to anyone you wish. Using HTTPS, you can ensure
      data security using Secure Socket Layer (SSL) encryption. This ensures
      all data is encrypted as it travels across a network or the Internet. In
      addition, LDAP authentication is available to restrict access to a set
      of users.</para>

      <para>Custom applications using SOAP provides the most flexibility and
      functionality. The application development process is simplified by
      Enterprise Services Platform's automatic Web Services Definition
      Language (WSDL) generation. Many development tools (such as, Microsoft's
      .NET Studio or NetBeans JAVA) include a tool to generate code to create
      proxy stubs from a WSDL document. This simplifies the development
      process and ensures exposure of all necessary methods and
      properties.</para>

      <sect2 id="Direct-Socket-Connection-TCP-IP">
        <title>Direct Socket Connection (TCP/IP)<?dbfo-need height="3in"?></title>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-04.jpg" /></para>

        <beginpage />
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="SOAPCALL_via_ECL">
        <title><emphasis>SOAPCALL via ECL</emphasis></title>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-05.jpg" /></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="SOAP-or-HTTP-HTTPS">
        <title>SOAP or HTTP/HTTPS<?dbfo-need height="6in"?></title>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-06.PNG" scale="90"
        scalefit="1" /></para>

        <para></para>

        <beginpage />
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Managing Queries</title>

    <para>Roxie queries are managed via Query Sets which are stored in Dali.
    Query Sets control which queries are loaded onto Roxie when it starts up
    and are manipulated by adding or removing them as required. The list of
    queries currently held within a QuerySet can be viewed using ECL
    Watch.</para>

    <para>Once a query has been published to the Query Set, it can now be run
    on the roxie using a web interface.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Adding a roxie query to the Query Set</title>

      <para>To add a roxie query to a Query Set:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use ECL IDE to write your query and then compile it setting
          the target as the roxie cluster in your HPCC environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Go the ECL Watch tab for the compiled workunit and click the
          Publish button. A message is displayed indicating that your query
          has been published successfully.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Viewing Query Sets using ECL Watch</title>

      <para>Using ECL Watch, you can view the query for all clusters on your
      HPCC. Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Query Sets/Browse</emphasis>
      menu item to see the clusters which are currently using Query Sets.
      Click on the <emphasis role="bold">myroxie</emphasis> link to view the
      list of queries currently available for roxie. Using this feature you
      can:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>View the list of currently available queries on a
          cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>View details about each query including the ID, the name of
          the query, the workunit ID, the DLL(s) it uses and whether it is
          suspended.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>View details of the aliases that exist for each query.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Delete a Query from the list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Delete an Alias.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggle the suspend setting on/off</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Using WsECL to run a roxie query</title>

      <para>WsECL is the ECL Web Service interface that is provided with HPCC
      and is available using the following URL: http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8002,
      where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address of your ESP.</para>

      <para>WsECL uses the Query Sets information to display the list of
      available runnable queries and you can use it, for example, to test that
      your query works as expected.</para>

      <para>The web page shows all clusters using Query Sets. Expand myroxie
      in the tree and select the query you want to run. A default form is
      displayed which is generated from the input field names and types. Enter
      values and press submit to see the results and test your query.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <xi:include href="RDDERef/RDDE_Mods/Packages.xml" xpointer="element(/1)"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <chapter id="Deploying-Data-to-a-Cluster-using-DFU">
    <title>Deploying Data to a Cluster using DFU</title>

    <para>You can use the Distributed File Utility (DFU) in ECL Watch to copy
    (or remote copy) data files to a Roxie cluster. This allows you to copy
    large files to a cluster in advance of publishing a query. If data files
    are copied in advance, a query which requires those files will use the
    ones already in place. If you have large data sets, this allows you to
    prepare in advance of query deployment.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> To use this feature, the
    FTSlave utility must be installed to each node in the cluster. This is
    done automatically by the Configuration Manager Wizard.</para>

    <sect1 id="Copy">
      <title><!---->DFU Copy</title>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the ECLWatch web page. You can reach this page using
            the following URL: http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8010, where
            nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is your node's IP address.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Browse Logical Files
            </emphasis>hyperlink below <emphasis role="bold">DFU
            Files</emphasis> in the menu on the left.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Locate the file to copy in the list of files, then click on
            the icon, then select <emphasis role="bold">Copy</emphasis> from
            the pop-up menu.</para>

            <para><graphic fileref="images/RDDE_DFUcopy.jpg"
            vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Fill in <emphasis role="bold">Destination</emphasis> and
            <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis>information.</para>

            <para><graphic fileref="images/RDDE_DFUcopy.2.jpg"
            vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>

            <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colwidth="122.40pt" />

                  <colspec colwidth="333.00pt" />

                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Destination:</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Group</entry>

                      <entry>Use the drop list to select the Roxie cluster to
                      copy to.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Note</emphasis>:</entry>

                      <entry>You can only choose from clusters within the
                      current environment.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Logical File</entry>

                      <entry>The logical name for the copied file.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>File Mask</entry>

                      <entry>Automatically updated based on logical file name
                      entered.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Options:</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Overwrite</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to overwrite files of the same
                      name.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Replicate</entry>

                      <entry><para>Check this box to create backup copies of
                      all file parts in the backup directory (by convention on
                      the secondary drive of the node following in the
                      cluster).</para><para><emphasis role="bold">This option
                      is only available on systems where replication has been
                      enabled.</emphasis></para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Wrap</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to keep the number of parts the
                      same and wrap if the target cluster is smaller that the
                      original.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Compress</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to compress the files.</entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </informaltable></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Submit
            </emphasis>button.</para>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">DFU
            Workunit</emphasis>displays.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">View Progress</emphasis>
            hyperlink to see a progress indicator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Remote_Copy">
      <title>Remote Copy</title>

      <para>Remote Copy allows you to copy data to a Roxie from a Thor or
      Roxie cluster outside your environment.</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the ECLWatch web page. You can reach this page using
            the following URL: http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8010, where
            nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is your node's IP address.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Remote Copy</emphasis>
            hyperlink below <emphasis role="bold">DFU Files</emphasis> in the
            menu on the left.</para>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Copy File</emphasis> page
            displays.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Fill in <emphasis role="bold">Source,
            Destination,</emphasis> and <emphasis
            role="bold">Options</emphasis>information.</para>

            <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colwidth="122.40pt" />

                  <colspec colwidth="333.00pt" />

                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Source:</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Logical File</entry>

                      <entry>The logical file name in the remote
                      environment</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Source Dali</entry>

                      <entry>The Dali Server in the remote environment</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Source Username</entry>

                      <entry>A valid user in the remote environment</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Source Password</entry>

                      <entry>The password for the user in the remote
                      environment</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Destination:</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Group</entry>

                      <entry>Use the drop list to select the cluster to copy
                      to.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Note:</entry>

                      <entry>You can only choose from clusters within the
                      current environment.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Logical File</entry>

                      <entry>The logical name for the copied file.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>File Mask</entry>

                      <entry>Automatically updated based on logical file name
                      entered.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry align="right"><emphasis
                      role="bold">Options:</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Overwrite</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to overwrite files of the same
                      name.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Replicate</entry>

                      <entry><para>Check this box to create backup copies of
                      all file parts in the backup directory (by convention on
                      the secondary drive of the node following in the
                      cluster).</para><para><emphasis role="bold">This option
                      is only available on systems where replication has been
                      enabled.</emphasis></para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Compress</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to compress the files.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                      <entry>Wrap</entry>

                      <entry>Check this box to keep the number of parts the
                      same and wrap if the target cluster is smaller that the
                      original.</entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </informaltable></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Submit
            </emphasis>button.</para>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">DFU Workunit</emphasis>
            displays.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">View Progress</emphasis>
            hyperlink to see a progress indicator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Capacity_Planning_for_Roxie_Clusters">
    <title>Capacity Planning for Roxie Clusters</title>

    <sect1 id="Capacity_Planning" role="nobrk">
      <title>Capacity Planning</title>

      <para>Roxie clusters are disk-based High Performance Computing Clusters
      (HPCC) , typically using indexed files. A cluster is capable of storing
      and manipulating as much data as its combined hard drive space; however,
      this does not produce optimal performance.</para>

      <para>For maximum performance, you should configure your cluster so
      slave nodes perform most jobs in memory.</para>

      <para>For example, if a query uses three data files with a combined file
      size of 60 GB, a 40-channel cluster is a good size, while a 60-channel
      is probably better.</para>

      <para>Another consideration is the size of the Thor cluster creating the
      data files and index files to be loaded. Your target Roxie cluster
      should be the same size as the Thor on which the data and index files
      are created or a number evenly divisible by the size of your Roxie
      cluster. For example, a 100-way Thor to a 20-way Roxie would be
      acceptable.</para>

      <para>This is due to the manner in which data is loaded and processed by
      Roxie slaves. If data is copied to slave nodes, the file parts are
      directly copied from source location to target locations. They are NOT
      split or resized to fit a different sized cluster. Therefore, if you
      load 50 file parts onto a 40-channel cluster, part one goes to channel
      one, part two to channel two, etc. Parts 41-50 start at the top again so
      that part 41 goes to channel 1, and part 42 goes to channel 2, etc. The
      result is an unevenly distributed workload and would result in reduced
      performance. A cluster will only perform as fast as its slowest
      node.</para>

      <para>The final consideration is the number of Server processes in a
      cluster. Each slave must also be a Server, but you can dedicate
      additional nodes to be only Server processes. This is useful for queries
      that require processing on the Server after results are returned from
      slaves. Those Server-intensive queries could be sent only to dedicated
      Server IP addresses so the load is removed from nodes acting as both
      Server and slave.</para>

      <sect2 id="Configuring_the_Channels">
        <title>Configuring the Channels</title>

        <para>In the illustration below, the nodes are configured using an N+5
        scheme to share channels. Channels can be configured in many ways,
        this is one example.</para>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-15.jpg" /></para>

        <para>In this depiction, each enclosure holds five Roxie slave blades
        (a row of servers in the picture). We will use this example for the
        rest of this manual.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="PreFlight_and_Roxie_Metrics">
    <title>PreFlight and Roxie Metrics</title>

    <sect1 id="ECL-Watch-Preflight">
      <title>ECL Watch / Preflight</title>

      <para>ECL Watch's Topology section is used to perform Preflight
      activities. These preflight utilities are used for daily health checks,
      as well as trouble avoidance and troubleshooting. It provides a central
      location to gather hardware and software information from a remote set
      of machines and has many uses for day-to-day environment
      preparation.</para>

      <sect2 id="Regular_Uses">
        <title>Regular Uses</title>

        <para>Typical uses for Preflight in the preparation of the environment
        before a data build</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Examine disk space utilization</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Critical for optimal operation of the Data Refinery
                nodes.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Disk space utilization alarm threshold easily
                adjusted.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>View last boot up of all nodes in a cluster</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Confirms the boot-up state of a node without having to
                login to the node.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Confirm expected processes running on each node</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Make sure all HPCC processes are running on the
                appropriate nodes</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Validate network availability of each node</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect3>
          <title>Using ECL Watch PreFlight in Troubleshooting</title>

          <para>These are typical uses for Preflight in troubleshooting</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Validate Disk Space Utilization</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Validate Memory Utilization</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Validate monitoring agent process running on nodes
              (heimdall.exe)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Validate processes running on the appropriate
              machines</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>On a routine basis, typically before processing begins, an
          entire system health check should be performed.</para>

          <para>There are three sections in the Topology area of ECL
          Watch:</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Clusters, including all clusters of any of the following
              types:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Thor (Data Refinery Cluster)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Roxie (Rapid Data Delivery Engine Cluster)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>System Servers, including all system components in the
              current environment:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Dali Server</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>DFU Server(s)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>ECL CC Server(s)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>ECL Scheduler</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>ECL Agent(s)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>ESP Server(s)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sasha Server</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECL_Watch_PreFlight_Tasks">
        <title><emphasis>ECL Watch PreFlight Tasks</emphasis></title>

        <para>Perform these tasks using ECL Watch when validating or
        troubleshooting a component.</para>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the ECLWatch web page. You can reach this page using
            the following URL: http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8010, where
            nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is your node's IP address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>In the left side menu, click on one of the hyperlinks under
            <emphasis role="bold">Topology</emphasis>:</para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">System Servers </emphasis>or<emphasis
            role="bold"> Clusters </emphasis></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <para>For a cluster, click on its hyperlink.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-16.jpg"
        vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>

        <para>A page displays showing all machines of the type selected in the
        previous steps.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>For a cluster, make sure the <emphasis role="bold">Select
            All</emphasis> checkbox is checked (to select all servers).</para>

            <para>For System Servers, the critical servers are pre-selected.
            If you only want to PreFlight a specific machine, check only the
            box next to its listing.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Check the boxes for <emphasis role="bold">Get Processor
            Information</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Get storage
            information</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">Get software
            information</emphasis>. These should be checked
            automatically.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Check the <emphasis role="bold">Show processes
            using</emphasis> filter checkbox. Submitting a request using the
            predefined filters verifies whether the appropriate HPCC processes
            are running. For example, a machine defined as a Dali server would
            be verified for all processes expected to run on a Dali
            server.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Optionally, check the <emphasis role="bold">Auto Refresh
            Every</emphasis> checkbox and provide the number of minutes. This
            will automatically query the servers and refresh the page at the
            provided interval.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis>
            button.</para>

            <para>The resulting page displays all the requested information,
            as shown below:</para>

            <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-17.jpg"
            vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Any expected processes that are not running are highlighted
            in orange in the <emphasis role="bold">Processes Down</emphasis>
            column.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Hovering the mouse over any column, displays additional
            information.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Any values below the specified thresholds (see above) are
            displayed with an orange background.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For disk space utilization, all local drives are displayed.
            Partitions to exclude (such as RAM Drives) are defined in the
            ECLWatch service.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis></para>

        <para>The following option settings are available to customize the
        execution and display.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Machine Information</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specifies that the query will return machine information for the
        selected machines.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Get Roxie Metrics</emphasis></para>

        <para>This option is available only to Roxie cluster. It displays
        diagnostic information about the cluster. See the <emphasis>Roxie
        Metrics</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis>section in this
        manual.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Get Processor
        Information</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specifies that the query will include results about the
        processor usage on the selected machines. The threshold for a warning
        is set in the <emphasis role="bold">Warn if CPU Usage is
        over</emphasis> entry control.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Get storage Information</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specifies that the query will include results about memory and
        disk space on the selected machines. The threshold for a warning about
        memory is set in the <emphasis role="bold">Warn if available memory is
        under</emphasis> entry control. The threshold for disk space warnings
        is set in the <emphasis role="bold">Warn if available disk space is
        under</emphasis> entry control.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Get software Information</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specifies that the query will include results about running
        processes on the selected machines.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Processes using
        filter</emphasis></para>

        <para>Checking this box specifies that a query using predefined
        filters will verify whether the appropriate HPCC processes are
        running. For example, a machine defined as a Dali server would be
        verified for all processes expected to run on a Dali server. If not
        checked, all running processes are displayed in a pop-up window when
        the mouse pointer is over the column.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Additional Processes to
        filter</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis>When using a filter, this entry
        box allows you to add additional processes to consider. If the
        specified process is not running, it will appear in the <emphasis
        role="bold">Down Processes</emphasis> column.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Auto Refresh Every ___
        mins.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Optionally, provide an interval in minutes to automatically
        re-submit the query.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Roxie-Queries-and-Roxie-Files-in-ECL-Watch">
      <title>Roxie Queries and Roxie Files in ECL Watch</title>

      <para>ECL Watch allows you to search for deployed Roxie Queries and to
      search for deployed Roxie Files.</para>

      <sect2 id="To_Search_Roxie_Queries">
        <title><emphasis>To Search Roxie Queries</emphasis></title>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the ECLWatch web page. You can reach this page using
            the following URL: http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8010, where
            nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is your node's IP address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The ECL Watch home page will open.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Search Roxie Queries
            </emphasis>below <emphasis role="bold">Roxie
            Queries</emphasis><graphic fileref="images/RM-18.jpg"
            vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Cluster </emphasis>from the
            drop list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>All Roxie clusters in this environment appear on the
        list.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the query type (Suspended, Non-Suspended, or both)
            from the <emphasis role="bold">Suspended </emphasis>drop
            list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Search
            </emphasis>button</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>The list of queries displays.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <para>Rt-click to the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/RM-19.jpg" />
            button on the left of any query, then select the action from the
            popup menu.<graphic fileref="images/RM-20.jpg"
            vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis> displays a page of
        details about the query, including:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>The Workunit ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Cluster</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the associated Shared Object (.so)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Query's priority</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The user that deployed it</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Whether or not it is suspended.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">ShowSuperFiles</emphasis> lists all
            superfiles used by the query</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">ShowNonSuperFiles</emphasis> lists all
            non-superfiles used by the query</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">ShowGraph </emphasis>displays the
            execution graph for the query.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">ShowGVCGraph </emphasis>displays the
            execution query's graph (in GVC format).</para>

            <graphic fileref="images/RM-20a.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect3>
          <title>To Search Roxie Files:</title>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Open the ECL Watch home page in a browser. The URL is the
              IP address of your ESP Server plus the port to which the
              EclWatch Service is bound (usually 8010).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The ECL Watch home page will open.</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Search Roxie Files
              </emphasis>below <emphasis role="bold">Roxie Queries</emphasis>
              in the menu on the left side.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Cluster </emphasis>from
              the drop list.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>All Roxie clusters in this environment appear on the
          list.</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Select the file type (Non-Super Files or Super FIles) from
              the <emphasis role="bold">File Type </emphasis>drop list.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Search
              </emphasis>button</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para>The list of files displays.</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>Rt-click to the <inlinegraphic
              fileref="images/RM-22.jpg" /> button on the left of any file,
              then select the action from the popup menu.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis> displays a page
              of details about the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">ViewDataFilee</emphasis> allows you
              to view the contents of a file. <emphasis
              role="bold"></emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">ShowQueries</emphasis> lists all
              queries using this file</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="Viewing_Roxie_Key_Files">
        <title>Viewing Roxie Key Files</title>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the ECL Watch home page in a browser. The URL is the IP
            address of your ESP Server plus the port to which the EclWatch
            Service is bound (usually 8010).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The ECL Watch home page will open.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Search Roxie Files
            </emphasis>below <emphasis role="bold">Roxie Queries</emphasis> in
            the menu on the left side.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Cluster </emphasis>from the
            drop list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>All Roxie clusters in this environment appear on the
        list.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the file type (Non-Super Files or Super FIles) from
            the <emphasis role="bold">File Type </emphasis>drop list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Search
            </emphasis>button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The list of files displays.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rt-click to the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/RM-25.jpg" />
            button on the left of any key file, then select <emphasis
            role="bold">ViewDataFile</emphasis> from the popup menu.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para>A form displays (containing fields in the Key File)</para>

        <para></para>

        <?hard-pagebreak ?>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Provide search criteria in the fields, then press the
            <emphasis role="bold">First </emphasis>button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Searching using a value in a Keyed column performs an indexed
        read. Values in Non-keyed columns provide post-fetch filtering (after
        the indexed read).</para>

        <para>The result displays in a similar manner as shown below:</para>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-28.jpg"
        vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="Roxie_Metrics">
      <title>Roxie Metrics<?dbfo-need height="5in"?></title>

      <para><graphic fileref="images/RM-30.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" /></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="102.05pt" />

            <colspec colwidth="293.95pt" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>IP Address</entry>

                <entry>The IP address of the Server node</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>slavesActive</entry>

                <entry>Number of slaves active for that Server</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>lastQueryTime</entry>

                <entry>Time stamp of most recent query executed</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>loQueryActive</entry>

                <entry>Number of low priority queries active</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>loMin</entry>

                <entry>Minimum time (ms) it took to run a low priority
                query</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>retriesNeeded</entry>

                <entry>Count of all reply packets that arrived to a Server as
                a response to more than one try.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>loMax</entry>

                <entry>Maximum time (ms) it took to run a low priority
                query</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>hiQueryActive</entry>

                <entry>Number of high priority queries active</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>loQueryCount</entry>

                <entry>Total number of low priority queries run</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>loQueryAverage</entry>

                <entry>Average time it took to run a high priority
                query</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>hiQueryCount</entry>

                <entry>Total number of high priority queries run</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>hiMax</entry>

                <entry>Maximum time (ms) it took to run a high priority
                query</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>hiMin</entry>

                <entry>Minimum time (ms) it took to run a high priority
                query</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>heapBlocksAllocated</entry>

                <entry>Number of times Roxie had to allocate memory from its
                memory allocator</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
