<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Capacity_Planning" role="nobrk">
  <title>Capacity Planning</title>

  <para>Roxie clusters are disk-based High Performance Computing Clusters
  (HPCC) , typically using indexed files. A cluster is capable of storing and
  manipulating as much data as its combined hard drive space; however, this
  does not produce optimal performance.</para>

  <para>For maximum performance, you should configure your cluster so agent
  nodes perform most jobs in memory.</para>

  <para>For example, if a query uses three data files with a combined file
  size of 60 GB, a 40-channel cluster is a good size, while a 60-channel is
  probably better.</para>

  <para>Another consideration is the size of the Thor cluster creating the
  data files and index files to be loaded. Your target Roxie cluster should be
  the same size as the Thor on which the data and index files are created or a
  number evenly divisible by the size of your Roxie cluster. For example, a
  100-way Thor to a 20-way Roxie would be acceptable.</para>

  <para>This is due to the manner in which data is loaded and processed by
  Roxie agents. If data is copied to agent nodes, the file parts are directly
  copied from source location to target locations. They are NOT split or
  resized to fit a different sized cluster. Therefore, if you load 50 file
  parts onto a 40-channel cluster, part one goes to channel one, part two to
  channel two, etc. Parts 41-50 start at the top again so that part 41 goes to
  channel 1, and part 42 goes to channel 2, etc. The result is an unevenly
  distributed workload and would result in reduced performance. A cluster will
  only perform as fast as its slowest node.</para>

  <para>The final consideration is the number of Server processes in a
  cluster. Each agent must also be a Server, but you can dedicate additional
  nodes to be only Server processes. This is useful for queries that require
  processing on the Server after results are returned from agents. Those
  Server-intensive queries could be sent only to dedicated Server IP addresses
  so the load is removed from nodes acting as both Server and agent.</para>

  <sect2 id="Configuring_the_Channels">
    <title>Configuring the Channels</title>

    <para>In the illustration below, the nodes are configured using an N+5
    scheme to share channels. Channels can be configured in many ways, this is
    one example.</para>

    <para><graphic fileref="../../images/RM-15.jpg" /></para>

    <para>In this depiction, each enclosure holds five Roxie agent blades (a
    row of servers in the picture). We will use this example for the rest of
    this manual.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
