<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect2>
  <!-- DNT-Start --><title><emphasis role="bold">Queries and Data</emphasis></title><!-- DNT-End -->

  <para>Data files and index files referenced by a Roxie query's <!-- DNT-Start -->ECL<!-- DNT-End --> code are
  made available in one of four ways, depending on the configuration of the
  Roxie cluster.</para>

  <para>There are two settings in the Roxie configuration that control where
  Roxie looks for data and index files:</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="123.60pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><!-- DNT-Start --><emphasis role="bold">copyResources</emphasis><!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>Copies necessary data and key files from the current
            location when the query is published.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><!-- DNT-Start --><emphasis role="bold">useRemoteResources</emphasis><!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>Instructs Roxie to look for data and key files in the
            current location after the query is published.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <graphic fileref="../../images/RM-31.jpg" />

  <para>These options may appear to be mutually exclusive, but the chart below
  shows what each of the four possible combination means.</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colwidth="125.40pt" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><!-- DNT-Start -->copyResources<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry><!-- DNT-Start -->T<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>F</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><!-- DNT-Start -->useRemoteResources<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry><!-- DNT-Start -->F<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry></entry>

            <entry align="left"><!-- DNT-Start -->Directs the Roxie cluster to use the remote
            instance of the data until it can copy the data locally. This
            allows a query to be available immediately while the data is
            copied.<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry align="left">Directs the Roxie cluster to copy the data
            locally. The query cannot be executed until the data is copied.
            This ensures optimum performance after the data is copied.</entry>

            <entry align="left"><!-- DNT-Start -->Directs the Roxie cluster to load the data
            from a remote location. The query can be executed immediately, but
            performance is limited by network bandwidth. This allows queries
            to run without using any Roxie disk space, but reduces its
            throughput capabilities.<!-- DNT-End --></entry>

            <entry align="left">Will use data and indexes already loaded
            (placed on the Roxie cluster using <!-- DNT-Start -->DFU<!-- DNT-End --> ) but will not copy or read
            remote data.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para>When <emphasis role="bold">copyResources</emphasis> is enabled, data
  files are copied from source locations to Roxie agent nodes. Index files are
  also copied, with an extra file part that is a "key-of-keys" or a
  metakey.</para>

  <para>A copy of the metakey is always stored on each Roxie server and in
  most cases is loaded into memory at startup to increase performance.</para>

  <sect3 id="RoxiePreferredCluster">
    <!-- DNT-Start --><title>Preferred Clusters</title><!-- DNT-End -->

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Preferred Clusters</emphasis> allows you to
    set priorities for clusters from which you want Roxie to copy files. If
    not otherwise specified Roxie copies from clusters in its own environment
    first. To enable the Preferred Clusters feature, you can use the <!-- DNT-Start -->HPCC<!-- DNT-End -->
    Systems Configuration Manager. (for additional information about
    Configuring your <!-- DNT-Start -->HPCC<!-- DNT-End --> System see <emphasis>Installing and Running the <!-- DNT-Start -->HPCC<!-- DNT-End -->
    Platform</emphasis>)<figure>
        <title>Roxie Preferred Clusters</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../../images/RxPrefCluster.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>The Preferred Clusters tab can be found on the RoxieCluster page
    within the <!-- DNT-Start -->HPCC<!-- DNT-End --> Configuration Manager.</para>

    <para>On the Preferred Clusters tab, you can add the name and the priority
    of your Roxie clusters. The highest priority number is the preferred
    cluster. To exclude a peer Roxie, add it to the Preferred Clusters list
    with a priority of 0. Roxie will then follow the priority specified in the
    Preferred Clusters list providing the highest priority to the Roxie
    cluster with the highest priority value when copying data.</para>

    <para>You should number your priorities with a numbering scheme of at
    least (the number of clusters)+1. Use a higher number to allow you to add
    clusters later.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="VipsRoxieAlias" role="brk">
    <!-- DNT-Start --><title>VIPs and Roxie Alias</title><!-- DNT-End -->

    <para>Roxie clusters accessed through a <!-- DNT-Start -->VIP<!-- DNT-End --> (Virtual <!-- DNT-Start -->IP<!-- DNT-End -->) usually use
    separate target names to represent the same set of queries. Each Roxie can
    also run more than one target at the same time.</para>

    <para>The Topology Alias feature provides a way to specify that any of the
    targets representing the same set of queries can be used. Allowing targets
    that represent the same set of queries to have a shared alias allows
    callers to select the right set of queries when calling through a
    <!-- DNT-Start -->VIP<!-- DNT-End -->.</para>

    <para>This setting can be found in the Topology section within the <!-- DNT-Start -->HPCC<!-- DNT-End -->
    Configuration Manager.</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>Roxie Alias in Configuration Manager</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../../images/RoxieAlias.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para></para>

    <?hard-pagebreak ?>

    <para>The following diagram shows an example of a system using
    aliases.</para>

    <figure>
      <!-- DNT-Start --><title>Roxie Aliases in a Production Environment</title><!-- DNT-End -->

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../images/RoxieAliasDiagram.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 role="brk">
    <!-- DNT-Start --><title><emphasis role="bold">Command Line support</emphasis></title><!-- DNT-End -->

    <para>The ecl command line tool offers a means of copying queries from one
    Roxie to another. Typically, this means data and index files would be
    copied or accessed remotely following Roxie's configuration
    settings.</para>

    <para>The ecl command line tool provides an option to instruct Roxie to
    not copy files at the time of the query copy. This allows you to quickly
    copy a query without copying files.</para>

    <!-- DNT-Start --><programlisting>
ecl queries copy --no-files
     </programlisting><!-- DNT-End -->

    <para>This specifies to <!-- DNT-Start -->NOT<!-- DNT-End --> copy files referenced by the query being
    copied. The query cannot run until data is made available.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
