<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Creating_Example_Data">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Creating Example Data</emphasis></title>

  <sect2 id="Getting_Code_Files">
    <title>Getting Code Files</title>
  <para>All the example code for the <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis>
  is available for download from the HPCC Systems website from the same page
  that the PDF is available (<ulink
  url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/docs/learning-ecl">click here</ulink>).
  To make this code available for use in the ECL IDE, you simply:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Download the ECL_Code_Files.ZIP file.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>In the ECL IDE, highlight your "My Files" folder, right-click and
      select "Insert Folder" from the popup menu.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Name your new folder "ProgrammersGuide" (please note -- spaces are
      NOT allowed in your ECL repository folder names).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>In the ECL IDE, highlight your "ProgrammersGuide" folder,
      right-click and select "Locate File in Explorer" from the popup
      menu.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Extract all the files from the ECL_Code_Files.ZIP file into your
      new folder.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Generating_Files">
    <title>Generating Files</title>

  <para>The code that generates the example data used by all the
  <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis> articles is contained in a file
  named Gendata.ECL. You simply need to open that file in the ECL IDE (select
  <emphasis role="bold">File &gt; Open</emphasis> from the menu, select the
  Gendata.ECL file, and it will open in a Builder window) then press the
  <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button to generate the data files.
  The process takes a couple of minutes to run. Here is the code, fully
  explained.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Some_Constants">
    <title>Some Constants</title>

    <programlisting>IMPORT std;

P_Mult1 := 1000;
P_Mult2 := 1000;
TotalParents := P_Mult1 * P_Mult2;
TotalChildren := 5000000;</programlisting>

    <para>These constants define the numbers used to generate 1,000,000 parent
    records and 5,000,000 child records. By defining these once as attributes
    the code could be easily made to generate a smaller number of parent
    records (such as 10,000 by changing both multipliers from 1000 to 100).
    However, the code as written is designed for a maximum of 1,000,000 parent
    records and would have to be changed in several places to accommodate
    generating more. The number of child records can be changed either
    direction without any other changes to the code (although if pushed too
    far upward you may encounter runtime errors regarding the maximum variable
    record length for the nested child dataset). For the purposes of
    demonstrating the techniques in these <emphasis>Programmer's
    Guide</emphasis> articles, 1,000,000 parent and 5,000,000 child records
    are more than sufficient.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="The_RECORD_Structures">
    <title>The RECORD Structures</title>

    <programlisting>Layout_Person := RECORD
  UNSIGNED3 PersonID;
  STRING15  FirstName;
  STRING25  LastName;
  STRING1   MiddleInitial;
  STRING1   Gender;
  STRING42  Street;
  STRING20  City;
  STRING2   State;
  STRING5   Zip;
END;

Layout_Accounts := RECORD
  STRING20  Account;
  STRING8   OpenDate;
  STRING2   IndustryCode;
  STRING1   AcctType;
  STRING1   AcctRate;
  UNSIGNED1 Code1;
  UNSIGNED1 Code2;
  UNSIGNED4 HighCredit;
  UNSIGNED4 Balance;
END;

Layout_Accounts_Link := RECORD
  UNSIGNED3 PersonID;
  Layout_Accounts;
END;

Layout_Combined := RECORD,MAXLENGTH(1000)
  Layout_Person;
  DATASET(Layout_Accounts) Accounts;
END;
</programlisting>

    <para>These RECORD structures define the field layouts for three datasets:
    a parent file (Layout_Person), a child file (Layout_Accounts_Link), and a
    parent with nested child dataset (Layout_Combined). These are used to
    generate three separate data files. The Layout_Accounts_Link and
    Layout_Accounts structures are separate because the child records in the
    nested structure will not contain the linking field to the parent, whereas
    the separate child file must contain the link.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Starting_Point_Data">
    <title>Starting Point Data</title>

    <programlisting>//define data for record generation:
             //100 possible middle initials, 52 letters and 48 blanks
SetMiddleInitials := 'ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ                  ' +
                     'ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ                  ';

             //1000 First names
SET OF STRING14     SetFnames := [
  'TIMTOHY       ','ALCIAN        ','CHAMENE       ',
  ... ];

            //1000 Last names
SET OF STRING16 SetLnames := [
  'BIALES          ','COOLING         ','CROTHALL        ',      
  ... ];
</programlisting>

    <para>These sets define the data that will be used to generate the
    records. By providing 1,000 first and last names, this code can generate
    1,000,000 unique names.</para>

    <para><programlisting>          //2400 street addresses to choose from
SET OF STRING31    SetStreets := [
     '1 SANDHURST DR                 ','1 SPENCER LN              ',
     ... ];

         //Matched sets of 9540 City,State, Zips
SET OF STRING15 SetCity := [
     'ABBEVILLE      ','ABBOTTSTOWN    ','ABELL          ',
     ... ];

SET OF STRING2 SetStates := [
     'LA','PA','MD','NC','MD','TX','TX','IL','MA','LA','WI','NJ',
     ... ];

SET OF STRING5 SetZips := [
     '70510','17301','20606','28315','21005','79311','79604',
     ... ];
</programlisting>Having 2400 street addresses and 9540 (valid) city, state,
    zip combinations provides plenty of opportunity to generate a reasonable
    mix of addresses.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Generating_Parent_Records">
    <title>Generating Parent Records</title>

    <programlisting>BlankSet := DATASET([{0,'','','','','','','','',[]}],
                   Layout_Combined);
CountCSZ := 9540;</programlisting>

    <para>Here is the beginning of the data generation code. The BlankSet is a
    single empty “seed” record, used to start the process. The CountCSZ
    attribute simply defines the maximum number of city, state, zip
    combinations that are available for use in subsequent calculations that
    will determine which to use in a given record.</para>

    <programlisting>Layout_Combined CreateRecs(Layout_Combined L,
                           INTEGER C,
                           INTEGER W) := TRANSFORM
  SELF.FirstName := IF(W=1,SetFnames[C],L.FirstName);
  SELF.LastName  := IF(W=2,SetLnames[C],L.LastName);
  SELF := L;
END;

base_fn  := NORMALIZE(BlankSet,P_Mult1,CreateRecs(LEFT,COUNTER,1));

base_fln := NORMALIZE(base_fn ,P_Mult2,CreateRecs(LEFT,COUNTER,2));
</programlisting>

    <para>The purpose of this code is to generate 1,000,000 unique first/last
    name records as a starting point. The NORMALIZE operation is unique in
    that its second parameter defines the number of times to call the
    TRANSFORM function for each input record. This makes it uniquely suited to
    generating the kind of “bogus” data we need.</para>

    <para>We're doing two NORMALIZE operations here. The first generates 1,000
    records with unique first names from the single blank record in the
    BlankSet inline DATASET. Then the second takes the 1,000 records from the
    first NORMALIZE and creates 1,000 new records with unique last names for
    each input record, resulting in 1,000,000 unique first/last name
    records.</para>

    <para>One interesting “trick” here is the use of a single TRANSFORM
    function for both of the NORMALIZE operations. Defining the TRANSFORM to
    receive one “extra” (third) parameter than it normally takes is what
    allows this. This parameter simply flags which NORMALIZE pass the
    TRANSFORM is doing.</para>

    <programlisting>Layout_Combined PopulateRecs(Layout_Combined L, 
          Layout_Combined R,
          INTEGER HashVal) := TRANSFORM
  CSZ_Rec            := (HashVal % CountCSZ) + 1;
  SELF.PersonID      := IF(L.PersonID = 0,
                           Thorlib.Node() + 1,
                           L.PersonID + CLUSTERSIZE);
  SELF.MiddleInitial := SetMiddleInitials[(HashVal % 100) + 1 ];
  SELF.Gender        := CHOOSE((HashVal % 2) + 1,'F','M');
  SELF.Street        := SetStreets[(HashVal % 2400) + 1 ];
  SELF.City          := SetCity[CSZ_Rec];
  SELF.State         := SetStates[CSZ_Rec];
  SELF.Zip           := SetZips[CSZ_Rec];
  SELF               := R;
END;

base_fln_dist := DISTRIBUTE(base_fln,HASH32(FirstName,LastName));

base_people   := ITERATE(base_fln_dist,
                         PopulateRecs(LEFT,
                         RIGHT,
                         HASHCRC(RIGHT.FirstName,RIGHT.LastName)),
                         LOCAL);

base_people_dist := DISTRIBUTE(base_people,HASH32(PersonID));
</programlisting>

    <para>Once the two NORMALIZE operations have done their work, the next
    task is to populate the rest of the fields. Since one of those fields is
    the PersonID, which is the unique identifier field for the record, the
    fastest way to populate it is with ITERATE using the LOCAL option. Using
    the Thorlib.Node() function and CLUSTERSIZE compiler directive, you can
    uniquely number each record in parallel on each node with ITERATE. You may
    end up with a few holes in the numbering towards the end, but since the
    only requirement here is uniqueness and not contiguity, those holes are
    irrelevant. Since the first two NORMALIZE operations took place on a
    single node (look at the data skews shown in the ECL Watch graph), the
    first thing to do is DISTRIBUTE the records so each node has a
    proportional chunk of the data to work with. Then the ITERATE can do its
    work on each chunk of records in parallel.</para>

    <para>To introduce an element of randomity to the data choices, the
    ITERATE passes a hash value to the TRANSFORM function as an “extra” third
    parameter. This is the same technique used previously, but passing
    calculated values instead of constants.</para>

    <para>The CSZ_Rec attribute definition illustrates the use of local
    attribute definitions inside TRANSFORM functions. Defining the expression
    once, then using it multiple times as needed to produce a valid city,
    state, zip combination. The rest of the fields are populated by data
    selected using the passed in hash value in their expressions. The modulus
    division operator (%—produces the remainder of the division) is used to
    ensure that a value is calculated that is in the valid range of the number
    of elements for the given set of data from which the field is
    populated.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Generating_Child_Records">
    <title>Generating Child Records</title>

    <programlisting>BlankKids := DATASET([{0,'','','','','',0,0,0,0}],
          Layout_Accounts_Link);

SetLinks  := SET(base_people,PersonID);

SetIndustryCodes := ['BB','DC','ON','FM','FP','FF','FC','FA','FZ',
                     'CG','FS','OC','ZZ','HZ','UT','HF','CS','DM',
                     'JA','FY','HT','UE','DZ','AT'];

SetAcctRates := ['1','0','9','*','Z','5','B','2',
                 '3','4','A','7','8','E','C'];

SetDateYears := ['1987','1988','1989','1990','1991','1992','1993',
                 '1994','1995','1996','1997','1998','1999','2000',
                 '2001','2002','2003','2004','2005','2006'];

SetMonthDays := [31,28,31,30,31,30,31,31,30,31,30,31];

SetNarrs     := [229,158,2,0,66,233,123,214,169,248,67,127,168,
                 65,208,114,73,218,238,57,125,113,88,
                 247,244,121,54,220,98,97];
</programlisting>

    <para>Once again, we start by defining a “seed” record for the process as
    an inline DATASET and several sets of appropriate data for the specific
    fields. The SET function builds a set of valid PersonID values to use to
    create the links between the parent and child records.</para>

    <programlisting>Layout_Accounts_Link CreateKids(Layout_Accounts_Link L,
                                INTEGER C) := TRANSFORM
  CSZ_IDX       := C % CountCSZ + 1;
  HashVal       := HASH32(SetCity[CSZ_IDX],SetStates[CSZ_IDX],SetZips[CSZ_IDX]);
  DateMonth     := HashVal % 12 + 1;
  SELF.PersonID := CHOOSE(TRUNCATE(C / TotalParents ) + 1,
                          IF(C % 2 = 0,
                             SetLinks[C % TotalParents  + 1],
                             SetLinks[TotalParents - (C % TotalParents )]),
                          IF(C % 3 &lt;&gt; 0,
                             SetLinks[C % TotalParents  + 1],
                             SetLinks[TotalParents  - (C % TotalParents )]),
                          IF(C % 5 = 0,
                             SetLinks[C % TotalParents  + 1],
                             SetLinks[TotalParents  - (C % TotalParents )]),
                          IF(C % 7 &lt;&gt; 0,
                             SetLinks[C % TotalParents  + 1],
                             SetLinks[TotalParents  - (C % TotalParents )]),
                          SetLinks[C % TotalParents  + 1]);
 SELF.Account      := (STRING)HashVal;
 SELF.OpenDate     := SetDateYears[DateMonth] + INTFORMAT(DateMonth,2,1) + 
                          INTFORMAT(HashVal % SetMonthDays[DateMonth]+1,2,1);
 SELF.IndustryCode := SetIndustrycodes[HashVal % 24 + 1];
 SELF.AcctType     := CHOOSE(HashVal%5+1,'O','R','I','9',' ');
 SELF.AcctRate     := SetAcctRates[HashVal % 15 + 1];
 SELF.Code1        := SetNarrs[HashVal % 15 + 1];
 SELF.Code2        := SetNarrs[HashVal % 15 + 16];
 SELF.HighCredit   := HashVal % 50000;
 SELF.Balance      := TRUNCATE((HashVal % 50000) * ((HashVal % 100 + 1) / 100));
END;

base_kids := NORMALIZE( BlankKids,
                        TotalChildren,
                        CreateKids(LEFT,COUNTER));
base_kids_dist := DISTRIBUTE(base_kids,HASH32(PersonID));
</programlisting>

    <para>This process is similar to the one used for the parent records. This
    time, instead of passing in a hash value, a local attribute does that work
    inside the TRANSFORM. Just as before, the hash value is used to select the
    actual data to go in each field of the record.</para>

    <para>The interesting bit here is the expression to determine the PersonID
    field value. Since we're generating 5,000,000 child records it would be
    very simple to just give each parent five children. However, real-world
    data rarely looks like that. Therefore, the CHOOSE function is used to
    select a different method for each set of a million child records. The
    first million uses the first IF expression, and the second million uses
    the second, and so on... This creates a varying number of children for
    each parent, ranging from one to nine.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Create_the_Nested_Child-Dataset_Records">
    <title>Create the Nested Child Dataset Records</title>

    <programlisting>Layout_Combined AddKids(Layout_Combined L, base_kids R) := TRANSFORM
  SELF.Accounts := L.Accounts + 
     ROW({R.Account,R.OpenDate,R.IndustryCode,
     R.AcctType,R.AcctRate,R.Code1,
     R.Code2,R.HighCredit,R.Balance},
         Layout_Accounts);
  SELF := L;
END;
base_combined := DENORMALIZE( base_people_dist, 
    base_kids_dist, 
    LEFT.PersonID = RIGHT.PersonID,
    AddKids(LEFT, RIGHT));
</programlisting>

    <para>Now that we have separate recordsets of parent and child records,
    the next step is to combine them into a single dataset with each parent's
    child data nested within the same physical record as the parent. The
    reason for nesting the child data this way is to allow easy parent-child
    queries in the Data Refinery and Rapid data Delivery Engine without
    requiring the use of separate JOIN steps to make the links between the
    parent and child records.</para>

    <para>To build the nested child dataset requires the DENORMALIZE
    operation. This operation finds the links between the parent records and
    their associated children, calling the TRANSFORM function as many times as
    there are child records for each parent. The interesting technique here is
    the use of the ROW function to construct each additional nested child
    record. This is done to eliminate the linking field (PersonID) from each
    child record stored in the combined dataset, since it is the same value as
    contained in the parent record's PersonID field.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Write_Files_to_Disk">
    <title>Write Files to Disk</title>

    <programlisting>O1 := OUTPUT(PROJECT(base_people_dist,Layout_Person),,'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::People',OVERWRITE);

O2 := OUTPUT(base_kids_dist,,'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::Accounts',OVERWRITE);

O3 := OUTPUT(base_combined,,'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::PeopleAccts',OVERWRITE);

P1 := PARALLEL(O1,O2,O3);
</programlisting>

    <para>These OUTPUT attribute definitions will write the datasets to disk.
    They are written as attribute definitions because they will be used in a
    SEQUENTIAL action. The PARALLEL action attribute simply indicates that all
    these disk writes can occur “simultaneously” if the optimizer decides it
    can do that.</para>

    <para>The first OUTPUT uses a PROJECT to produce the parent records as a
    separate file because the data was originally generated into a RECORD
    structure that contains the nested child DATASET field (Accounts) in
    preparation for creating the third file. The PROJECT eliminates that empty
    Accounts field from the output for this dataset.</para>

    <programlisting>D1 := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::People',
              {Layout_Person,UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}}, THOR);

D2 := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::Accounts',
              {Layout_Accounts_Link,UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}},THOR);

D3 := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::PeopleAccts',
              {,MAXLENGTH(1000) Layout_Combined,UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}},THOR);
</programlisting>

    <para>These DATASET declarations are needed to be able to build indexes.
    The UNSIGNED8 RecPos fields are the virtual fields (they only exist at
    runtime and not on disk) that are the internal record pointers. They're
    declared here to be able to reference them in the subsequent INDEX
    declarations.</para>

    <programlisting>I1 := INDEX(D1,{PersonID,RecPos},'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::People.PersonID');

I2 := INDEX(D2,{PersonID,RecPos},'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::Accounts.PersonID');

I3 := INDEX(D3,{PersonID,RecPos},'~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::PeopleAccts.PersonID');

B1 := BUILD(I1,OVERWRITE);
B2 := BUILD(I2,OVERWRITE);
B3 := BUILD(I3,OVERWRITE);

P2 := PARALLEL(B1,B2,B3);
</programlisting>

    <para>These INDEX declarations allow the BUILD actions to use the
    single-parameter form. Once again, the PARALLEL action attribute indicates
    the index build may be done all at the same time.</para>

    <programlisting>SEQUENTIAL(P1,P2);</programlisting>

    <para>This SEQUENTIAL action simply says, “write all the data files to
    disk, and then build the indexes.”</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Adding_the_Files-to_the_Repository">
    <title>Defining the Files</title>

    <para>Once the datasets and indexes have been written to disk you must
    declare the files in order to use them in the example ECL code in the rest
    of the articles. These declarations are contained in the DeclareData.ECL
    file. To make them available to the rest of the example code you simply
    need to IMPORT it. Therefore, at the beginning of each example you will
    find this line of code:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;</programlisting>

    <para>This IMPORTs all the files in the ProgrammersGuide folder (including
    the DeclareData MODULE structure definition). Referencing anything from
    DeclareData is done by prepending $.DeclareData to the name of the EXPORT
    definition you need to use, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile := $.DeclareData.Person.File;  //rename $DeclareData.Person.File to MyFile to make 
                                      //subsequent code simpler</programlisting>

    <para>Here is some of the code contained in the DeclareData.ECL
    file:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT DeclareData := MODULE

  EXPORT Layout_Person := RECORD
    UNSIGNED3 PersonID;
    STRING15  FirstName;
    STRING25  LastName;
    STRING1   MiddleInitial;
    STRING1   Gender;
    STRING42  Street;
    STRING20  City;
    STRING2   State;
    STRING5   Zip;
  END;

  EXPORT Layout_Accounts := RECORD
    STRING20   Account;
    STRING8    OpenDate;
    STRING2    IndustryCode;
    STRING1    AcctType;
    STRING1    AcctRate;
    UNSIGNED1  Code1;
    UNSIGNED1  Code2;
    UNSIGNED4  HighCredit;
    UNSIGNED4  Balance;
  END;

  EXPORT Layout_Accounts_Link := RECORD
    UNSIGNED3 PersonID;
    Layout_Accounts;
  END;

  SHARED Layout_Combined := RECORD,MAXLENGTH(1000)
    Layout_Person;
    DATASET(Layout_Accounts) Accounts;
  END;

  EXPORT Person := MODULE
    EXPORT File     := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::People',Layout_Person, THOR);
    EXPORT FilePlus := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::People',
                               {Layout_Person,UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}}, THOR);
  END;                                        
  EXPORT Accounts := DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::Accounts',
                             {Layout_Accounts_Link,
                              UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}}, 
                             THOR);
  EXPORT PersonAccounts:=   DATASET('~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::PeopleAccts',
                                    {Layout_Combined,
                                     UNSIGNED8 RecPos{virtual(fileposition)}}, 
                                     THOR);

  EXPORT IDX_Person_PersonID := 
  INDEX(Person,
        {PersonID,RecPos},
        '~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::People.PersonID');

  EXPORT IDX_Accounts_PersonID := 
  INDEX(Accounts,
        {PersonID,RecPos},
        '~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::Accounts.PersonID');

  EXPORT IDX_PersonAccounts_PersonID := 
  INDEX(PersonAccounts,
        {PersonID,RecPos},
        '~PROGGUIDE::EXAMPLEDATA::KEYS::PeopleAccts.PersonID');

END;
</programlisting>

    <para>By using a MODULE structure as a container, all the DATASET and
    INDEX declarations are in a single attribute editor window. This makes
    maintenance and update simple while allowing complete access to them
    all.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
