<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Roxie_Overview" role="nobrk">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Roxie Overview</emphasis></title>

  <para>Let's start with some definitions:</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" colwidth="87.45pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Thor</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>An HPCC cluster specifically designed to perform massive
            data manipulation (ETL) processes. This is a back-office data
            preparation tool and not meant for end-user production-level
            queries. See the HPCC operational manuals for complete
            documentation.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Roxie</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>An HPCC cluster specifically designed to service standard
            queries, providing a throughput rate of a thousand-plus responses
            per second (actual response rate for any given query is, of
            course, dependent on its complexity). This is a production-level
            tool designed for mission-critical application. See the HPCC
            operational manuals for complete documentation.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">hThor</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>An R&amp;D platform designed for iterative, interactive
            development and testing of Roxie queries. This is not a separate
            cluster, but a “piggyback” implementation of ECL Agent and Thor.
            See the HPCC operational manuals for complete
            documentation.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <sect2 id="Thor">
    <title>Thor</title>

    <para>Thor clusters are used to do all the “heavy lifting” data
    preparation work to process raw data into standard formats. Once that
    process is complete, end-users can query that standardized data to glean
    real information. However, end-users typically want to see their results
    “immediately or sooner”—and usually more than one end-user wants their
    result at the same time. The Thor platform only works on one query at a
    time, which makes it impractical for use by end-users, and that is why the
    Roxie platform was created.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Roxie">
    <title>Roxie</title>

    <para>Roxie clusters can handle thousands of simultaneous end-users and
    provide them all with the perception of “immediately or sooner” results.
    It does this by only allowing end-users to run standard, pre-compiled
    queries that have been developed specifically for end-user use on the
    Roxie cluster. Typically, these queries use indexes and thus, provide
    extremely fast performance. However, the Roxie cluster is impractical for
    use as a development tool, since all its queries must be pre-compiled and
    the data they use must have been previously deployed. Therefore, the
    iterative query development and testing process is performed using
    Doxie.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Doxie">
    <title>hThor</title>

    <para>hThor is not a separate cluster on its own; it is an instance of ECL
    Agent (which operates on a single server) that emulates the operation of a
    Roxie cluster. Just as with Thor queries, hThor queries are compiled each
    time they are run. hThor queries access data directly from an associated
    Thor cluster's disk drives without interfering with any Thor operations.
    This makes it an appropriate tool for developing queries that are destined
    for use on a Roxie cluster.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="How_to_Structure_Roxie_Queries">
    <title>How to Structure Roxie Queries</title>

    <para>To begin developing queries for use on Roxie clusters you must start
    by deciding what data to query and how to index that data so that
    end-users see their result in minimum time. The process of putting the
    data into its most useful form and indexing it is accomplished on a Thor
    cluster. The previous articles on indexing and superfiles should guide you
    in the right direction for that.</para>

    <para>Once the data is ready to use, you can then write the query. Queries
    for Roxie clusters always contain at least one action—usually a simple
    OUTPUT to return the result set.</para>

    <para>Roxie queries use either a SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol) or
    JSON (JavaScript Object Notation) interface to “pass in” data values. The
    values passed through the interface wind up in definitions with the STORED
    workflow service. Your ECL code then can use those definitions to
    determine the passed values and return the appropriate result to the
    end-user.</para>

    <para>Here is a simple example of the structure of a Roxie query
    (contained in RoxieOverview1.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;

EXPORT RoxieOverview1 := FUNCTION

STRING30 lname_value := '' : STORED('LastName');
STRING30 fname_value := '' : STORED('FirstName');

IDX  := $.DeclareData.IDX__Person_LastName_FirstName;
Base := $.DeclareData.Person.FilePlus;

Fetched := IF(fname_value = '', 
              FETCH(Base, IDX(LastName=lname_value), RIGHT.RecPos),
              FETCH(Base, IDX(LastName=lname_value, FirstName=fname_value), RIGHT.RecPos));

RETURN OUTPUT(CHOOSEN(Fetched,2000));

END;</programlisting>

    <para>Notice that the FUNCTION does not receive any parameters. Instead,
    the lname_value and fname_value definitions both have the STORED workflow
    service that supply storage names. The SOAP/JSON interface uses the
    storage names to pass in values, because the STORED option opens up a
    storage space in the workunit where the interface can place the values to
    pass to the service.</para>

    <para>This code uses FETCH because it is the simplest example of using an
    INDEX in ECL. More typically, Roxie queries use half-keyed JOIN operations
    with payload keys (the <emphasis>Complex Roxie Queries</emphasis> article
    addresses this issue). Note that the OUTPUT contains a CHOOSEN as a simple
    example of how to ensure you limit the maximum amount of data that can be
    returned from the query to some “reasonable” amount—it doesn't make much
    sense to have a Roxie query that could possibly return 10 billion records
    to an end-user's PC (anybody actually needing that much data should be
    working in Thor, not Roxie).</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Testing_Queries_with_Doxie">
    <title>Testing Queries</title>

    <para>Once you have written your query you naturally need to test it.
    That's where hThor comes into play. hThor is an interactive test system
    that you can use before deploying your queries to Roxie. The easiest way
    to describe the process is to walk through it using this simple example
    query.</para>

    <para>1. Open the Samples\ProgrammersGuide\RoxieOverview1.ECL file</para>

    <para>Now you're ready to publish this query to hThor.</para>

    <para>2. Select "hthor" on the Target drop list</para>

    <para>3. Click the down arrow on the Submit button and select
    Compile</para>

    <para>4. Open the compiled workunit and select the ECL Watch tab</para>

    <para>5. Press the Publish button</para>

    <para>Open the ECL Watch web page (not using the ECL IDE — open it in
    Internet Explorer). The IP for ECL Watch is the same as the IP you used to
    configure the ECL IDE to access the environment you're working in. The
    Port is 8010.</para>

    <para>6. Click on <emphasis role="underline">System Servers</emphasis>
    (it's in the Topology section)</para>

    <para>7. Find the <emphasis role="bold">ESP Servers</emphasis>
    section</para>

    <para>8. Click on the ESP server's name link to display its list of
    services and their ports</para>

    <para>9. Note the port number beside the <emphasis
    role="bold">wsecl</emphasis> Service Type (this is usually 8002, but it
    could be set to something else)</para>

    <para>Once you've know the IP and port for your wsecl service (the service
    that makes hthor "pretend" to be a Roxie), you can go there and run the
    query.</para>

    <para>10. The easy way is to right-click on the wsecl link and open it in
    a new tab or window (or you can Edit Internet Explorer's address bar to
    point to the correct IP:port</para>

    <para>11. Press the Enter key</para>

    <para>A login dialog may appear—your login ID and password are the same as
    the ones you use for the ECL IDE. After you've logged in, you'll see a
    tree list of QuerySets on the left.</para>

    <para>12. Click on the <emphasis role="underline">hthor</emphasis>
    branch</para>

    <para>A list of all the Queries published to your hthor appears in the
    tree. In this case, there's only the one.</para>

    <para>13. Click on the <emphasis
    role="underline">RoxieOverview1.1</emphasis> branch</para>

    <para>A web page containing two entry controls and a <emphasis
    role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button appears.</para>

    <para>14. Type in any last name from the set of last names that were used
    by the code in GenData.ECL to generate the data files for this
    <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis></para>

    <para>COOLING is a good example to use. Note that, since this is an
    extremely simple example, you'll need to type it in ALL CAPS, otherwise
    the FETCH will fail to find any matching records (this is only due to the
    simplicity of this ECL code and not any inherent lack in the
    system).</para>

    <para>15. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button</para>

    <para>Queries are pre-compiled when you Publish, so after a second you
    should see an XML result with 1,000 records in it.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Deploying_Queries_to_Roxie">
    <title>Deploying Queries to Roxie</title>

    <para>Once you've done enough testing on hThor to be sure the query does
    what you expect it to do, the only step then required is to deploy it to
    Roxie and test it there, too (just to be completely certain that
    everything operates the way it should). Once you've tested it on Roxie,
    you can inform the users that the query is available for their use.</para>

    <para>The Roxie deployment process is done the same way we just did for
    hThor, except the Target drop list has to be set to Roxie.</para>

    <para>Once you've deployed the query, you can test it the same way you
    tested it on hThor, except the new service will appear under your Roxie in
    the tree list.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Restrictions">
    <title>Restrictions</title>

    <para>Roxie queries may <emphasis role="underline">not</emphasis> contain
    any code that would write a file to disk, such as:</para>

    <para>OUTPUT actions that write to disk files</para>

    <para>BUILD (or BUILDINDEX) actions</para>

    <para>PERSISTed attributes</para>

    <para></para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
