<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Query_Libraries">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Query Libraries</emphasis></title>

  <para>A Query Library is a set of attributes, packaged together in a self
  contained unit, which allows the code to be shared between different
  workunits. This reduces the time required to deploy a set of attributes, and
  can reduce the memory footprint for the set of queries within Roxie that use
  the library. It is also possible to update a query library without having to
  re-deploy all the queries that use it.</para>

  <para>Query libraries are not supported in Thor, but may be in the
  future.</para>

  <para>A Query Library is defined by two structures—an INTERFACE to define
  the parameters to pass, and a MODULE that implements the INTERFACE.</para>

  <sect2 id="Library_INTERFACE_Definition">
    <title>Library INTERFACE Definition</title>

    <para>To create a Query Library, the first requirement is a definition of
    its input parameters with an INTERFACE structure that receives the
    parameters:</para>

    <programlisting>NamesRec := RECORD
  INTEGER1  NameID;
  STRING20  FName;
  STRING20  LName;
END;
     
FilterLibIface1(DATASET(namesRec) ds, STRING search) := INTERFACE
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) matches;
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) others;
END;</programlisting>

    <para>This example defines the INTERFACE for a library that takes two
    inputs—a DATASET (with the specified layout format) and a STRING—and which
    gives you the ability to output two DATASET results.</para>

    <para>For most library queries it may be preferable to also use a separate
    INTERFACE to define the input parameters. Using an INTERFACE makes the
    passed parameters clearer and makes it easier to keep the interface and
    implementation in sync. This example defines the same library interface as
    above:</para>

    <programlisting>NamesRec := RECORD
    INTEGER1  NameID;
    STRING20  FName;
    STRING20  LName;
END;

IFilterArgs := INTERFACE //defines passed parameters
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) ds;
  EXPORT STRING search;
END;
FilterLibIface2(IFilterArgs args) := INTERFACE
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) matches;
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) others;
END;</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Library_MODULE_Definitions">
    <title>Library MODULE Definitions</title>

    <para>A query library is a MODULE structure definition that implements a
    particular library INTERFACE definition. The parameters passed to the
    MODULE must exactly match the parameters for the library INTERFACE
    definition, and the MODULE must contain compatible EXPORT attribute
    definitions for each of the results specified in the library INTERFACE.
    The LIBRARY option on the MODULE definition specifies the library
    INTERFACE being implemented. This example defines an implementation for
    the INTERFACEs above:</para>

    <programlisting>FilterDsLib1(DATASET(namesRec) ds,
             STRING search) := MODULE,LIBRARY(FilterLibIface1)
  EXPORT matches := ds(Lname = search);
  EXPORT others := ds(Lname != search);
END;</programlisting>

    <para>and for the variety that takes an INTERFACE as its single
    parameter:</para>

    <programlisting>FilterDsLib2(IFilterArgs args) := MODULE,LIBRARY(FilterLibIface2)
  EXPORT matches := args.ds(Lname = args.search);
  EXPORT others := args.ds(Lname != args.search);
END;</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Building_an_External_library">
    <title>Building an External library</title>

    <para>A query library may be either internal or external. An internal
    library would be primarily used in hthor queries for testing and debugging
    before deploying to Roxie. Although you can use internal query libraries
    in Roxie queries, the advantages come from using the external
    version.</para>

    <para>An external query library is created by the BUILD action, which
    compiles the query library into its own workunit. The name of the library
    is the job name associated with the workunit. Therefore, the #WORKUNIT
    would normally be used to give the workunit a meaningful job name, as in
    this example:</para>

    <programlisting>#WORKUNIT('name','Ppass.FilterDsLib');
BUILD(FilterDsLib1);</programlisting>

    <para>This code builds the library for the INTERFACE parameter version of
    the code above:</para>

    <programlisting>#WORKUNIT('name','Ipass.FilterDsLib');
BUILD(FilterDsLib2);</programlisting>

    <para>The system maintains a catalog of the latest versions of each query
    library that is updated whenever a library is built. Hthor uses this to
    resolve query libraries when running a query (as will Thor, when it
    eventually supports query libraries). Roxie uses the query aliasing
    mechanism in the same way.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Using_a_Query_Library">
    <title>Using a Query Library</title>

    <para>The syntax for using a query library is slightly different depending
    on whether the library is internal or external. However, both methods use
    the LIBRARY function.</para>

    <para>The LIBRARY function returns a MODULE implementation with the proper
    parameters passed for the instance in which you want to use it, which may
    be used to access the EXPORT attributes from the library.</para>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_InternalLibraries">
      <title id="RoxieQueryLibrary_InternalLibraries">Internal
      Libraries</title>

      <para>An internal library generates the library code as a separate unit,
      but then includes that unit within the query workunit. It doesn't have
      the advantage of reducing compile time or memory usage in Roxie, but it
      does retain the library structure, which means that changes to the code
      cannot affect anyone else using the system. That makes internal
      libraries a perfect testing method.</para>

      <para>The syntax for using an internal query library simply passes the
      library MODULE attribute's name inside an INTERNAL function call in the
      first parameter to the LIBRARY function, as in this example (for the
      version that does not take an INTERFACE as its parameter):</para>

      <programlisting>NamesTable := DATASET([ {1,'Doc','Holliday'},
                        {2,'Liz','Taylor'},
                        {3,'Mr','Nobody'},
                        {4,'Anywhere','but here'}],
                      NamesRec);
lib1 := LIBRARY(INTERNAL(FilterDsLib1),FilterLibIface1(NamesTable, 'Holliday'));
</programlisting>

      <para>In this case, result is a MODULE with two EXPORTed
      attributes—matches and others—that can be used just like any other
      MODULE, as in this example:</para>

      <programlisting>OUTPUT(lib1.matches);
OUTPUT(lib1.others);</programlisting>

      <para>and the code changes to this for the variety that takes an
      INTERFACE:</para>

      <programlisting>NamesTable := DATASET([ {1,'Doc','Holliday'},
                        {2,'Liz','Taylor'},
                        {3,'Mr','Nobody'},
                        {4,'Anywhere','but here'}],
                      NamesRec);
SearchArgs := MODULE(IFilterArgs)
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) ds := NamesTable;
  EXPORT STRING search := 'Holliday';
END;
lib3 := LIBRARY(INTERNAL(FilterDsLib2),FilterLibIface2(SearchArgs));
OUTPUT(lib3.matches);
OUTPUT(lib3.others);</programlisting>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_ExternalLibraries">
      <title><emphasis role="bold">External Libraries</emphasis></title>

      <para>Once the library is implemented as an external library (using the
      BUILD action to create the library is done in a separate workunit) the
      LIBRARY function no longer requires the use of the INTERNAL function to
      specify the library. Instead, it takes a string constant containing the
      name of the workunit created by BUILD as its first parameter, like
      this:</para>

      <programlisting>NamesTable := DATASET([ {1,'Doc','Holliday'},
                        {2,'Liz','Taylor'},
                        {3,'Mr','Nobody'},
                        {4,'Anywhere','but here'}],
                    NamesRec);
lib2 := LIBRARY('Ppass.FilterDsLib',FilterLibIface1(NamesTable, 'Holliday'));
OUTPUT(lib2.matches);
OUTPUT(lib2.others);</programlisting>

      <para>Or, for the INTERFACE version:</para>

      <programlisting>NamesTable := DATASET([ {1,'Doc','Holliday'},
                        {2,'Liz','Taylor'},
                        {3,'Mr','Nobody'},
                        {4,'Anywhere','but here'}],
                     NamesRec);
  
SearchArgs := MODULE(IFilterArgs)
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) ds := NamesTable;
  EXPORT STRING search := 'Holliday';
END;
      
lib4 := LIBRARY('Ipass.FilterDsLib',FilterLibIface2(SearchArgs));
OUTPUT(lib4.matches);
OUTPUT(lib4.others);
</programlisting>

      <para>A couple of words of warning about using external libraries: If
      you are developing an attribute inside a library that is shared by other
      people, then you need to make sure that your development changes don't
      invalidate other queries. This means you need to use a different library
      name while developing. The simplest method is probably to use a
      different attribute for the library implementation while you are
      developing. Another way to avoid this is to develop/test with internal
      libraries and only build and implement the external library when you are
      ready to put the query into production.</para>

      <para>If libraries are nested then it gets more complicated. If you are
      working on a libraryC, which is called from a libraryA, which is then
      called from a query, then you will need to use different library names
      for libraryC and libraryA. Otherwise you will either not call your
      modified code in libraryC, or everyone using libraryA will call your
      modified code. You may prefer to make libraryA and libraryC internal
      instead, but you won't gain from the reduced compile time associated
      with external libraries.</para>

      <para>Also remember your changes are occurring in the library, not in
      the query. It's not uncommon to wonder why changes to the ECL aren't
      having any effect, and then realize that you've been
      rebuilding/deploying the wrong item.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Query_Library_Tips">
    <title>Query Library Tips</title>

    <para>You can make your code cleaner by making the LIBRARY call a function
    attribute, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>FilterDataset(DATASET(namesRecord) ds,
              STRING search) := LIBRARY('Ppass.FilterDsLib',FilterLibIface1(ds, search));
</programlisting>

    <para>The use of the library then becomes:</para>

    <programlisting>FilterDataset(myNames, 'Holliday');</programlisting>

    <para>The library name (specified as the first parameter to the LIBRARY
    function) does not have to be a constant value, but it must not change
    while the query is running. This means you can conditionally select
    between different versions of a library.</para>

    <para>For example, it is likely that you will want separate libraries for
    handling FCRA and non-FCRA data, since combining the two could generate
    inefficient or un-processable code. The code for selecting between the two
    implementations would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>LibToUse := IF(isFCRA,'special.lookupFRCA','special.lookupNoFCRA);
MyResults := LIBRARY(LibToUse, InterfaceCommonToBoth(args));
</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Query_Library_Restrictions">
    <title>Restrictions</title>

    <para>The system will report an error if you attempt to use an
    implementation of a query library that has a different INTERFACE from the
    one specified in the LIBRARY function.</para>

    <para>There is one particularly notable restriction on the ECL that can be
    included within a library: they cannot include workflow services such as
    INDEPENDENT, PERSIST, SUCCESS, and especially, STORED. STORED attributes
    don't make sense inside a query library because a query library should be
    independent of both the queries that use it, and other query libraries.
    Instead of using STORED attributes (like SOAP-enabled Roxie queries use)
    to pass parameters to the library queries, the parameters must be
    explicitly passed into the query library—either as an individual
    parameter, or as part of an INTERFACE definition that provides the
    arguments. The query that uses the query library can use stored variables,
    and then map those stored variables to the parameters expected by the
    query libraries.</para>

    <para>Query libraries can currently only EXPORT datasets, datarows, and
    single-valued expressions. In particular they cannot EXPORT actions (like
    OUTPUT), TRANSFORM structures, or other MODULE structures.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Notes_on_the_implementation">
    <title>Notes on the implementation</title>

    <para>There are a couple of items that may be worth noting about the
    implementation. In Roxie, before executing the query, all library graphs
    are expanded into the query graph. Any datasets that are supplied as
    parameters to the library (or a dataset inside an interface parameter) are
    directly connected to the place they are used in the query library, and
    only results that are used are evaluated. This means that using a query
    library should have very little overhead compared with including the ECL
    code directly in the query. NOTE: Datasets inside row parameters aren't
    streamed, so passing a ROW containing a dataset as a parameter to the
    library is not as efficient as using an INTERFACE.</para>

    <para>The implementation in hthor is not as efficient. Dataset parameters
    are fully evaluated, and passed to the library as a complete unit block
    and all results are evaluated. Thor does not yet support query
    libraries.</para>

    <para>The other item of note is that if libraryA uses libraryC, and
    libraryB also uses libraryC with the same parameters, the calls from
    different libraries will not be commoned up. However if an attribute
    exported from an instance of libraryC is passed to libraryA and libraryB,
    then the calls to libraryC will be commoned up. The way attributes
    currently tend to be structured in the repository, e.g., calculating
    get_Dids() and passing that into other attributes means this is unlikely
    to cause any issues in practice.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Suggested_Structure">
    <title>Suggested Structure</title>

    <para>Before writing a lot of libraries, it is worth spending some time
    working out how the attributes for a library are structured, so all the
    libraries in the system are consistent. Here are some guidelines to use
    during your query library design phase:</para>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_SuggStructure_NamingConventions">
      <title>Naming Conventions</title>

      <para>I would also suggest coming up with a consistent naming convention
      before developing lots of libraries. In particular, you need a
      convention for the names of the library arguments, library definition,
      implementing module, library implementation and the attribute that wraps
      the use of the library. (E.g., something like IXArgs, Xinterface, DoX,
      Xlibrary, and X()).</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_SuggStructure_InterfaceToDefineParameters">
      <title>Use an INTERFACE to define parameters</title>

      <para>This mechanism (example shown below) provides documentation for
      the parameters required by a service. It means the code inside the
      implementation will access them as args.xxx or options.xxx, so it will
      be clear when parameters are being accessed. It also makes some of the
      following suggestions simpler.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_SuggStructure_HideTheLibrary">
      <title>Hide the LIBRARY</title>

      <para>Making the LIBRARY function call a functional attribute (example
      also shown below) means you can easily modify all uses of a library if
      you are developing a new version. Similarly you can easily switch to use
      an internal library instead by changing just the one line of
      code.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="RoxieQuery_SuggStructure_UseModuleInheritance">
      <title>Use MODULE Inheritance</title>

      <para>Use a MODULE structure (without the LIBRARY option) that
      implements the library's INTERFACE, and a separate MODULE derived from
      the first to implement the LIBRARY using that service module. By hiding
      the LIBRARY and using a separate MODULE implementation you can easily
      remove the library all together. Also, using a separate implementation
      from the library definitions means you can easily generate multiple
      variants of the same library from the same definition.</para>

      <programlisting>NamesRec := RECORD
    INTEGER1  NameID;
    STRING20  FName;
    STRING20  LName;
END;
NamesTable := DATASET([ {1,'Doc','Holliday'},
                        {2,'Liz','Taylor'},
                        {3,'Mr','Nobody'},
                        {4,'Anywhere','but here'}],
                      NamesRec);
      
 //define an INTERFACE for the passed parameters
IFilterArgs := INTERFACE
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) ds;
  EXPORT STRING search;
END;

 //then define an INTERFACE for the query library
FilterLibIface2(IFilterArgs args) := INTERFACE
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) matches;
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) others;
END;

 //implement the INTERFACE
FilterDsLib(IFilterArgs args) := MODULE
  EXPORT matches := args.ds(Lname = args.search);
  EXPORT others := args.ds(Lname != args.search);
END;

 //then derive that MODULE to implement the LIBRARY
FilterDsLib2(IFilterArgs args) := MODULE(FilterDsLib(args)),LIBRARY(FilterLibIface2)
END;

 //make the LIBRARY call a function
FilterDs(IFilterArgs args) := LIBRARY(INTERNAL(FilterDsLib2),FilterLibIface2(args));
 //easily modified to eliminate the LIBRARY, if desired
 // FilterDs(IFilterArgs args) := FilterDsLib2(args));
 //define the parameters to pass as the interface
SearchArgs := MODULE(IFilterArgs)
  EXPORT DATASET(namesRec) ds := NamesTable;
  EXPORT STRING search := 'Holliday';
END;
      
 //use the LIBRARY, passing the parameters
OUTPUT(FilterDs(SearchArgs).matches);
OUTPUT(FilterDs(SearchArgs).others);</programlisting>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
