<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Controlling_Roxie_Queries">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Controlling Roxie Queries</emphasis></title>

  <para>There are several ECL functions that are designed specifically to help
  optimize queries for execution on Roxie. These include PRELOAD, ALLNODES,
  THISNODE, LOCAL, and NOLOCAL. Understanding how all these functions work
  together can make a big difference in the performance of your Roxie
  queries.</para>

  <sect2 id="How_Graphs_Execute">
    <title>How Graphs Execute</title>

    <para>Writing efficient queries for Roxie or Thor can require an
    understanding of how the different clusters operate. This brings up three
    questions:</para>

    <para>How does the graph execute, on a single node, or on all nodes in
    parallel?</para>

    <para>How are datasets accessed by each node executing the graph, only the
    parts that are local to the node, or all parts on all nodes?</para>

    <para>Does an operation coordinate with the same operation on other nodes,
    or does each node operate independently?</para>

    <para>Here's how queries “normally” execute on each type of
    cluster:</para>

    <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="77.40pt" />

          <colspec />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Thor</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Graphs execute on multiple slave nodes in
              parallel.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Index/disk reads are done locally by each slave
              node.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>All other disk access (FETCH, keyed JOIN, etc.) are
              effectively accessed across all nodes.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Coordination with operations on other nodes is controlled
              by the presence or absence of the LOCAL option on the
              operation.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>No support for child queries (this may change in future
              releases).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">hthor</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Graphs execute on the single ECL Agent node.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>All parts of the dataset/index are accessed by directly
              accessing the disk drive of the node with the data—no other
              interaction with the other nodes.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Child queries always execute on same node as
              parent.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Roxie</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Graphs execute on a single (Roxie server) node.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>All parts of the dataset/index are accessed by directly
              accessing the disk drive of the node with the data—no other
              interaction with the other nodes.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Child queries might execute on a single agent node
              instead of a Roxie server node.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable></para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="ALLNODES_vs_THISNODE">
    <title>ALLNODES vs. THISNODE</title>

    <para>In Roxie, graphs execute on a single Roxie server node unless the
    ALLNODES() function is used. ALLNODES() causes the portion of the query it
    encloses to execute on all agent nodes in parallel. The results are
    calculated independently on each node then merged together, without
    ordering the records. It is generally used to do some complex remote
    processing which only requires local index access, substantially reducing
    the network traffic between the nodes.</para>

    <para>By default, everything within the ALLNODES() will be executed on all
    the nodes, but sometimes the ALLNODES() query requires some input or
    arguments that shouldn't be executed on all the nodes—for example, the
    previous best guess at the results, or some information controlling the
    parallel query. The THISNODE() function can be used to surround element
    that are to be evaluated by the current node instead.</para>

    <para>A typical usage would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>bestSearchResults := ALLNODES(doRemoteSearch(THISNODE(searchWords),THISNODE(previousResults)))
</programlisting>

    <para>Where 'searchWords' and 'previousResults' are effectively calculated
    on the current node, and then passed as parameters to each instance of the
    doRemoteSearch() executing in parallel on all nodes.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="LOCAL_vs_NOLOCAL">
    <title>LOCAL vs. NOLOCAL</title>

    <para>The LOCAL option available on many functions (like JOIN, SORT, etc.)
    and the LOCAL() and NOLOCAL() functions control whether the graphs running
    on a particular node access all parts of a file/index or only those
    associated with the particular node (LOCAL). Often within an ALLNODES()
    context you only want to access local index parts from a single node
    because each node is independently processing its associated parts.
    Specifying that an index read or a keyed JOIN is LOCAL means that only the
    local part is used on each node. A local read of a single part INDEX will
    only be evaluated on the first agent node (or the farmer node if not
    within an ALLNODES)</para>

    <para>Local evaluation can be specified in two ways:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>1) As a dataset operation:</para>

      <programlisting>LOCAL(MyIndex)(myField = searchField)</programlisting>

      <para>2) As an option on the operation:</para>

      <programlisting>JOIN(... ,LOCAL)
FETCH(... ,LOCAL)</programlisting>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The LOCAL(<emphasis>dataset</emphasis>) function causes every
    operation on the <emphasis>dataset</emphasis> to access the file/key
    locally. For example,</para>

    <programlisting>LOCAL(JOIN(index1, index2,...))</programlisting>

    <para>will read index1 and index2 locally. This rule is recursively
    applied until you reach one of the following:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Use of the NOLOCAL() function</para>

      <para>A non-local attribute—the operation stays non-local, but children
      are still marked as local as necessary</para>

      <para>A GLOBAL() or THISNODE() or workflow operation—since they will be
      evaluated in a different context</para>

      <para>Use of the ALLNODES() function (as in a nested child query)</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Note that:</para>

    <para>JOIN(x, LOCAL(index1)...) is treated the same as JOIN(x, index1,
    ..., local).</para>

    <para>LOCAL is also supported as an option on an INDEX, but the LOCAL()
    function is preferred, because it generally depends on the context an
    index is used in whether or not access to it should be local or
    not.</para>

    <para>A non-local attribute is supported everywhere that a LOCAL attribute
    is allowed - to override an enclosing LOCAL() function.</para>

    <para>The use of LOCAL to indicate that dataset/key access is local does
    not conflict with its use to control coordination of an operation with
    other nodes, because there is no operation that potentially co-ordinates
    with other nodes and also accesses indexes or datasets.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="NOROOT_Indexes">
    <title>NOROOT Indexes</title>

    <para>The ALLNODES() function is particularly useful if there is more than
    one index co-distributed on a particular value so that all information
    that relates to a particular key field value is associated with the same
    node. However generally indexes are globally sorted. <emphasis
    role="bold">Adding a NOROOT option to a BUILD action or INDEX declaration
    indicates that the index is </emphasis><emphasis
    role="bold">not</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> globally sorted, and
    there is no root index to indicate which part of the index will contain a
    particular entry.</emphasis></para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
