<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Getting_Things_Done">
  <title><emphasis>Getting Things Done</emphasis></title>

  <sect2 id="Scanning_Landing_Zone_Files">
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Scanning Landing Zone
    Files</emphasis></title>

    <para><emphasis>Here’s the scenario—you’ve just received a data file from
    someone and it has been put on your landing zone. Before you spray that
    file to your Thor cluster and start to work with it, you want to have a
    quick look to see exactly what kind of data it contains and whether the
    format of that data matches the format that you were given by the
    supplier. There are a number of ways to do this, including mapping a drive
    to your landing zone and using a text/hex editor to open the file and look
    at the contents. </emphasis></para>

    <para>This article will show you how to accomplish this from within
    QueryBuilder using ECL. Here’s the code (contained in the
    Default.ProgGuide MODULE attribute):</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT MAC_ScanFile(IP, infile, scansize) := MACRO
ds := DATASET(FileServices.ExternalLogicalFileName(IP, infile),
     {DATA1 S},
      THOR )[1..scansize];
OUTPUT(TABLE(ds,{hex := ds.s,txt := (STRING1)ds.s}),ALL);
Rec := RECORD
UNSIGNED2 C;
DATA S {MAXLENGTH(8*1024)};
END;
Rec XF1(ds L,INTEGER C) := TRANSFORM
SELF.C := C;
SELF.S := L.s;
END;

ds2 := PROJECT(ds,XF1(LEFT,COUNTER));
Rec XF2(Rec L,Rec R) := TRANSFORM
SELF.S := L.S[1 .. R.C-1] + R.S[1];
SELF := L;
END;
Rolled := ROLLUP(ds2,TRUE,XF2(LEFT,RIGHT));
OUTPUT(TRANSFER(Rolled[1].S,STRING));
ENDMACRO;
</programlisting>

    <para>This is written as a MACRO because you could have multiple Landing
    Zones, and you certainly are going to want to look into different files
    each time. Therefore, a MACRO that generates the standard process code to
    scan the file is precisely what’s needed here.</para>

    <para>This MACRO takes three parameters: the IP of the landing zone
    containing the file the fully-qualified path to that file on the landing
    zone the number of bytes to read (maximum 8K)</para>

    <para>The initial DATASET declaration uses the
    FileServices.ExternalLogicalFileName function to name the file. Defining
    the RECORD structure as a single DATA1 field is necessary to ensure that
    both text and binary fields can be read correctly. Specifying the DATASET
    as a THOR file (no matter what type of file it actually is) makes it
    simple to read as a fixed-length record file. The square brackets at the
    end of the DATASET declaration automatically limit the number of 1-byte
    records read to the first <emphasis>scansize</emphasis> number of bytes in
    the file.</para>

    <para>The first OUTPUT action allows you to see the raw Hexadecimal data
    from the file.</para>

    <para>The TABLE function doubles up the input data, producing a DATA1
    displaying the Hex value and a STRING1 that type casts each byte to a
    STRING1 for display. Viewing the raw Hex value is necessary because most
    binary fields will not contain text-displayable characters (and those that
    do may mislead you as to the actual contents of the field).
    Non-displayable binary characters show up as a square box in the text
    column display.</para>

    <para>Next, we’ll construct a more text-friendly view of the data. To do
    that we’ll start with the Rec RECORD structure, which defines a
    byte-counter field (UNSIGNED2 C) and a variable-length field (DATA S
    {MAXLENGTH(8*1024)} to contain the text representation of the data as a
    single horizontal line of text.</para>

    <para>The XF1 TRANSFORM and its associated PROJECT moves the data from the
    input format into the format needed to roll up that data into a single
    text string. Adding the byte-counter field is necessary to ensure that
    blank spaces are not accidentally trimmed out of the final display.</para>

    <para>The XF2 TRANSFORM and its associated ROLLUP function performs the
    actual data append. The TRUE condition parameter ensures that only one
    record will result containing all the input bytes rolled into a single
    record.</para>

    <para>The last OUTPUT action uses the TRANSFER function instead of type
    casting to ensure that all the text characters in the original data are
    accurately represented.</para>

    <para>You call this MACRO like this:</para>

    <programlisting>ProgGuide.MAC_ScanFile( '10.173.9.4',
'C:\\training\\import\\BOCA.XML', 200)
</programlisting>

    <para>When viewing the result, the QueryBuilder Result_1 tab displays a
    column of hexadecimal values and the text character (if any) next to it in
    the second column. This byte-by-byte view of the data is designed to allow
    you to see the raw Hexadecimal values of each byte alongside its text
    representation. This is the primary view to use when looking at the
    contents of files containing binary data.</para>

    <para>The QueryBuilder Result_2 tab displays a single record with a single
    field. You can click on that field to highlight it, right-click and select
    “Copy” from the popup menu, then paste the text into any text editor to
    view. Binary fields will appear as square blocks or “garbage” characters,
    depending on their hex value. Once pasted into a text editor, you can
    easily look for data patterns that indicate the start for fields or
    records and validate that the data layout information provided by the data
    vendor is accurate (or not).</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Cartesian_Product_of_Two-Datasets">
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Cartesian Product of Two
    Datasets</emphasis></title>

    <para><emphasis>A Cartesian Product is the product of two non-empty sets
    in terms of ordered pairs. As an example, if we take the set of values, A,
    B and C, and a second set of values, 1, 2, and 3, the Cartesian Product of
    these two sets would be the set of ordered pairs, A1, A2, A3, B1, B2, B3,
    C1, C2, C3.</emphasis></para>

    <para>The ECL code to produce this kind of result from any two input
    datasets would look like this (contained in Cartesian.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>OutFile1 := '~PROGGUIDE::OUT::CP1';

rec := RECORD
STRING1 Letter;
  END;
  Inds1 := DATASET([{'A'},{'B'},{'C'},{'D'},{'E'},
                    {'F'},{'G'},{'H'},{'I'},{'J'},
                    {'K'},{'L'},{'M'},{'N'},{'O'},
                    {'P'},{'Q'},{'R'},{'S'},{'T'},
                    {'U'},{'V'},{'W'},{'X'},{'Y'}],
                   rec);

Inds2 := DATASET([{'A'},{'B'},{'C'},{'D'},{'E'},
                  {'F'},{'G'},{'H'},{'I'},{'J'},
                  {'K'},{'L'},{'M'},{'N'},{'O'},
                  {'P'},{'Q'},{'R'},{'S'},{'T'},
                  {'U'},{'V'},{'W'},{'X'},{'Y'}],
                 rec);

CntInDS2 := COUNT(Inds2);
SetInDS2 := SET(inds2,letter);
outrec := RECORD
  STRING1 LeftLetter;
  STRING1 RightLetter;
END;

outrec CartProd(rec L, INTEGER C) := TRANSFORM
  SELF.LeftLetter := L.Letter;
  SELF.RightLetter := SetInDS2[C];
END;

//Run the small datasets
CP1 := NORMALIZE(Inds1,CntInDS2,CartProd(LEFT,COUNTER));
OUTPUT(CP1,,OutFile1,OVERWRITE);
</programlisting>

    <para>The core structure of this code is the NORMALIZE that will produce
    the Cartesian Product. The two input datasets each have twenty-five
    records, so the number of result records will be six hundred twenty-five
    (twenty-five squared).</para>

    <para>Each record in the LEFT input dataset to the NORMALIZE will execute
    the TRANSFORM once for each entry in the SET of values. Making the values
    a SET is the key to allowing NORMALIZE to perform this operation,
    otherwise you would need to do a JOIN where the join condition is the
    keyword TRUE to accomplish this task. However, in testing this with
    sizable datasets (as in the next instance of this code below), the
    NORMALIZE version was about 25% faster than using JOIN. If there is more
    than one field, then multiple SETs may be defined and the process stays
    the same.</para>

    <para>This next example does the same operation as above, but first
    generates two sizeable datasets to work with (also contained in
    Cartesian.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>InFile1 := '~PROGGUIDE::IN::CP1';
InFile2 := '~PROGGUIDE::IN::CP2';
OutFile2 := '~PROGGUIDE::OUT::CP2';

//generate data files
rec BuildFile(rec L, INTEGER C) := TRANSFORM
  SELF.Letter := Inds2[C].Letter;
END;

GenCP1 := NORMALIZE(InDS1,CntInDS2,BuildFile(LEFT,COUNTER));
GenCP2 := NORMALIZE(GenCP1,CntInDS2,BuildFile(LEFT,COUNTER));
GenCP3 := NORMALIZE(GenCP2,CntInDS2,BuildFile(LEFT,COUNTER));

Out1 := OUTPUT(DISTRIBUTE(GenCP3,RANDOM()),,InFile1,OVERWRITE);
Out2 := OUTPUT(DISTRIBUTE(GenCP2,RANDOM()),,InFile2,OVERWRITE);

// Use the generated datasets in a cartesian join:

ds1 := DATASET(InFile1,rec,thor);
ds2 := DATASET(InFile2,rec,thor);

CntDS2 := COUNT(ds2);
SetDS2 := SET(ds2,letter);

CP2  := NORMALIZE(ds1,CntDS2,CartProd(LEFT,COUNTER));
Out3 := OUTPUT(CP2,,OutFile2,OVERWRITE);
SEQUENTIAL(Out1,Out2,Out3) </programlisting>

    <para>Using NORMALIZE in this case to generate the datasets is the same
    type of usage previously described in the Creating Example Data article.
    After that, the process to achieve the Cartesian Product is exactly the
    same as the previous example.</para>

    <para>Here’s an example of how this same operation can be done using JOIN
    (also contained in Cartesian.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>// outrec joinEm(rec L, rec R) := TRANSFORM
    // SELF.LeftLetter := L.Letter;
    // SELF.RightLetter := R.Letter;
// END;

// ds4 := JOIN(ds1, ds2, TRUE, joinEM(LEFT, RIGHT), ALL);
// OUTPUT(ds4);
</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Records_Containing_Any_of_a-Set_of_Words">
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Records Containing Any of a Set of
    Words</emphasis></title>

    <para><emphasis>Part of the data cleanup problem is the possible presence
    of profanity or cartoon character names in the data. This can become an
    issue whenever you are working with data that originated from direct input
    by end-users to a website. The following code (contained in the
    BadWordSearch.ECL file) will detect the presence of any of a set of “bad”
    words in a given field:</emphasis></para>

    <programlisting>SetBadWords := ['JUNK', 'GARBAGE', 'CRAP'];
BadWordDS := DATASET(SetBadWords,{STRING10 word});

SearchDS := DATASET([{1,'FRED','FLINTSTONE'},
                     {2,'GEORGE','JETSON'},
                     {3,'CRAPOLA','NASTYGUY'},
                     {4,'JUNKER','JUNKEE'},
                     {5,'GARBAGEGUY','JUNKMAN'},
                     {6,'FREDDY','KRUEGER'},
                     {7,'TIM','JONES'},
                     {8,'JOHN','SMITH'},
                     {9,'MIKE','MALARKEY'},
                     {10,'GEORGE','KRUEGER'}
        ],{UNSIGNED6 ID,STRING10 firstname,STRING10 lastname});

        outrec := RECORD
        SearchDS.ID;
        SearchDS.firstname;
        BOOLEAN FoundWord;
END;

{BOOLEAN Found} FindWord(BadWordDS L, STRING10 inword) := TRANSFORM
 SELF.Found := StringLib.StringFind(inword,TRIM(L.word),1) &gt; 0;
END;

outrec CheckWords(SearchDS L) := TRANSFORM
  SELF.FoundWord := EXISTS(PROJECT(BadWordDS,
                      FindWord(LEFT,L.firstname))(Found=TRUE));
  SELF := L;
END;

result := PROJECT(SearchDS,CheckWords(LEFT));

OUTPUT(result(FoundWord=TRUE),NAMED('BadWordsInFirstName'));
OUTPUT(result(FoundWord=FALSE),NAMED('NoBadWordsInFirstName'));
</programlisting>

    <para>This code is a simple PROJECT of each record that you want to
    search. The result will be a record set containing the record ID field,
    the firstname search field, and a BOOLEAN FoundWord flag field indicating
    whether any “bad” word was found.</para>

    <para>The search itself is done by a nested PROJECT of the field to be
    searched against the DATASET of “bad” words. Using the EXISTS function to
    detect if any records are returned from that PROJECT where the returned
    Found field is TRUE sets the FoundWord flag field value.</para>

    <para>The StringLib.StringFind function simoply detects the presence
    anywhere within the search strin of any of the “bad” words. The OUTPUT of
    the set of records where the FoundWord is TRUE allows post-processing to
    evaluate whether the record is worth keeping or garbage (probably
    requiring human intervention).</para>

    <para>The above code is a specific example of this technique, but it would
    be much more useful to have a MACRO that accomplishes this task, something
    like this one (also contained in the BadWordSearch.ECL file):</para>

    <programlisting>MAC_FindBadWords(BadWordSet,InFile,IDfld,SeekFld,ResAttr,MatchType=1)
                 := MACRO
  #UNIQUENAME(BadWordDS)
  %BadWordDS% := DATASET(BadWordSet,{STRING word{MAXLENGTH(50)}});

  #UNIQUENAME(outrec)
  %outrec% := RECORD
    InFile.IDfld;
    InFile.SeekFld;
    BOOLEAN FoundWord := FALSE;
    UNSIGNED2 FoundPos := 0;
  END;

  #UNIQUENAME(ChkTbl)
  %ChkTbl% := TABLE(InFile,%outrec%);

  #UNIQUENAME(FindWord)
  {BOOLEAN Found,UNSIGNED2 FoundPos} %FindWord%(%BadWordDS% L,
                                            INTEGER C,
                                            STRING inword)
                                    := TRANSFORM
   #IF(MatchType=1) //"contains" search
     SELF.Found := StringLib.StringFind(inword,TRIM(L.word),1) &gt;  0;
   #END
   #IF(MatchType=2) //"exact match" search
     SELF.Found := inword = L.word;
  #END
  #IF(MatchType=3) //"starts with" search
     SELF.Found := StringLib.StringFind(inword,TRIM(L.word),1) = 1;
  #END
    SELF.FoundPos := IF(SELF.FOUND=TRUE,C,0);
  END;

  #UNIQUENAME(CheckWords)
  %outrec% %CheckWords%(%ChkTbl% L) := TRANSFORM
  WordDS := PROJECT(%BadWordDS%,%FindWord%(LEFT,COUNTER,L.SeekFld));
  SELF.FoundWord := EXISTS(WordDS(Found=TRUE));
  SELF.FoundPos := WordDS(Found=TRUE)[1].FoundPos;
  SELF := L;
 END;

  ResAttr := PROJECT(%ChkTbl%,%CheckWords%(LEFT));
ENDMACRO;    </programlisting>

    <para>This MACRO does a bit more than the previous example. It begins by
    passing in:</para>

    <para>* The set of words to find* The file to search* The unique
    identifier field for the search record* The field to search in* The
    attribute name of the resulting recordset* The type of matching to do
    (defaulting to 1)</para>

    <para>Passing in the set of words to seek allows the MACRO to operate
    against any given set of strings. Specifying the result attribute name
    allows easy post-processing of the data.</para>

    <para>Where this MACRO starts going beyond the previous example is in the
    MatchType parameter, which allows the MACRO to use the Template Language
    #IF function to generate three different kinds of searches from the same
    codebase: a “contains” search (the default), an exact match, and a “starts
    with” search.</para>

    <para>It also has an expanded output RECORD structure that includes a
    FoundPos field to contain the pointer to the first entry in the passed in
    set that matched. This allows post processing to detect positional matches
    within the set so that “matched pairs” of words can be detected, as in
    this example (also contained in the BadWordSearch.ECL file):</para>

    <programlisting>SetCartoonFirstNames := ['GEORGE','FRED', 'FREDDY'];
SetCartoonLastNames := ['JETSON','FLINTSTONE','KRUEGER'];

MAC_FindBadWords(SetCartoonFirstNames,SearchDS,ID,firstname,Res1,2)
MAC_FindBadWords(SetCartoonLastNames,SearchDS,ID,lastname,Res2,2)

Cartoons := JOIN(Res1(FoundWord=TRUE),
           Res2(FoundWord=TRUE),
           LEFT.ID=RIGHT.ID AND LEFT.FoundPos=RIGHT.FoundPos);

MAC_FindBadWords(SetBadWords,SearchDS,ID,firstname,Res3,3)
MAC_FindBadWords(SetBadWords,SearchDS,ID,lastname,Res4)
SetBadGuys := SET(Cartoons,ID) +
           SET(Res3(FoundWord=TRUE),ID) +
           SET(Res4(FoundWord=TRUE),ID);

GoodGuys := SearchDS(ID NOT IN SetBadGuys);
BadGuys := SearchDS(ID IN SetBadGuys);
OUTPUT(BadGuys,NAMED('BadGuys'));
OUTPUT(GoodGuys,NAMED('GoodGuys'));
</programlisting>

    <para>Notice that the position of the cartoon character names in their
    separate sets define a single character name to search for in multiple
    passes. Calling the MACRO twice, searching for the first and last names
    separately, allows you to post-process their results with a simple inner
    JOIN where the same record was found in each and, most importantly, the
    positional values of the matches are the same. This prevents “GEORGE
    KRUEGER” from being mis-labelled a cartoon chracter name.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Simple_Random_Samples">
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Simple Random Samples</emphasis></title>

    <para><emphasis>There is a statistical concept called a “Simple Random
    Sample” in which a statistically “random” (different from simply using the
    RANDOM() function) sample of records is generated from any dataset. The
    algorithm inmplemented in the following code example was provided by a
    customer.</emphasis></para>

    <para>This code is implemented as a MACRO to allow multiple samples to be
    produced in the same workunit (contained in the SimpleRandomSamples.ECL
    file):</para>

    <programlisting>SimpleRandomSample(InFile,UID_Field,SampleSize,Result) := MACRO
  //build a table of the UIDs
  #UNIQUENAME(Layout_Plus_RecID)
  %Layout_Plus_RecID% := RECORD
     UNSIGNED8 RecID := 0;
     InFile.UID_Field;
  END;
  #UNIQUENAME(InTbl)
  %InTbl% := TABLE(InFile,%Layout_Plus_RecID%);

  //then assign unique record IDs to the table entries
  #UNIQUENAME(IDRecs)
  %Layout_Plus_RecID% %IDRecs%(%Layout_Plus_RecID% L, INTEGER C) :=
     TRANSFORM
     SELF.RecID := C;
     SELF := L;
  END;
  #UNIQUENAME(UID_Recs)
  %UID_Recs% := PROJECT(%InTbl%,%IDRecs%(LEFT,COUNTER));

   //discover the number of records
   #UNIQUENAME(WholeSet)
   %WholeSet% := COUNT(InFile) : GLOBAL;

   //then generate the unique record IDs to include in the sample
   #UNIQUENAME(BlankSet)
   %BlankSet% := DATASET([{0}],{UNSIGNED8 seq});
   #UNIQUENAME(SelectEm)
   TYPEOF(%BlankSet%) %SelectEm%(%BlankSet% L, INTEGER c) := TRANSFORM
     SELF.seq := ROUNDUP(%WholeSet% * (((RANDOM()%100000)+1)/100000));
   END;
   #UNIQUENAME(selected)
   %selected% := NORMALIZE( %BlankSet%, SampleSize,
                           %SelectEm%(LEFT, COUNTER));

  //then filter the original dataset by the selected UIDs
  #UNIQUENAME(SetSelectedRecs)
%SetSelectedRecs% := SET(%UID_Recs%(RecID IN SET(%selected%,seq)),
                          UID_Field);
  result := infile(UID_Field IN %SetSelectedRecs% );
ENDMACRO;
</programlisting>

    <para>This MACRO takes four parameters:</para>

    <para>* The name of the file to sample * The name of the unique identifier
    field in that file * The size of the sample to generate * The name of the
    attribute for the result, so that it may be post-processed</para>

    <para>The algorithm itself is fairly simple. We first create a TABLE of
    uniquely numbered unique identifier fields. Then we use NORMALIZE to
    produce a recordset of the candidate records. Which candidate is chosen
    each time the TRANSFORM function is called is determined by generating a
    “random” value between zero and one, using modulus division by one hundred
    thousand on the return from the RANDOM() function, then multiplying that
    result by the number of records to sample from, rounding up to the next
    larger integer. This determines the position of the field identifier to
    use. Once the set of positions within the TABLE is determined, they are
    used to define the SET of unique fields to use in the final result.</para>

    <para>This algorithm is designed to produce a sample “with replacement” so
    that it is possible to have a smaller number of records returned than the
    sample size requested. To produce exactly the size sample you need (that
    is, a “without replacement” sample), you can request a larger sample size
    (say, 10% larger) then use the CHOOSEN function to retrieve only the
    actual number of records required, as in this example (also contained in
    the SimpleRandomSamples.ECL file).</para>

    <programlisting>SomeFile := DATASET([{'A1'},{'B1'},{'C1'},{'D1'},{'E1'},
                     {'F1'},{'G1'},{'H1'},{'I1'},{'J1'},
                     {'K1'},{'L1'},{'M1'},{'N1'},{'O1'},
                     {'P1'},{'Q1'},{'R1'},{'S1'},{'T1'},
                     {'U1'},{'V1'},{'W1'},{'X1'},{'Y1'},
                     {'A2'},{'B2'},{'C2'},{'D2'},{'E2'},
                     {'F2'},{'G2'},{'H2'},{'I2'},{'J2'},
                     {'K2'},{'L2'},{'M2'},{'N2'},{'O2'},
                     {'P2'},{'Q2'},{'R2'},{'S2'},{'T2'},
                     {'U2'},{'V2'},{'W2'},{'X2'},{'Y2'},
                     {'A3'},{'B3'},{'C3'},{'D3'},{'E3'},
                     {'F3'},{'G3'},{'H3'},{'I3'},{'J3'},
                     {'K3'},{'L3'},{'M3'},{'N3'},{'O3'},
                     {'P3'},{'Q3'},{'R3'},{'S3'},{'T3'},
                     {'U3'},{'V3'},{'W3'},{'X3'},{'Y3'},
                     {'A4'},{'B4'},{'C4'},{'D4'},{'E4'},
                     {'F4'},{'G4'},{'H4'},{'I4'},{'J4'},
                     {'K4'},{'L4'},{'M4'},{'N4'},{'O4'},
                     {'P4'},{'Q4'},{'R4'},{'S4'},{'T4'},
                     {'U4'},{'V4'},{'W4'},{'X4'},{'Y4'}
                     ],{STRING2 Letter});

ds := DISTRIBUTE(SomeFile,HASH(letter[2]));
SimpleRandomSample(ds,Letter,6, res1) //ask for 6
SimpleRandomSample(ds,Letter,6, res2)
SimpleRandomSample(ds,Letter,6, res3)

OUTPUT(CHOOSEN(res1,5)); //actually need 5
OUTPUT(CHOOSEN(res3,5));
</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Hex_String_to_Decimal_String">
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Hex String to Decimal
    String</emphasis></title>

    <para><emphasis>An email request came to me to suggest a way to convert a
    string containing Hexadecimal values to a string containing the decimal
    equivalent of that value. The problem was that this code needed to run in
    Roxie and the StringLib.String2Data plugin library fiunction was not
    available for use in Roxie queries at that time. Therefore, an all-ECL
    solution was needed.</emphasis></para>

    <para>This example function (contained in the Hex2Decimal.ECL file)
    provides that functionality, while at the same time demonstrating
    practical usage of BIG ENDIAN integers and type transfer.</para>

    <programlisting>HexStr2Decimal(STRING HexIn) := FUNCTION

  //type re-definitions to make code more readable below
  BE1 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED1;
  BE2 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED2;
  BE3 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED3;
  BE4 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED4;
  BE5 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED5;
  BE6 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED6;
  BE7 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED7;
  BE8 := BIG_ENDIAN UNSIGNED8;

  TrimHex := TRIM(HexIn,ALL);
  HexLen := LENGTH(TrimHex);
  UseHex := IF(HexLen % 2 = 1,'0','') + TrimHex;

  //a sub-function to translate two hex chars to a packed hex format
  STRING1 Str2Data(STRING2 Hex) := FUNCTION
    UNSIGNED1 N1 :=
        CASE( Hex[1],
            '0'=&gt;00x,'1'=&gt;10x,'2'=&gt;20x,'3'=&gt;30x,
            '4'=&gt;40x,'5'=&gt;50x,'6'=&gt;60x,'7'=&gt;70x,
            '8'=&gt;80x,'9'=&gt;90x,'A'=&gt;0A0x,'B'=&gt;0B0x,
            'C'=&gt;0C0x,'D'=&gt;0D0x,'E'=&gt;0E0x,'F'=&gt;0F0x,00x);
     UNSIGNED1 N2 :=
        CASE( Hex[2],
            '0'=&gt;00x,'1'=&gt;01x,'2'=&gt;02x,'3'=&gt;03x,
            '4'=&gt;04x,'5'=&gt;05x,'6'=&gt;06x,'7'=&gt;07x,
            '8'=&gt;08x,'9'=&gt;09x,'A'=&gt;0Ax,'B'=&gt;0Bx,
            'C'=&gt;0Cx,'D'=&gt;0Dx,'E'=&gt;0Ex,'F'=&gt;0Fx,00x);
     RETURN (&gt;STRING1&lt;)(N1 | N2);
  END;

  UseHexLen := LENGTH(TRIM(UseHex));
  InHex2 := Str2Data(UseHex[1..2]);
  InHex4 := InHex2 + Str2Data(UseHex[3..4]);
  InHex6 := InHex4 + Str2Data(UseHex[5..6]);
  InHex8 := InHex6 + Str2Data(UseHex[7..8]);
  InHex10 := InHex8 + Str2Data(UseHex[9..10]);;
  InHex12 := InHex10 + Str2Data(UseHex[11..12]);
  InHex14 := InHex12 + Str2Data(UseHex[13..14]);
  InHex16 := InHex14 + Str2Data(UseHex[15..16]);
  RETURN CASE(UseHexLen,
          2 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE1&lt;)InHex2,
          4 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE2&lt;)InHex4,
          6 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE3&lt;)InHex6,
          8 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE4&lt;)InHex8,
          10 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE5&lt;)InHex10,
          12 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE6&lt;)InHex12,
          14 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE7&lt;)InHex14,
          16 =&gt; (STRING)(&gt;BE8&lt;)InHex16,
          'ERROR');
END;
</programlisting>

    <para>This HexStr2Decimal FUNCTION takes a variable-length STRING
    parameter containing the hexadecimal value to evaluate. It begins by
    re-defining the eight possible sizes of unsigned BIG ENDIAN integers. This
    re-definition is purely for cosmetic purposes—to make the subsequent code
    more readable.</para>

    <para>The next three attributes detect whether an even or odd number of
    hexadecimal characters have been passed. If an odd number is passed, then
    a “0” character is prepended to the passed value to ensure the hex values
    are placed inthe correct nibbles.</para>

    <para>The Str2Data FUNCTION takes a two-character STRING parameter and
    translates each character into the appropriate hexadecimal value for each
    nibble of the resulting 1-character STRING that it returns. The first
    character defines the first nibble and the second defines the second.
    These two values are ORed together (using the bitwise | operator) then the
    result is type transferred to a one-character string, using the shorthand
    syntax— (&gt;STRING1&lt;) —so that the bit pattern remains untouched. The
    RETURN result from this FUNCTION is a STRING1 because each succeeding
    two-character portion of the HexStr2Decimal FUNCTION’s input parameter
    will pass through the Str2Data FUNCTION and be concatenated with all the
    preceding results.</para>

    <para>The UseHexLen attribute determines the appropriate size of BIG
    ENDIAN integer to use to translate the hex into decimal, while the InHex2
    through InHex16 attributes define the final packed-hexadecimal value to
    evaluate. The CASE function then uses that UseHexLen to determine which
    InHex attribute to use for the number of bytes of hex value passed in.
    Only even numbers of hex characters are allowed (meaning the call to the
    function would need to add a leading zero to any odd-numbered hex values
    to translate) and the maximum number of characters allowed is sixteen
    (representing an eight-byte packed hexadecimal value to translate).</para>

    <para>In all cases, the result from the InHex attribute is
    type-transferred to the appropriately sized BIG ENDIAN integer. The
    standard type cast to STRING then performs the actual value translation
    from the hexadecimal to decimal.</para>

    <para>The following calls return the indicated results:</para>

    <programlisting>OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('0101'));               // 257
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FF'));                 // 255
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFF'));               // 65535
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFF'));             // 16777215
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFF'));           // 4294967295
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFFFF'));         // 1099511627775
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFFFFFF'));       // 281474976710655
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFFFFFFFF'));     // 72057594037927935
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF'));   // 18446744073709551615
OUTPUT(HexStr2Decimal('FFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF')); // ERROR
</programlisting>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
