<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Direct Access to Roxie</title>

  <sect1 role="nobrk">
    <title>Roxie Query Access Overview</title>

    <para>WsECL provides quick and easy access to your published queries, but
    is not optimized for the rapid throughput Roxie provides. To take full
    advantage of this capability, you should access Roxie directly.</para>

    <para>WsECL still plays an important role when using this technique. It
    provides an immediate means of testing, provides a web interface for
    one-off query execution, and provides the WSDL and schema which can be
    used for automated code generators for SOAP access. It also provides the
    HTTP-GET and form encodes support. Finally, it also provides a JSON
    (Javascript Simple Object Notation) interface which is similar to Roxie’s
    direct interface.</para>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Web Services</title>

      <para>A Web service is a standards-based software component accessible
      over the Internet. The service can be simple or complex.</para>

      <para>For example, a Web service could request a number of stock quotes
      and return them in an XML result set.</para>

      <para>Web Services are available to any platform, object model, or
      programming language. This provides access to users over the Internet,
      Intranet, or Extranet regardless of the user’s platform.</para>

      <para>It also simplifies distributed systems development. The use of
      standards-based components protects development investment regardless of
      future trends. Web Service Technologies are based upon HTTP.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Simple Object Access Protocol
        (SOAP)</emphasis></title>

        <para>SOAP is the most common XML-based protocol for sending requests
        to and receiving responses from Web Services. Basically, it is a
        protocol for communication between applications. It is designed to
        communicate over the Internet and is platform independent and language
        independent. Based on XML, SOAP is simple and extensible.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>JavaScript Object Notation<emphasis role="bold">
        (JSON)</emphasis></title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">JSON</emphasis> is a lightweight
        data-interchange format. It is easy for humans to read and write. It
        is easy for machines to parse and generate. It is based on a subset of
        the JavaScript Programming Language, it is completely language
        independent.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Accessing your Roxie Queries</title>

    <para>Once you have developed, compiled, and published your queries, you
    need to provide access to users.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title><emphasis role="bold">ESP and WsECL</emphasis></title>

      <para>A standard installation of the HPCC platform includes an
      Enterprise Services Platform (ESP) with the WsECL service configured
      through a service binding to port 8002 (configurable).</para>

      <para>WsECL provides a means to access all of your compiled and
      published queries using a Web interface or by using SOAP or JSON.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Tip: </emphasis>You can provide a JobName in
      the URL using this form:</para>

      <programlisting>http://ip:port/WsEcl/submit/query/<emphasis role="bold">&lt;targetCluster&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis
          role="bold">&lt;query&gt;</emphasis>?_jobname=<emphasis role="bold">&lt;jobname&gt;</emphasis></programlisting>

      <para>This is useful for testing queries. It is also suitable for
      providing real-time access to a small set of users; however, it is not
      intended to scale to larger audiences.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title><emphasis role="bold">Access WsECL VIA SOAP</emphasis></title>

      <sect3>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">WSDL</emphasis></title>

        <para>The Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) sets a standard for
        communication between processes using a common xml based format. SOAP
        libraries are readily available for many languages and development
        platforms, including Microsoft .NET (accessible using C#, VB.NET,
        ASP.NET, and other CLR languages), Java (e.g.,. JAX and Apache AXIS),
        PERL, and many others.</para>

        <para>Web Service Description Language (WSDL) is used to provide a
        structured description of a Web service interface.</para>

        <para>Many of the libraries available for allowing applications to use
        the SOAP protocol also provide tools for automatically generating
        service specific APIs from a WSDL document.</para>

        <para>The WSDL description is automatically available for any
        published query.</para>

        <para>The following URL can be used to retrieve the WSDL description
        of a published query:</para>

        <para>http://<emphasis>nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn</emphasis>:8002/WsEcl/definitions/query/roxie/&lt;queryName&gt;/main/&lt;queryName&gt;.wsdl</para>

        <para>where <emphasis>nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn</emphasis> is the IP address (or
        DNS Name) of that ESP server with the binding to WsECL.</para>

        <para>8002 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
        setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>

        <para>The syntax and functionality of the SOAP protocol itself is also
        beyond the scope of this document. The following list of external
        resources can help in your understanding of standards-based
        technologies used.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>SOAP</title>

        <para>http://www.w3.org/TR/soap12-part0</para>

        <para>http://www.w3.org/TR/soap12-part1</para>

        <para>http://www.w3.org/TR/soap12-part2</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Web Service Definition Language (WSDL)
        1.1</emphasis></title>

        <para>http://www.w3.org/TR/wsdl</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title><emphasis role="bold">Direct Access Via SOAP</emphasis></title>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Create and publish your query to a target cluster
          (Roxie).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Test and validate using WsECL to access the query.</para>

          <para>Use the default interface provided to test:</para>

          <para>http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8002/</para>

          <para>where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address (or DNS Name) of that
          ESP server with the binding to WsECL.</para>

          <para>8002 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
          setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Begin development of the application that will consume the web
          service by importing the WSDL from:</para>

          <para>http://<emphasis>nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn</emphasis>:8002/WsEcl/definitions/query/roxie/&lt;queryName&gt;/main/&lt;queryName&gt;.wsdl</para>

          <para>where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address (or DNS Name) of that
          ESP server with the binding to WsECL.</para>

          <para>8002 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
          setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When testing is complete, change the base URL to</para>

          <para>http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:9876/</para>

          <para>where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address (or DNS Name) of a
          Roxie Server.</para>

          <para>9876 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
          setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title><emphasis role="bold">Direct Access Via JSON</emphasis></title>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Create and publish your query to a target cluster
          (Roxie).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Test and validate using WsECL to access the query.</para>

          <para>Use the default interface provided to test:</para>

          <para>http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8002/</para>

          <para>where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address (or DNS Name) of that
          ESP server with the binding to WsECL.</para>

          <para>8002 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
          setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Begin development of the application that will consume the web
          service using the JSON definitions available from the form in
          WsECL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the drop list, select JSON Test, then press the submit
          button.</para>

          <para><graphic fileref="../../images/json1.jpg" /></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Edit the query criteria on the left, then press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Send Request</emphasis> button.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The results display on the right side.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Edit and resubmit (by pressing the <emphasis role="bold">Send
          Request</emphasis> button ) to see responses for different
          criteria.</para>

          <para><graphic fileref="../../images/json2.jpg" /></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the base URL in your application to</para>

          <para>http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:9876/</para>

          <para>where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is the IP address (or DNS Name) of a
          Roxie Server.</para>

          <para>9876 is the default port. If you have a modified the port
          setting, use the port you have selected for that purpose.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The WsECL service
      automatically distributes the load by sending queries to Roxie Servers
      in a round-robin fashion. To utilize all servers, your application
      should implement a similar load distribution scheme. Alternatively, you
      can use a load balancer and submit the query to the Virtual IP created
      by the load balancer.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Direct Access Via JSONP</title>

      <para>To get a JSONP response, add the <emphasis
      role="bold">&amp;jsonp=&lt;myfunctionname&gt;</emphasis> decoration to
      the URL. This returns a javascript wrapped json response:</para>

      <para><programlisting>myfunc("{"data_1": "hello world", "data_2": ["the","sun","is","up"]}");</programlisting></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
