<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect2>
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Queries and Data</emphasis></title>

  <para>Data files and index files referenced by a Roxie query’s ECL code are
  made available in one of four ways, depending on the configuration of the
  RDDE cluster.</para>

  <para>There are two settings in the Roxie configuration that control where
  Roxie looks for data and index files:</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="123.60pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">copyResources</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Copies necessary data and key files from the current
            location when the query is published.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">useRemoteResources</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Instructs Roxie to look for data and key files in the
            current location after the query is published.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <graphic fileref="../../images/RM-31.jpg" />

  <para>These options may appear to be mutually exclusive, but the chart below
  shows what each of the four possible combination means.</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colwidth="125.40pt" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>copyResources</entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>useRemoteResources</entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>

            <entry>T</entry>

            <entry>F</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry></entry>

            <entry align="left">Directs the Roxie cluster to use the remote
            instance of the data until it can copy the data locally. This
            allows a query to be available immediately while the data is
            copied.</entry>

            <entry align="left">Directs the Roxie cluster to copy the data
            locally. The query cannot be executed until the data is copied.
            This ensures optimum performance after the data is copied.</entry>

            <entry align="left">Directs the Roxie cluster to load the data
            from a remote location. The query can be executed immediately, but
            performance is limited by network bandwidth. This allows queries
            to run without using any Roxie disk space, but reduces its
            throughput capabilities.</entry>

            <entry align="left">Will use data and indexes already loaded
            (placed on the Roxie cluster using DFU ) but will not copy or read
            remote data.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para>When <emphasis role="bold">copyResources</emphasis> is enabled, data
  files are copied from source locations to slave nodes. Index files are also
  copied, with an extra file part that is a “key-of-keys” or a metakey.</para>

  <para>A copy of the metakey is always stored on each Farmer and in most
  cases is loaded into memory at startup to increase performance.</para>

  <sect3>
    <title><emphasis role="bold">Command Line support</emphasis></title>

    <para>The ecl command line tool offers a means of copying queries from one
    Roxie to another. Typically, this means data and index files would be
    copied or accessed remotely following Roxie’s configuration
    settings.</para>

    <para>The ecl command line tool provides an option to instruct Roxie to
    not copy files at the time of the query copy. This allows you to quickly
    copy a query without copying files.</para>

    <programlisting>
ecl queries copy --no-files
     </programlisting>

    <para>This specifies to NOT copy files referenced by the query being
    copied. The query cannot run until data is made available.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
