<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Creating_and_Maintaining_SuperFiles">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Creating and Maintaining
  SuperFiles</emphasis></title>

  <sect2 id="Creating_Data">
    <title>Creating Data</title>

    <para>First, we need to create some logical files to put into a
    SuperFile.</para>

    <para>The following filenames for the new sub-files are declared in the
    DeclareData MODULE structure:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT BaseFile := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::Base';
EXPORT SubFile1 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People1';
EXPORT SubFile2 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People2';
EXPORT SubFile3 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People3';
EXPORT SubFile4 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People4';
EXPORT SubFile5 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People5';
EXPORT SubFile6 := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::People6';
</programlisting>

    <para>The following code (in SuperFile1.ECL) creates the files that we'll
    use to build SuperFiles:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

s1 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] = 'A');
s2 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] BETWEEN 'B' AND 'C');
s3 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] BETWEEN 'D' AND 'J');
s4 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] BETWEEN 'K' AND 'N');
s5 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] BETWEEN 'O' AND 'R');
s6 := $.DeclareData.Person.File(firstname[1] BETWEEN 'S' AND 'Z');

Rec := $.DeclareData.Layout_Person;

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile1),
   OUTPUT(s1,,$.DeclareData.SubFile1));

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile2),
   OUTPUT(s2,,$.DeclareData.SubFile2));

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile3),
   OUTPUT(s3,,$.DeclareData.SubFile3));

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile4),
   OUTPUT(s4,,$.DeclareData.SubFile4));

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile5),
   OUTPUT(s5,,$.DeclareData.SubFile5));  

IF(~Std.File.FileExists($.DeclareData.SubFile6),
   OUTPUT(s6,,$.DeclareData.SubFile6));
</programlisting>

    <para>This code takes data from the ProgGuide.Person.File dataset (created
    by the code in GenData.ECL and declared in the ProgGuide MODULE structure
    attribute in the Default module) and writes six separate discrete samples
    to their own logical files, but only if they do not already exist. We'll
    use these logical files to build some SuperFiles.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="A_Simple_Example">
    <title>A Simple Example</title>

    <para>We'll start with a simple example of how to create and use a
    SuperFile. This dataset declaration is in the ProgGuide MODULE structure
    (contained in the Default module). This declares the SuperFile as a
    DATASET that can be referenced in ECL code:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT SuperFile1 := DATASET(BaseFile,Layout_Person,FLAT);
</programlisting>

    <para>Then we'll create and add sub-files to a SuperFile (this code is
    contained in SuperFile2.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.CreateSuperFile($.DeclareData.BaseFile),
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.BaseFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile1),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.BaseFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile2),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>If the workunit failed with a “logical name
    progguide::superfile::base already exists” error message, then open the
    SuperFileRestart.ECL file and run it, then re-try the above code. Once
    you've successfully executed this code in a builder window, you've created
    the SuperFile and added two sub-files into it.</para>

    <para>The SuperFile1 DATASET declaration attribute makes the SuperFile
    available for use just as any other DATASET would be—this is the key to
    using SuperFiles. That means the following types of actions can be
    executed against the SuperFile, just as with any other dataset:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
COUNT($.DeclareData.SuperFile1(PersonID &lt;&gt; 0));
OUTPUT($.DeclareData.SuperFile1);
</programlisting>

    <para>Given the logical files previously built, the results of the COUNT
    should be 317,000. The filter condition will always be true, so the COUNT
    returned will be the total number of records in the SuperFile. The
    (PersonID &lt;&gt; 0) record filter is necessary so that the actual COUNT
    is performed each time and the result is not a shortcut value stored
    internally by the ECL Agent. Of course, the OUTPUT produces the first 100
    records in the SuperFile.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Nesting_SuperFiles">
    <title>Nesting SuperFiles</title>

    <para>Nesting SuperFiles (a SuperFile containing a sub-file that is itself
    another SuperFile) is a technique that allows new data coming in on a
    periodic basis (every day, or every hour, or ....) to be “instantly”
    available to the system. Since the ECL code that refers to a SuperFile
    always references the DATASET declaration, the only change necessary to
    make new data available to queries is to add the new data as a sub-file.
    Since adding a new sub-file always takes place within a SuperFile
    transaction, any queries are locked out while the update is in
    progress.</para>

    <para>Implicit in this technique is also the periodic roll up and
    consolidation of the new data into composite files. This is necessary
    because the practical limit to the number of physical files you should
    combine into a SuperFile is about one hundred (100), since every time you
    reference the SuperFile every sub-file must be physically opened and read
    from disk, and the more sub-files there are the more operating system
    resources are used just to get at the data.</para>

    <para>Therefore, you need to periodically run a process that physically
    combines all the incremental logical files and combines them into a single
    logical file that replaces them all. Periodic SuperFile data consolidation
    is a simple process of using OUTPUT to write the complete contents of the
    SuperFile to a new, single logical file. Once all data is in a single
    file, a SuperFile transaction can clear the old set of sub-files then add
    in the new “base” logical file.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Nested_SuperFile_Example">
    <title>Nested SuperFile Example</title>

    <para>Here is an example of how to nest SuperFiles. This example assumes
    you have new data coming every day. It also assumes you want to roll up
    the new data daily and weekly. The following filenames for the new
    sub-files are declared in the DeclareData MODULE structure
    attribute:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT AllPeople := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::AllPeople';
EXPORT WeeklyFile := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::Weekly';
EXPORT DailyFile := '~PROGGUIDE::SUPERFILE::Daily';
</programlisting>

    <para>Creating three more SuperFiles has to be done just once, then you
    need to add the sub-files to them (this code is contained in
    SuperFile3.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.CreateSuperFile($.DeclareData.AllPeople),
  Std.File.CreateSuperFile($.DeclareData.WeeklyFile),
  Std.File.CreateSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile),
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.AllPeople,$.DeclareData.BaseFile),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.AllPeople,$.DeclareData.WeeklyFile),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.AllPeople,$.DeclareData.DailyFile),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>Now the AllPeople SuperFile contains the BaseFile, WeeklyFile, and
    DailyFile Superfiles as sub-files, creating a hierarchy of SuperFiles,
    only one of which yet contains any actual data. The Base SuperFile
    contains all the currently known data, as of the time of the build of the
    logical files. The Weekly and Daily SuperFiles will contain the interim
    data updates as they come in the door, precluding the need to rebuild the
    entire database every time a new set of data comes in.</para>

    <para>One important caveat to this scheme is that a given actual logical
    file (real data file) should be contained in exactly one of the nested
    SuperFiles at a time, otherwise you would have duplicate records in the
    base SuperFile. Therefore, you have to be careful how you maintain your
    hierarchy so as not to allow the same logical file to be referenced by
    more than one of the nested SuperFiles at once, outside of a transaction
    frame.</para>

    <para>As you get new logical files in during the day, you can add them to
    the Daily SuperFile like this (this code is contained in
    SuperFile4.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile3),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>This appends the ProgGuide.SubFile3 logical file to the list of
    sub-files in the DailyFile SuperFile. This means that the very next query
    using the SuperFile1 dataset will be using the very latest
    up-to-the-minute data.</para>

    <para>This dataset declaration is in the DeclareData MODULE structure
    (contained in the Default module). This declares the nested SuperFile as a
    DATASET that can be referenced in ECL code:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT SuperFile2 := DATASET(AllPeople,Layout_Person,FLAT);</programlisting>

    <para>Execute the following action:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT ProgrammersGuide AS PG;
COUNT(PG.DeclareData.SuperFile2(PersonID &lt;&gt; 0));
</programlisting>

    <para>The result of the COUNT should now be 451,000.</para>

    <para>Edit the code from SuperFile4.ECL to add in ProgGuide.SubFile4, like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile4),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>Re-running the above COUNT action should now result in
    620,000.</para>

    <para>Once a day, you can roll all the sub-files up into the WeeklyFile
    and clear out the DailyFile for the next day's data ingest processing,
    like this (this code is contained in SuperFile5.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.WeeklyFile,$.DeclareData.DailyFile,,TRUE),
  Std.File.ClearSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>This moves the references to all the sub-files from the DailyFile to
    the WeeklyFile (the fourth parameter to the AddSuperFile function being
    TRUE copies the references from one SuperFile to another), then clears out
    the DailyFile.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Data_Consolidation">
    <title>Data Consolidation</title>

    <para>Since the practical limit to the number of logical files you should
    combine into a SuperFile is about a hundred, you'll need to periodically
    run a process that physically combines all the incremental logical files
    and combines them into a single logical file that replaces them all, like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

OUTPUT($.DeclareData.SuperFile2,,'~$.DeclareData::SUPERFILE::People14',OVERWRITE);
</programlisting>

    <para>This will write a new file containing all the records from all the
    sub-files in the SuperFile.</para>

    <para>Once you've done that, you'll need to clear all the component
    SuperFiles and add the new all-the-data-there-is data file into the
    BaseFile, like this (this code is contained in SuperFile6.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;
SEQUENTIAL(
  Std.File.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  Std.File.ClearSuperFile($.DeclareData.BaseFile),
  Std.File.ClearSuperFile($.DeclareData.WeeklyFile),
  Std.File.ClearSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile),
  Std.File.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.BaseFile,'~$.DeclareData::SUPERFILE::People14'),
  Std.File.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>This action clears out the Base SuperFile, adds the reference to the
    new all-inclusive logical file, then clears all the incremental
    SuperFiles.</para>

    <para>Re-running the above COUNT action should still result in
    620,000.</para>

    <para>Once again, edit the code from SuperFile4.ECL to add
    ProgGuide.SubFile5 and ProgGuide.SubFile6 to the DailyFile, like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

SEQUENTIAL(
  FileServices.StartSuperFileTransaction(),
  FileServices.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile5),  
  FileServices.AddSuperFile($.DeclareData.DailyFile,$.DeclareData.SubFile6),
  FileServices.FinishSuperFileTransaction());
</programlisting>

    <para>Once you've done that, re-running the above COUNT action should now
    result in 1,000,000.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Getting_SuperFile_Components">
    <title>Getting SuperFile Components</title>

    <para>This macro (in the DeclareData MODULE structure attribute)
    demonstrates one technique to list the component sub-files of a
    SuperFile:</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT MAC_ListSFsubfiles(SuperFile) := MACRO

#UNIQUENAME(SeedRec)
%SeedRec% := DATASET([{''}], {STRING name});

#UNIQUENAME(Xform)
TYPEOF(%SeedRec%) %Xform%(%SeedRec% L, INTEGER C) :=
          TRANSFORM
SELF.name :=
          FileServices.GetSuperFileSubName(SuperFile,C);
END;

OUTPUT(NORMALIZE(%SeedRec%,
FileServices.GetSuperFileSubCount(SuperFile),
%Xform%(LEFT,COUNTER)));
ENDMACRO;
</programlisting>

    <para>The interesting technique here is the use of NORMALIZE to call the
    TRANSFORM function iteratively until all sub-files in the SuperFile are
    listed. You can call this macro in a builder window like this (this code
    is contained in SuperFile7.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;

$.DeclareData.MAC_ListSFsubfiles($.DeclareData.AllPeople);</programlisting>

    <para>This will return a list of all the sub-files in the specified
    SuperFile. However, this type of code is no longer necessary, since the
    default mode of the SuperFileContents() function now returns exactly the
    same result, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;
OUTPUT(Std.File.SuperFileContents($.DeclareData.AllPeople));</programlisting>

    <para>The SuperFileContents() function has an advantage over the macro—it
    has an option to return the sub-files from any nested SuperFile (which the
    macro can't do). That form looks like this:</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT $;
IMPORT Std;
OUTPUT(Std.File.SuperFileContents($.DeclareData.AllPeople,TRUE));</programlisting>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
