<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="SuperFile_Overview" role="nobrk">
  <title>SuperFile Overview</title>

  <para>First, let's define some terms:</para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" colwidth="81.35pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical File</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A single logical entity whose multiple physical parts (one
            on each node of the cluster) are internally managed by the
            Distributed File Utility (DFU).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dataset</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A Logical File declared as a DATASET.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">SuperFile</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A managed list of sub-files (Logical Files) treated as a
            single logical entity. The sub-files do not need DATASET
            declarations (although they may have). A SuperFile must be
            declared as a DATASET for use in ECL, and is treated in ECL code
            just like any other Dataset. The complexities of managing the
            multiple sub-files are left up to the DFU (just as it manages the
            physical parts of each sub-file).</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Each sub-file in a SuperFile must have the same
  structure type (THOR, CSV, or XML) and the same field layout.</emphasis> A
  sub-file may itself be a SuperFile, allowing you to build multi-level
  hierarchies that allow easy maintenance. The functions that build and
  maintain SuperFiles are all in the File standard library (see the
  <emphasis>Standard Library Reference</emphasis>).</para>

  <para>The major advantage of using SuperFiles is the easy maintenance of the
  set of sub-files. This means that updating the actual data a query reads can
  be as simple as adding a new sub-file to an existing SuperFile.</para>

  <sect2 id="SuperFile_Existence_Functions">
    <title>SuperFile Existence Functions</title>

    <para>The following functions govern SuperFile creation, deletion, and
    existence detection:</para>

    <programlisting>CreateSuperFile()
DeleteSuperFile()
SuperFileExists()</programlisting>

    <para>You must first create a SuperFile using the CreateSuperFile()
    function before you can perform any other SuperFile operations on that
    file. The SuperFileExists() function tells you if a SuperFile with the
    specified name exists, and DeleteSuperFile() removes a SuperFile from the
    system.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="SuperFile_Inquiry_Functions">
    <title>SuperFile Inquiry Functions</title>

    <para>The following functions provide information about a given
    SuperFile:</para>

    <programlisting>GetSuperFileSubCount()
GetSuperFileSubName()
FindSuperFileSubName()
SuperFileContents()
LogicalFileSuperOwners()      </programlisting>

    <para>The GetSuperFileSubCount() function allows you to determine the
    number of sub-files in a given SuperFile. The GetSuperFileSubName()
    function returns the name of the sub-file at a given position in the list
    of sub-files. The FindSuperFileSubName() function returns the ordinal
    position of a given sub-file in the list of sub-files. The
    SuperFileContents() function returns a recordset of logical sub-file names
    contained in the SuperFile. The LogicalFileSuperOwners function returns a
    list of all the SuperFiles that contain a specified sub-file.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="SuperFile_Maintenance_Functions">
    <title>SuperFile Maintenance Functions</title>

    <para>The following functions allow you to maintain the list of sub-files
    that comprise a SuperFile:</para>

    <programlisting>AddSuperFile()
RemoveSuperFile()
ClearSuperFile()
SwapSuperFile()
ReplaceSuperFile()</programlisting>

    <para>The AddSuperFile() function adds a sub-file to the SuperFile. The
    RemoveSuperFile() function deletes a sub-file from the SuperFile. The
    ClearSuperFile() function deletes all sub-files from the SuperFile. The
    SwapSuperFile() function moves swaps all sub-files between two SuperFiles.
    The ReplaceSuperFile() function replaces one sub-file in the SuperFile
    with another.</para>

    <para>All of these functions must be called within a transaction frame to
    ensure there are no problems with SuperFile usage.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="SuperFile_Transactions">
    <title>SuperFile Transactions</title>

    <para>The SuperFile Maintenance functions (only) must be called within a
    transaction frame if there is a possibility another process may try to use
    the superfile during sub-file maintenance. The transaction frame locks out
    all other operations for the duration of the transaction. This way,
    maintenance work can be accomplished without causing problems with any
    query that might use the SuperFile. This means two things:</para>

    <para>1) The SEQUENTIAL action must be used to ensure sequential execution
    of the function calls within the transaction frame.</para>

    <para>2) The StartSuperFileTransaction() and FinishSuperFileTransaction()
    functions are used to “lock” the SuperFile during maintenance, and always
    surround the SuperFile Maintenance function calls within the SEQUENTIAL
    action.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Any function other than the Maintenance
    Functions listed above that might be present inside a transaction frame
    might appear to be part of the transaction, but are not.</emphasis> This
    can lead to confusion if you, for example, include a call to
    ClearSuperFile() (which is valid for use within the transaction frame) and
    follow it with a call to DeleteSuperFile() (which is <emphasis
    role="underline">not</emphasis> valid for use within the transaction
    frame) then you will get an error, because the delete operation will occur
    outside the transaction frame, and before the ClearSuperFile() function
    has a chance to do its work.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Other_Useful_Functions">
    <title>Other Useful Functions</title>

    <para>The following functions, while not specifically designed for
    SuperFile use, are generally useful in creating and maintaining
    SuperFiles:</para>

    <programlisting>RemoteDirectory()
ExternalLogicalFilename()
LogicalFileList()
LogicalFileSuperOwners()
</programlisting>

    <para>Use of these functions will be described in the subsequent set of
    SuperFile articles.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
