<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Working_with_BLOBs">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">Working with BLOBs</emphasis></title>

  <para>BLOB (Binary Large OBject) support in ECL begins with the DATA value
  type. This type may contain any type of data, making it perfect for housing
  BLOB data.</para>

  <para>There are essentially three issues around working with BLOB
  data:</para>

  <para>1) How to get the data into the HPCC (spraying).</para>

  <para>2) How to work with the data, once it is in the HPCC.</para>

  <para>3) How to get the data back out of the HPCC (despraying).</para>

  <sect2 id="Spraying_BLOB_Data">
    <title>Spraying BLOB Data</title>

    <para>In the HPCCClientTools.PDF there is a chapter devoted to the
    DFUplus.exe program. This is a command line tool with specific options
    that allow you to spray and despray files into BLOBs in the HPCC. In all
    the examples below, we'll assume you have a DFUPLUS.INI file containing
    the standard content described in that section of the PDF.</para>

    <para>The key to making a spray operation write to BLOBs is the use of the
    <emphasis>prefix=Filename,Filesize</emphasis> option. For example, the
    following command line sprays all the .JPG and .BMP files from the
    c:\import directory of the 10.150.51.26 machine into a single logical file
    named LE::imagedb:</para>

    <programlisting>C:\&gt;dfuplus action=spray srcip=10.150.51.26 srcfile=c:\import\*.jpg,c:\import\*.bmp 
            dstcluster=le_thor dstname=LE::imagedb overwrite=1 
            PREFIX=FILENAME,FILESIZE nosplit=1</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Working_with_BLOB_Data">
    <title>Working with BLOB Data</title>

    <para>Once you've sprayed the data into the HPCC you must define the
    RECORD structure and DATASET. The following RECORD structure defines the
    result of the spray above:</para>

    <programlisting>imageRecord := RECORD
  STRING filename;
  DATA   image;   
       //first 4 bytes contain the length of the image data
  UNSIGNED8  RecPos{virtual(fileposition)};
END;
imageData := DATASET('LE::imagedb',imageRecord,FLAT);
</programlisting>

    <para>The key to this structure is the use of variable-length STRING and
    DATA value types. The filename field receives the complete name of the
    original .JPG or .BMP file that is now contained within the image field.
    The first four bytes of the image field contain an integer value
    specifying the number of bytes in the original file that are now in the
    image field.</para>

    <para>The DATA value type is used here for the BLOB field because the JPG
    and BMP formats are essentially binary data. However, if the BLOB were to
    contain XML data from multiple files, then it could be defined as a STRING
    value type. In that case, the first four bytes of the field would still
    contain an integer value specifying the number of bytes in the original
    file, followed by the XML data from the file.</para>

    <para>The addition of the RecPos field (a standard ECL “record pointer”
    field) allows us to create an INDEX, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>imageKey := INDEX(imageData,{filename,fpos},'LE::imageKey');  
BUILDINDEX(imageKey);</programlisting>

    <para>Having an INDEX allows you to work with the imageData file in keyed
    JOIN or FETCH operations. Of course, you can also perform any operation on
    the BLOB data files that you would do with any other file in ECL.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Despraying_BLOB_Data">
    <title>Despraying BLOB Data</title>

    <para>The DFUplus.exe program also allows you to despray BLOB files from
    the HPCC, splitting them back into the separate files they originated
    from. The key to making a despray operation write BLOBs to separate files
    is the use of the <emphasis>splitprefix=Filename,Filesize</emphasis>
    option. For example, the following command line desprays all the BLOB data
    to the c:\import\despray directory of the 10.150.51.26 machine from the
    single logical file named LE::imagedb:</para>

    <programlisting>C:\&gt;dfuplus action=despray dstip=10.150.51.26 dstfile=c:\import\despray\*.* 
            srcname=LE::imagedb PREFIX=FILENAME,FILESIZE nosplit=1</programlisting>

    <para>Once this command has executed, you should have the same set of
    files that were originally sprayed, recreated in a separate
    directory.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
