<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="SOAP-enabling_Queries">
  <title><emphasis role="bold">SOAP-enabling Queries</emphasis></title>

  <para>Queries destined for use in Roxie are SOAP-enabled first. The required
  ECL code to accomplish this is the STORED workflow service. Roxie queries
  may be contained in the FUNCTION structure or may simply be an executable
  query.</para>

  <sect2 id="The_ECL_Key_to_SOAP">
    <title>The ECL Key to SOAP</title>

    <para>The ECL code requirement for SOAP-enabled input parameters is the
    use of the STORED workflow service. Each SOAP parameter name must be the
    STORED name for an ECL definition. The STORED workflow service creates a
    data storage space in the workunit that the SOAP interface uses to
    populate the “passed” data. The ECL code simply uses those STORED
    definitions to determine whether data was passed from that “parameter” and
    what that data is. The data type of the passed SOAP parameter is implied
    by the STORED definition.</para>

    <para>For the following code example, you must create two definitions with
    STORED names duplicating the SOAP parameter name, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>STRING30 lname_value := '' : STORED('LastName');
  
STRING30 fname_value := '' : STORED('FirstName');
</programlisting>

    <para>These default to blank and the STORED workflow service opens a space
    in the workunit to store the value. The Enterprise Service Platform (ESP)
    handles the SOAP interface chores by plugging in the appropriate values
    into the storage space created by STORED. Therefore, the ECL code only
    needs to use the definitions (in this case, Lname and Fname) to accomplish
    the query. This makes the ECL side of the equation very simple.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Putting_It_All_Together">
    <title>Putting It All Together</title>

    <para>Once you understand the requirements, a SOAP-enabled query would
    look like this (contained in SOAPenabling.ECL):</para>

    <programlisting>IMPORT ProgrammersGuide.DeclareData AS ProgGuide;
     
EXPORT SOAPenabling() := FUNCTION
  STRING30 lname_value := '' : STORED('LastName');
  STRING30 fname_value := '' : STORED('FirstName');
  IDX  := ProgGuide.IDX__Person_LastName_FirstName;
  Base := ProgGuide.Person.FilePlus;
  Fetched := IF(fname_value = '',
           FETCH(Base,IDX(LastName=lname_value),RIGHT.RecPos),
                FETCH(Base,IDX(LastName=lname_value,
      FirstName=fname_value),RIGHT.RecPos));
  RETURN OUTPUT(CHOOSEN(Fetched,2000));
END;</programlisting>

    <para></para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
