<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="SORT">
  <title>SORT</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">SORT<indexterm>
      <primary>SORT</primary>
    </indexterm><indexterm>
      <primary>SORT function</primary>
    </indexterm>(</emphasis><emphasis>recordset,value </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">[</emphasis><emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">JOINED<indexterm>
      <primary>JOINED</primary>
    </indexterm>(</emphasis><emphasis> joinedset </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">)][</emphasis><emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">SKEW<indexterm>
      <primary>SKEW</primary>
    </indexterm>(</emphasis><emphasis> limit </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">[</emphasis><emphasis>,target</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">]</emphasis><emphasis> </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">)]</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> [</emphasis><emphasis>,
  </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">THRESHOLD<indexterm>
      <primary>THRESHOLD</primary>
    </indexterm>( </emphasis><emphasis>size</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">
  )]</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">[</emphasis><emphasis>,
  </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">LOCAL<indexterm>
      <primary>LOCAL</primary>
    </indexterm>] [</emphasis><emphasis>,</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">FEW<indexterm>
      <primary>FEW</primary>
    </indexterm>]</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> [, STABLE<indexterm>
      <primary>STABLE</primary>
    </indexterm> [ ( </emphasis><emphasis>algorithm</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold"> )] | UNSTABLE<indexterm>
      <primary>UNSTABLE</primary>
    </indexterm> [ ( </emphasis><emphasis>algorithm</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold"> )] ] )</emphasis></para>

  <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="89.75pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>recordset</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>The set of records to process. This may be the name of a
            dataset or a record set derived from some filter condition, or any
            expression that results in a derived record set.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>value</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A comma-delimited list of expressions or key fields in the
            recordset on which to sort, with the leftmost being the most
            significant sort criteria. A leading minus sign (-) indicates a
            descending-order sort on that element. You may have multiple value
            parameters to indicate sorts within sorts. You may use the keyword
            RECORD (or WHOLE RECORD) to indicate an ascending sort on all
            fields, and/or you may use the keyword EXCEPT to list non-sort
            fields in the recordset.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">JOINED</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Indicates this sort will use the same
            radix-points as already used by the <emphasis>joinedset</emphasis>
            so that matching records between the recordset and
            <emphasis>joinedset</emphasis> end up on the same supercomputer
            nodes. Used to optimize supercomputer joins where the
            <emphasis>joinedset</emphasis> is very large and the recordset is
            small.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>joinedset</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A set of records that has been previously sorted by the
            same value parameters as the recordset.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">SKEW</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Indicates that you know the data is not spread
            evenly across nodes (is skewed) and you choose to override the
            default by specifying your own limit value to allow the job to
            continue despite the skewing.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>limit</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A value between zero (0) and one (1.0 = 100%) indicating
            the maximum percentage of skew to allow before the job fails (the
            default is 0.1 = 10%).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>target</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. A value between zero (0) and one (1.0 = 100%)
            indicating the desired maximum percentage of skew to allow (the
            default is 0.1 = 10%).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">THRESHOLD</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Indicates the minimum size for a single part of
            the recordset before the SKEW limit is enforced.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>size</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>An integer value indicating the minimum number of bytes for
            a single part.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">LOCAL</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Specifies the operation is performed on each
            supercomputer node independently, without requiring interaction
            with all other nodes to acquire data; the operation maintains the
            distribution of any previous DISTRIBUTE. An error occurs if the
            recordset has been GROUPed.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">FEW</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Specifies that few records will be sorted. This
            prevents spilling the SORT to disk if another resource-intensive
            activity is executing concurrently.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">STABLE</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Specifies a stable sort—duplicates output in the
            same order they were in the input. This is the default if neither
            STABLE nor UNSTABLE sorting is specified. Ignored if not supported
            by the target platform.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>algorithm</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. A string constant that specifies the sorting
            algorithm to use (see the list of valid values below). If omitted,
            the default algorithm depends on which platform is targeted by the
            query.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">UNSTABLE</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Optional. Specifies an unstable sort—duplicates may output
            in any order. Ignored if not supported by the target
            platform.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Return:</entry>

            <entry>SORT returns a set of records.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para>The <emphasis role="bold">SORT </emphasis>function sorts the
  <emphasis>recordset</emphasis> according to the <emphasis>values</emphasis>
  specified. SORT is usually used to produce the record sets operated on by
  the DEDUP, GROUP, and ROLLUP function<indexterm>
      <primary>ROLLUP function</primary>
    </indexterm>s, so that those functions may operate optimally. Sorting
  final output is, of course, another common use.</para>

  <sect2 id="Sorting_Algorithms">
    <title>Sorting Algorithms</title>

    <para>There are three sort algorithms<indexterm>
        <primary>sort algorithms</primary>
      </indexterm> available: quicksort<indexterm>
        <primary>quicksort</primary>
      </indexterm>, insertionsort<indexterm>
        <primary>insertionsort</primary>
      </indexterm>, and heapsort<indexterm>
        <primary>heapsort</primary>
      </indexterm>. They are not all available on all platforms. Specifying an
    invalid algorithm for the targeted platform will be ignored and the
    default algorithm for that platform will be implemented.</para>

    <para><informaltable colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="84.55pt" />

          <colspec />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Thor<indexterm>
                  <primary>Thor</primary>
                </indexterm></emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Supports stable and unstable quicksort—the sort will
              spill to disk, if necessary. Parallel sorting happens
              automatically on clusters with multiple-CPU or multi-CPU-core
              nodes.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">hthor<indexterm>
                  <primary>hthor</primary>
                </indexterm></emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Supports stable and unstable quicksort, stable and
              unstable insertionsort, and stable heapsort—the sort will spill
              to disk, if necessary. Stable heapsort is the default if both
              STABLE and UNSTABLE are omitted or if STABLE is present without
              an algorithm parameter.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Unstable quicksort is the default if UNSTABLE is present
              without an algorithm parameter.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Roxie<indexterm>
                  <primary>Roxie</primary>
                </indexterm></emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Supports unstable quicksort, stable insertionsort, and
              stable heapsort—the sort does not spill to disk.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Stable heapsort is the default if both STABLE and
              UNSTABLE are omitted or if STABLE is present without an
              algorithm parameter. The insertionsort implements blocking and
              heapmerging when there are more than 1024 rows.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable></para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Quick_Sort">
    <title>Quick Sort</title>

    <para>A quick sort does nothing until it receives the last row of its
    input, and it produces no output until the sort is complete, so the time
    required to perform the sort cannot overlap with either the time to
    process its input or to produce its output. Under normal circumstances,
    this type of sort is expected to take the least CPU time. There are rare
    exceptional cases where it can perform badly (the famous "median-of-three
    killer" is an example) but you are very unlikely to hit these by
    chance.</para>

    <para>On a Thor cluster where each node has multiple CPUs or CPU cores, it
    is possible to split up the quick sort problem and run sections of the
    work in parallel. This happens automatically if the hardware supports it.
    Doing this does not improve the amount of actual CPU time used (in fact,
    it fractionally increases it because of the overhead of splitting the
    task) but the overall time required to perform the sort operation is
    significantly reduced. On a cluster with dual CPU/core nodes it should
    only take about half the time, only about a quarter of the time on a
    cluster with quad-processor nodes, etc.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Insertion_Sort">
    <title>Insertion Sort</title>

    <para>An insertion sort does all its work while it is receiving its input.
    Note that the algorithm used performs a binary search for insertion
    (unlike the classic insertion sort). Under normal circumstances, this sort
    is expected to produce the worst CPU time. In the case where the input
    source is slow but not CPU-bound (for example, a slow remote data read or
    input from a slow SOAPCALL), the time required to perform the sort is
    entirely overlapped with the input.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Heap_Sort">
    <title>Heap Sort</title>

    <para>A heap sort does about half its work while receiving input, and the
    other half while producing output. Under normal circumstances, it is
    expected to take more CPU time than a quick sort, but less than an
    insertion sort. Therefore, in queries where the input source is slow but
    not CPU-bound, half of the time taken to perform the sort is overlapped
    with the input. Similarly, in queries where the output processing is slow
    but not CPU-bound, the other half of the time taken to perform the sort is
    overlapped with the output. Also, if the sort processing terminates
    without consuming all of its input, then some of the work can be avoided
    entirely (about half in the limiting case where no output is consumed),
    saving both CPU and total time.</para>

    <para>In some cases, such as when a SORT is quickly followed by a CHOOSEN,
    the compiler will be able to spot that only a part of the sort's output
    will be required and replace it with a more efficient implementation. This
    will not be true in the general case.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Stable_vs_Unstable">
    <title>Stable vs. Unstable</title>

    <para>A stable sort is required when the input might contain duplicates
    (that is, records that have the same values for all the sort fields) and
    you need the duplicates to appear in the result in the same order as they
    appeared in the input. When the input contains no duplicates, or when you
    do not mind what order the duplicates appear in the result, an unstable
    sort will do.</para>

    <para>An unstable sort will normally be slightly faster than the stable
    version of the same algorithm. However, where the ideal sort algorithm is
    only available in a stable version, it may often be better than the
    unstable version of a different algorithm.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Performance_Considerations">
    <title>Performance Considerations</title>

    <para>The following discussion applies principally to local sorts, since
    Thor is the only platform that performs global sorts, and Thor does not
    provide a choice of algorithms.</para>

    <sect3 id="CPU_time_vs_Total_time">
      <title>CPU time vs. Total time</title>

      <para>In some situations a query might take the least CPU time using a
      quick sort, but it might take the most total time because the sort time
      cannot be overlapped with the time taken by an I/O-heavy task before or
      after it. On a system where only one subgraph or query is being run at
      once (Thor or hthor), this might make quick sort a poor choice since the
      extra time is simply wasted. On a system where many subgraphs or queries
      are running concurrently (such as a busy Roxie) there is a trade-off,
      because minimizing total time will minimize the latency for the
      particular query, but minimizing CPU time will maximize the throughput
      of the whole system.</para>

      <para>When considering the parallel quick sort, we can see that it
      should significantly reduce the latency for this query; but that if the
      other CPUs/cores were in use for other jobs (such as when dual Thors are
      running on the same dual CPU/core machines) it will not increase (and
      will slightly decrease) the throughput for the machines.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="Spilling_to_disk">
      <title>Spilling to disk</title>

      <para>Normally, records are sorted in memory. When there is not enough
      memory, spilling to disk may occur. This means that blocks of records
      are sorted in memory and written to disk, and the sorted blocks are then
      merged from disk on completion. This significantly slows the sort. It
      also means that the processing time for the heap sort will be longer, as
      it is no longer able to overlap with its output.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">When there is not enough memory to hold all
      the records and spilling to disk is not available (like on the Roxie
      platform), the query will fail.</emphasis></para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="How_sorting_affects_JOINs">
      <title>How sorting affects JOINs</title>

      <para>A normal JOIN operation requires that both its inputs be sorted by
      the fields used in the equality portion of the match condition. The
      supercomputer automatically performs these sorts "under the covers"
      unless it knows that an input is already sorted correctly. Therefore,
      some of the considerations that apply to the consideration of the
      algorithm for a SORT can also apply to a JOIN. To take advantage of
      these alternate sorting algorithms in a JOIN context you need to SORT
      the input dataset(s) the way you want, then specify the NOSORT option on
      the JOIN.</para>

      <para>Note well that no sorting is required for JOIN operations using
      the KEYED (or half-keyed), LOOKUP, or ALL options. Under some
      circumstances (usually in Roxie queries or in those cases where the
      optimizer thinks there are few records in the right input dataset) the
      supercomputer's optimizer will automatically perform a LOOKUP or ALL
      join instead of a regular join. This means that, if you have done your
      own SORT and specified the NOSORT option on the JOIN, that you will be
      defeating this possible optimization.</para>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <programlisting>MySet1 := SORT(Person,-last_name, first_name);
// descending last name, ascending first name

MySet2 := SORT(Person,RECORD,EXCEPT per_sex,per_marital_status);
// sort by all fields except sex and marital status

MySet3 := SORT(Person,last_name, first_name,STABLE('quicksort'));
// stable quick sort, not supported by Roxie

MySet4 := SORT(Person,last_name, first_name,UNSTABLE('heapsort'));
// unstable heap sort,
// not supported by any platform,
// therefore ignored

MySet5 := SORT(Person,last_name,first_name,STABLE('insertionsort'));
// stable insertion sort, not supported by Thor
</programlisting>

      <para>See Also: <link linkend="SORTED">SORTED</link>, <link
      linkend="RANK">RANK</link>, <link linkend="RANKED">RANKED</link>, <link
      linkend="EXCEPT">EXCEPT</link></para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
