<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Scope_and_Logical_Filenames">
  <title>Scope<indexterm>
      <primary>SCOPE</primary>
    </indexterm> and Logical Filenames<indexterm>
      <primary>LOGICAL Filenames</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <sect2 id="File_Scope">
    <title>File Scope<indexterm>
        <primary>File Scope</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">The logical filenames used in DATASET and
    INDEX attribute definitions and the OUTPUT and BUILD (or BUILDINDEX)
    actions may begin with a scope name, indicated by a leading tilde (~), and
    may contain directories. The scope and directories are delimited by double
    colons (::). The presence of a scope in the filename allows you to
    override the default scope name for the cluster.</emphasis></para>

    <para>For example, assuming you are operating on a cluster whose default
    scope name is “Training” then the following two OUTPUT actions result in
    the same scope:</para>

    <programlisting>OUTPUT(SomeFile,,'SomeDir::SomeFileOut1');
OUTPUT(SomeFile,,'~Training::SomeDir::SomeFileOut2');</programlisting>

    <para>The presence of the leading tilde in the filename only defines the
    scope name and does not change the set of disks to which the data is
    written (<emphasis role="bold">files are </emphasis><emphasis
    role="bold">always</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> written to the disks
    of the cluster on which the code executes</emphasis>). The DATASET
    declaration<indexterm>
        <primary>DATASET declaration</primary>
      </indexterm>s for these files might look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>RecStruct := {STRING line};
ds1 := DATASET('SomeDir::SomeFileOut1',RecStruct,THOR);
ds2 := DATASET('~Training::SomeDir::SomeFileOut2',RecStruct,THOR);</programlisting>

    <para>These two files are in the same scope, so that when you use the
    DATASETs in a workunit the Distributed File Utility (DFU) will look for
    both files in the Training scope.</para>

    <para>However, once you know the scope name you can reference files from
    any other cluster within the same environment. For example, assuming you
    are operating on a cluster whose default scope name is “Production” and
    you want to use the data in the above two files. Then the following two
    DATASET definitions allow you to access that data:</para>

    <programlisting>FileX := DATASET('~Training::SomeDir::SomeFileOut1',RecStruct,THOR);
FileY := DATASET('~Training::SomeDir::SomeFileOut2',RecStruct,THOR);</programlisting>

    <para>Notice the presence of the scope name in both of these definitions.
    This is required because the files are in another scope.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Foreign_Files">
    <title>Foreign Files<indexterm>
        <primary>Foreign files</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Similar to the scoping rules described above, you can also reference
    files in separate environments serviced by a different Dali. This allows a
    read-only reference to remote files (both logical files and
    superfiles).</para>

    <para>The syntax looks like this:</para>

    <para><emphasis
    role="bold">‘~foreign::&lt;dali-ip&gt;::&lt;scope&gt;::&lt;tail&gt;’</emphasis></para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile :=DATASET('~foreign::10.150.50.11::training::thor::myfile',
                 RecStruct,FLAT);</programlisting>

    <para>gives read-only access to the remote
    <emphasis>training::thor::myfile</emphasis> file in the
    <emphasis>10.150.50.11</emphasis> environment.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Landing_Zone_Files">
    <title>Landing Zone Files<indexterm>
        <primary>Landing Zone files</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>You can also directly read and write files on a landing zone (or any
    other IP-addressable box) that have not been sprayed to Thor. The landing
    zone must be running the dafileserv utility program. If the box is a
    Windows box, dafileserv must be installed as a service.</para>

    <para>The syntax looks like this:</para>

    <para><emphasis
    role="bold">‘~file::&lt;LZ-ip&gt;::&lt;path&gt;::&lt;filename&gt;’</emphasis></para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile :=DATASET('~file::10.150.50.12::c$::training::import::myfile',RecStruct,FLAT);</programlisting>

    <para>gives access to the remote
    <emphasis>c$/training/import/myfile</emphasis> file on the linux-based
    <emphasis>10.150.50.12</emphasis> landing zone.</para>

    <para>ECL logical filenames are case insensitive and physical names
    default to lower case, which can cause problems when the landing zone is a
    Linux box (Linux is case sensitive). The case of characters can be
    explicitly uppercased by escaping them with a leading caret (^), as in
    this example:</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile :=DATASET('~file::10.150.50.12::c$::^Advanced^E^C^L::myfile',RecStruct,FLAT);</programlisting>

    <para>gives access to the remote
    <emphasis>c$/AdvancedECL/myfile</emphasis> file on the linux-based
    <emphasis>10.150.50.12</emphasis> landing zone.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Dynamic_Files">
    <title>Dynamic Files<indexterm>
        <primary>Dynamic Files</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>In Roxie queries (only) you can also read files that may not exist
    at query deployment time, but that will exist at query runtime by making
    the filename DYNAMIC.</para>

    <para>The syntax looks like this:</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">DYNAMIC(‘&lt;filename&gt;’ )</emphasis></para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile :=DATASET(DYNAMIC('~training::import::myfile'),RecStruct,FLAT);</programlisting>

    <para>This causes the file to be resolved when the query is executed
    instead of when it is deployed.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Temporary_SuperFiles">
    <title>Temporary SuperFile<indexterm>
        <primary>Temporary SuperFile</primary>
      </indexterm>s</title>

    <para>A SuperFile<indexterm>
        <primary>SuperFile</primary>
      </indexterm> is a collection of logical files treated as a single entity
    (see the <emphasis role="bold">SuperFile Overview</emphasis> article in
    the <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis>). You can specify a temporary
    SuperFile by naming the set of sub-files within curly braces in the string
    that names the logical file for the DATASET declaration<indexterm>
        <primary>DATASET declaration</primary>
      </indexterm>. The syntax looks like this:</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">DATASET<indexterm>
        <primary>DATASET</primary>
      </indexterm>( '{</emphasis><emphasis> listoffiles </emphasis><emphasis
    role="bold">} '</emphasis>, recstruct, THOR);</para>

    <para><emphasis>listoffiles</emphasis> A comma-delimited list of the set
    of logical files to treat as a single SuperFile. The logical filenames
    must follow the rules listed above for logical filenames with the one
    exception that the tilde indicating scope name override may be specified
    either on each appropriate file in the list, or outside the curly
    braces.</para>

    <para>For example, assuming the default scope name is “thor,” the
    following examples both define the same SuperFile:</para>

    <programlisting>MyFile :=DATASET('{in::file1,
                   in::file2,
                  ~train::in::file3}'),
                 RecStruct,THOR);

MyFile :=DATASET('~{thor::in::file1,
                   thor::in::file2,
                   train::in::file3}'),
                 RecStruct,THOR);</programlisting>

    <para>You cannot use this form of logical filename to do an OUTPUT or
    PERSIST; this form is read-only.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
