<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Wrapper</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>Wrapper</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../../images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email> Please include
      <emphasis role="bold">Documentation Feedback</emphasis> in the subject
      line and reference the document name, page numbers, and current Version
      Number in the text of the message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license. Other products,
      logos, and services may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their
      respective companies. All names and example data used in this manual are
      fictitious. Any similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="FooterInfo"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="DateVer"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <corpname>HPCC Systems<superscript>®</superscript></corpname>

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="Copyright"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../../images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="WrapperECLWatchQueries">
    <title>Wrapper</title>

    <para>wrapper</para>

    <sect1 id="Queries_Page" role="nobrk">
      <title>Queries Page in ECL Watch</title>

      <para>The Queries page lists published queries for each target cluster.
      On this page you can see the published queries . You can also perform
      some actions on the selected queries.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Browse Query Sets</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA432.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The Queries interface provides some information at a glance, there
      are three columns on the left side of each listed query. These three
      columns provide information about these queries.</para>

      <!--Per Miguel: The Icons are very likely to be removed from the Main Queries page, 
can probably just move the table here to the query detail page... 
depending on where they wind up.-->

      <para><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
          <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

            <colspec />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="../../images/ECLWA-pause.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates a paused query</para><para>
                </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="../../images/ECLWA-active.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates an activated query</para><para>
                </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic
                fileref="../../images/ECLWA-suspend.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>Indicates a query suspended by the
                system</para><para> </para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>

      <para>The queries page also provides other information at a
      glance:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the query ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the query name</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the target</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the workunit id (WUID)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the dll</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Published by</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>All the above available at a glance on the main queries
      page, with further actions that can be performed from the action buttons
      along the top of the tab. You can sort a column by clicking on the
      column heading. Click once for ascending, click again to toggle to
      descending. The direction of the arrow indicates the sort order.</para>

      <!--VERIFY THAT THIS BEHAVIOR APPLIES HERE: YES, was not implemented but added when I brought this up.***-->

      <para>To see the details page for a particular query, or to perform some
      action on it you must select it. You can select a query or queries by
      checking the check box. You can also open a particular query by double
      clicking on it.</para>

      <sect2 id="QueryDetails" role="brk">
        <title>Query Details</title>

        <para>To examine the Query Details page, you select and open the query
        or queries. This opens a tab containing the query details. From the
        query details page you can get more information about the specific
        query. You can also perform some actions on that query. There are
        several tabs with additional information about the selected
        query.</para>

        <sect3 id="QuerySummaryTab">
          <title>Query Summary Tab</title>

          <para>The default query tab opened when you select a query is the
          Summary tab. The summary tab shows you some detail information about
          the query.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Query detail page</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLW006.jpg"
                             vendor="eclwatchSS" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>There are a few actions that you can perform on the query
          from this tab. Press the action buttons for the desired activity for
          the selected query.</para>

          <para><variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Refresh</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Refreshes the information displayed for the selected
                  query.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Saves the selected query (or queries).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Delete</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Deletes the selected query (or queries).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="ErrorsTab">
          <title>Errors Tab</title>

          <para>For each selected query there is an Errors tab. The Errors tab
          displays any errors that may have been encountered during the
          compiling and publishing of that query. If there aren't any errors
          the errors tab will be blank. If there are errors, you can further
          examine any specific error by checking the box and selecting it, and
          then press the open action button. You could also just double click
          on the selected error. <figure>
              <title>Query Error</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006E.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="GraphsTab">
          <title>Graphs Tab</title>

          <para>The graphs tab provides access to graphical interpretations of
          the query. This can be helpful in visualizing how the query ran. The
          graphs tab displays a list of any graphs generated by the selected
          query, along with some additional information like timing. To
          display a specific graph, you must select it, and choose to open it,
          or you can double click on listed graph.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Graphs list</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006G.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Opening a graph will open a new tab showing the selected
          graph(s).</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Graphs</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006G1.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>When you open a graph the visible area splits into three
          smaller sections each displaying some relevant component of the
          query graph. Notice the myriad of graph controls, and tabs in the
          border area of each tab. Manipulate these controls to view different
          aspects of the graphs.</para>

          <para>The Advanced action button on the main graph control area,
          provides access to even more advanced graphing options.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="ECLWatch_Queries_LogicalFiles">
          <title>Logical Files Tab</title>

          <para>The Published queries details page provides a link to the
          queries Logical Files tab. The Logical Files tab shows all logical
          files that are used by the query. To view the logical file details
          for any file listed, select one or more files by checking the
          checkbox and press the Open action button. Tabs for each file
          selected opens where you can view and make changes to the file(s)
          without the need to go back to the logical files page.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Queries:Logical Files Tab</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006L.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The above image shows the list of Logical files on the Logical
          Files tab. To view more detail about a logical file listed here,
          check the box next to the file, and then press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Open</emphasis> action button. You can also just double
          click on the logical file you want to view.</para>

          <para>Once open, you can select any of the tabs to see Summary,
          Contents, ECL, DEF, XML, File Parts, Queries, or the
          Workunit.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Queries:Logical Files:Contents Tab</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006j.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="Test_Pages">
          <title>Test Pages</title>

          <para>The Test Pages tab provides a number of resources you can use
          to test your query including SOAP/JSON/WSDL and the legacy WS-ECL
          form, as well as other tabs showing useful information or sample
          details about the query.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Test Pages tab</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA012.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>Information available from the Test pages tab.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">SOAP</emphasis> This tab provides an
              interactive interface to submit the query (with input data) and
              see the response in XML format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">JSON</emphasis> This tab provides an
              interactive interface to submit the query (with input data) and
              see the response in JSON format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">WSDL</emphasis> This tab provides a
              WSDL definition describing the functionality offered by the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Request Schema </emphasis>This tab
              provides a schema in XSD format describing a request for the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Response Schema</emphasis> This tab
              provides a schema in XSD format describing a response from the
              query (web service).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Sample Request </emphasis>This tab
              provides a sample request for the query (web service) in XML
              Format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Sample Response</emphasis> This tab
              provides a sample response from the query (web service) in XML
              Format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Parameter XML</emphasis> This tab
              provides Parameterized XML representation of the query
              interface.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Legacy Form</emphasis> This tab
              provides a form that can be used to submit a query and get a
              response. This is similar to the WsECL form.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Links</emphasis> Provides a list of
              useful links such as: the Form, a sample REST URL, sample
              request, sample response, parameter XML, SOAP POST, WSDL, XSD,
              and the result schema.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="QueriesWorkUnits">
          <title>The Workunits link</title>

          <para>The Published queries details page provides a link to to the
          workunits, page. This tab is a shortcut that takes you to the same
          workunits tab you can get to through the ECL workunits menu.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Queries Workunit</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA006W.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>This is the same as the <emphasis role="bold">ECL
          Workunits</emphasis> page from the navigation sub-menu Workunits
          link. You can perform the same operations here. Notice that there
          are some other familiar tabs here as well, for example the Graphs
          tab, both from the Queries details page, and from the workunit tab
          nested here.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="Package_Maps">
        <title>Package Maps</title>

        <para>From the Queries icon link, you can access the package maps
        page. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Package Maps</emphasis> button
        on the navigation sub-menu bar, to access to the Package Maps on your
        cluster. <figure>
            <title>Package Maps</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWA470.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>The package maps page, displays all the package maps loaded on
        your cluster. You can Add, Activate, Deactivate, Delete, or Open a
        package map. To examine a package map, select a package map from the
        list.</para>

        <para>You can select the <emphasis role="bold">Validate Package
        Map</emphasis> tab to validate a package map.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Validate Package Maps</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWaPkMgr.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Choose the <emphasis role="bold">Target</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">Process</emphasis> from the drop lists on the Validate
        Package Map tab.</para>

        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Validate</emphasis> button to
        validate the package map. The result is shown on the <emphasis
        role="bold">Validate Active Package Map</emphasis> tab. You can also
        Validate the package content, on the V<emphasis role="bold">alidate
        Package Content</emphasis> tab.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
