<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en_US" xml:base="../">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>HPCC Monitoring and Reporting (Technical Preview)</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email> </para>

      <para>Please include <emphasis role="bold">Documentation
      Feedback</emphasis> in the subject line and reference the document name,
      page numbers, and current Version Number in the text of the
      message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license.</para>

      <para> HPCC Systems is a registered trademark of LexisNexis Risk Data
      Management Inc.</para>

      <para>Other products, logos, and services may be trademarks or
      registered trademarks of their respective companies. </para>

      <para>All names and example data used in this manual are fictitious. Any
      similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="FooterInfo"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="DateVer"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <corpname>HPCC Systems</corpname>

    <xi:include href="common/Version.xml" xpointer="Copyright"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="GangliaIntroduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The HPCC systems platform supports graphical monitoring and
    reporting components.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Ganglia:</emphasis></para>

    <para>The HPCC monitoring component leverages Ganglia, an open source,
    scalable, distributed monitoring system to display system information in a
    graphical manner.</para>

    <para>With the the graphical monitoring component you can: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>See system information at a glance</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>View a grid of Roxie clusters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Examine Roxie metrics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Keep a historical record of metrics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Drill down to individual server metrics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Quickly detect troubled nodes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>More applications, such as better informed resource planning
          and allocation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Nagios</emphasis></para>

    <para>The HPCC reporting and alerting component leverages Nagios, a
    powerful monitoring and notification system, which can help you identify
    and resolve infrastructure problems before they affect critical
    processes.</para>

    <para>With the HPCC reporting and alerting component you can set up alerts
    to inform of any changes to:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>SSH connectivity</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Users on system</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System Load</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disk Usage</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Roxie</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dali</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dafilesrv</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sasha</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bound services on each ESP</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <!--***NOTE: At some point this next bit will need to get moved into the next chapter/section***-->

    <sect1 id="HPCC_Viewer">
      <title>The HPCC Ganglia Viewer</title>

      <para>A Ganglia viewer comes preinstalled and configured in the 4.2.x
      (or later) HPCC Virtual Machine. The monitoring provided with the
      Virtual Machine is set up to monitor Roxie instances on the network.
      This document introduces the monitoring and describes how to get it
      working on your system. <figure>
          <title>HPCC Monitoring</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/GAN001.jpg" vendor="Ganglia" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The above image is an overview summary of all the monitored Roxie
      nodes in the cluster named VM Demo.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Ganglya_Overview">
    <title>Ganglia</title>

    <para>The HPCC Monitoring component leverages Ganglia, an open source,
    scalable, distributed monitoring system, to produce a graphical view of a
    Roxie cluster's servers. Ganglia leverages widely accepted technologies
    for data representation. It provides near real-time monitoring and
    visualizations for performance metrics. If your enterprise already has a
    Ganglia monitoring server, you can easily add Roxie clusters to its
    monitoring.</para>

    <sect1 id="Ganglia_Overview">
      <title>Ganglia Overview</title>

      <para>Ganglia Monitoring has two primary components: the viewer and the
      Ganglia Monitoring Daemon (gmond). Installation and configuration will
      vary depending on your system.</para>

      <para>On an <emphasis role="bold">RPM-based system</emphasis>, install
      the <emphasis>ganglia-gmond-modules-python</emphasis> RPM running a
      command such as:</para>

      <programlisting>sudo rpm -i ganglia-gmond-modules-python-3.4.0-1.x86_64.rpm</programlisting>

      <para>On a <emphasis role="bold">Debian-based system</emphasis>, install
      the <emphasis>ganglia-monitor</emphasis> running a command such
      as:</para>

      <programlisting>sudo apt-get install ganglia-monitor</programlisting>

      <para>The specific steps required to install and configure Ganglia are
      covered in the Ganglia wiki:</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules">http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules</ulink></para>

      <sect2 id="Ganglia_Viewer">
        <title>The Viewer</title>

        <para>If you already have a Ganglia monitoring server running in your
        network, the viewer component may already be in place. If you do not
        have Ganglia then you will need to install and configure the
        viewer.</para>

        <para>Refer to the <ulink
        url="https://github.com/hpcc-systems/ganglia-monitoring/tree/master/vm_precise">https://github.com/hpcc-systems/ganglia-monitoring/tree/master/vm_precise</ulink>
        directory. There you will see the resources used to configure the
        Ganglia for the virtual machine and can use them as the examples to
        configure it for your enterprise.</para>

        <para>The script, <emphasis>install_graphs_helper.sh</emphasis>
        available from the github link above and also provided with the
        virtual machine, is what is used to embed the viewer component. Using
        this script as a basis, you can then similarly configure and deploy
        the viewer component for your system.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="Ganglia_Monitoring_Daemon">
        <title>Ganglia Monitoring Daemon</title>

        <para>The monitoring daemon is required on the Roxie nodes you wish to
        monitor. Install the <emphasis>gmond</emphasis> daemon on the nodes
        you wish to monitor. Installation and configuration are described
        in;</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules">http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules</ulink></para>

        <para>If you have a Ganglia monitoring server running in your
        environment, you already have the required components and
        prerequisites. Verify that you have
        <emphasis>/etc/ganglia/conf.d</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>/etc/ganglia/.pyconf</emphasis> files in place and then add
        the Roxie nodes you wish to monitor. You can do that by installing the
        Ganglia components and HPCC Monitoring components on to each Roxie
        node.</para>

        <para>If you do not have Ganglia, or want to install it, read the
        Ganglia documentation provided at the above link, and install it and
        any system dependencies. You will then need to download and install
        the HPCC Monitoring component.</para>

        <sect3 id="Installing-HPCCGanglia" role="brk">
          <title>Installing the HPCC Monitoring component</title>

          <para>The HPCC Monitoring component is available for download. The
          HPCC Monitoring components leverage the Ganglia monitoring tools,
          and would only be needed if you do not already have Ganglia
          monitoring components on your system.</para>

          <para>To get the HPCC Monitoring components, find the appropriate
          package for your system.</para>

          <para>Packages are available for download from the HPCC Systems
          site:</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="http://hpccsystems.com/download">hpccsystems.com/download</ulink></para>

          <para>or</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/all">http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/all</ulink></para>

          <para>Find and install the appropriate package for your
          system.</para>

          <para>For example, if you have a CentOS 6.x system, get the RPM
          package.</para>

          <programlisting>hpccsystems-ganglia-monitoring-4.2.0-rc1.el6.x86_64.rpm</programlisting>

          <para>Install the monitoring package on the system that you want to
          monitor. Optionally, you can look at that installation package
          provided and use that as a guide to implement your own customized
          monitoring components.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="VirtuaLMetrics">
      <title>Metrics in the Virtual Machine</title>

      <para>An easy way to understand how the metrics work and how to
      implement them on a larger system, is to examine the metrics in
      action.</para>

      <para>Ganglia integration is built into the current HPCC Virtual Machine
      images. Download and start up a virtual image and look at how the
      monitoring component works.</para>

      <para>This allows you:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A preview of the metrics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A quickstart</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A guide for set up</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Evaluate the value of the content and decide what aspects of
      measurement are relevant to your needs.</para>

      <!--INCLUDE-VM_STEPS-as-Sect2-->

      <!--H11780-->

      <xi:include href="HPCCMonitoring/MonRep-Mods/MonRep-VM.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="GangliaIntegration">
      <title>Ganglia Integration with HPCC</title>

      <para>The Roxie nodes are able to report metrics to Ganglia when the
      nodes have Ganglia monitoring and the associated dependencies
      installed.</para>

      <para>Review the Ganglia wiki: <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules">http://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/ganglia/wiki/ganglia_gmond_python_modules</ulink>
      to understand the requirements.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Install the Ganglia components on every node.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configure the Ganglia as appropriate for your system</para>

          <para>The Ganglia configuration files can be typically found in the
          <emphasis>/etc/ganglia/</emphasis> directory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the HPCC Systems monitoring component on every
          node.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Deploy the monitoring daemon (gmond) and the HPCC Monitoring
          package to each of the nodes you wish to monitor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The VM graphs can be used to monitor Roxie clusters. You can add
      more Roxie nodes installed anywhere on the same network utilizing
      multi-cast.</para>

      <para>To add a new Roxie node, install the HPCC Monitoring package on to
      each Roxie node to monitor. In most basic configurations you may need to
      add the node(s) IP address(es) to the
      <emphasis>/etc/ganglia/gmetad.conf</emphasis> file. As long as the new
      Roxie node can communicate with (for example ping) the Monitoring
      component host, the graphs for that will automatically be added to the
      graph display.</para>

      <para><variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>NOTE:</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Some of the graphs take some time to populate with data.
              These graphs may appear blank or empty at first, but will render
              properly as more data accumulates to populate the graph.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Nagios</title>

    <para>The HPCC Reporting component leverages Nagios, an open source,
    system and network infrastructure monitoring application to monitor and
    alert HPCC administrators. Nagios leverages established and accepted open
    source technologies to alert users to changes or potential issues. It
    provides near real-time system monitoring and reporting.</para>

    <para>With the HPCC integration, you can generate Nagios configuration
    files to monitor HPCC server health. Once the Nagios is configured, you
    can monitor:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>SSH connectivity</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Users on system</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System Load</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disk Usage</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Roxie</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dali</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dafilesrv</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sasha</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bound services on each ESP</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Nagios is a powerful monitoring and notification system, which can
    be used with HPCC to help identify and resolve infrastructure problems
    before they affect critical processes. Nagios hardware notifications can
    help keep your system highly available and alerts can assist in
    pre-emptive maintenance for processes which are down or behaving outside
    expected parameters to ensure system stability, reliability, and uptime.
    Scripts and tools are provided to extract HPCC Platform system metrics and
    easily integrate that data into Nagios.</para>

    <sect1 id="NagiosVM">
      <title>Nagios in the Virtual Machine</title>

      <para>An easy way to understand how the Nagios works and how to
      implement it on a larger system, is to examine an established session in
      action.</para>

      <para>Nagios integration is built into the current HPCC Virtual Machine
      images. Download and start up a virtual image and look at how the
      monitoring component works.</para>

      <para>The Nagios component for HPCC on the VM allows you:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A preview of the alerts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A quickstart</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A guide for set up</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Evaluate the value of the content and decide what aspects are
      relevant to your needs.</para>

      <!--INCLUDE-VM_STEPS-as-Sect2-->

      <sect2 id="hpcc-2id">
        <xi:include href="HPCCMonitoring/MonRep-Mods/MonRep-VM.xml"
                    xpointer="xpointer(/sect2/node())"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Nagios Interface</title>

        <para>There are a number of Nagios configurations available. To get a
        better understanding of Nagios configuration, look at the
        configuration delivered with the VM. To login to the Nagios admin
        page:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to
            <emphasis>http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn/</emphasis>nagios3</para>

            <para>Where the <emphasis>nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn</emphasis> is your ESP
            server running ECL Watch.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Login with username : nagiosadmin</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the password : nagiosadmin</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Once logged in the Nagios landing page displays. This page
        displays information about Nagios and contains links to the various
        components, items, and documentation.</para>

        <para>To view the configuration, click on the <emphasis
        role="bold">Host Groups</emphasis> link from the Nagios navigation
        menu on the left side of the page.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Nagios Host Groups</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/NAG001.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>This displays the Host Groups being monitored.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Nagios Host Groups</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/NAG002.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <sect3>
          <title>Nagios Services</title>

          <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Services</emphasis> link
          from the Nagios navigation menu on the left side of the page.
          <figure>
              <title>Nagios Services</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/NAG003.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>The services link displays the Service Status details for the
          systems being monitored. <figure>
              <title>Nagios Service status</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/NAG004.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>You can see the service status for the systems being
          monitored.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Installation of Nagios</title>

      <para>The HPCC Nagios package provides tools and utilities for
      generating Nagios configurations. These configurations check HPCC and
      perform some of the HPCC specific checks. HPCC Nagios installation is
      provided on the HPCC Systems portal.</para>

      <sect2 id="HPCC_Nagios_Installation">
        <title>HPCC Nagios Installation Package</title>

        <para>To get the HPCC Nagios monitoring on your system you need the
        Installation package. Download the installation package from the HPCC
        Systems portal.</para>

        <para>The HPCC Systems web portal is where you can find HPCC
        resources, downloads, plug-ins, as well as helpful information.</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/monitoring">http://hpccsystems.com/</ulink></para>

        <para>You can find the HPCC Monitoring and Reporting Installation
        packages at:</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/monitoring">http://hpccsystems.com/download/free-community-edition/monitoring</ulink></para>

        <para>Download the appropriate installation package for your operating
        system.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Install Nagios</title>

        <para>To Install Nagios for HPCC, you must have HPCC System platform
        installed and also have the open-source Nagios package
        installed.</para>

        <para><orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Install the <emphasis
              role="bold">hpcc-nagios-monitoring</emphasis> on the node that
              will be doing the monitoring. The node where you install the
              Nagios monitoring must have network connectivity to all the
              monitored nodes.</para>

              <para>With the hpcc-nagios tools installed, you have HPCC check
              utilities in:</para>

              <para><programlisting> /usr/lib/nagios/plugins/ </programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Generate Nagios configuration files.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>Generate a host groups configuration for
        Nagios.</para>

        <programlisting> /opt/HPCCSystem/bin/hpcc-nagios-tools -env   \
 /etc/HPCCSystems/environment.xml -h -out /etc/nagios3/config.d/hpcc_hostgroups.cfg 
</programlisting>

        <para>Generate a services configuration file.</para>

        <programlisting> /opt/HPCCSystem/bin/hpcc-nagios-tools -env   \
 /etc/HPCCSystems/environment.xml -g -out /etc/nagios3/config.d/hpcc_services.cfg
</programlisting>

        <para>You can use some or all of the configurations. You can use the
        generated configurations, or you could merge them into any existing
        Nagios configuration as needed.</para>

        <para><orderedlist continuation="continues">
            <listitem>
              <para>Integrate the host and services configuration files into
              the Nagios configuration folders.</para>

              <para>You must restart Nagios for the new configuration to take
              effect.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Help</title>

          <para>For help with HPCC Nagios enter:</para>

          <programlisting> /opt/HPCCSystems/bin/hpcc-nagios-tools</programlisting>

          <para>Entering the command without any parameters or options
          specified displays all the available options.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
