<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
    <title>system/jlib</title>

    <para>
        The system/jlib directory contains the sources for the system/jlib library. jlib is the core 
    common library used by all hpcc components, and all OS-dependent code should be in here. As
    well as isolating the rest of the system from OS dependencies by providing platform-neutral
    implementations of such things as file IO, threading, synchronization primitives etc, jlib
    provides common data structures and algorithms like hash tables, expanding arrays, etc.
    </para>
  
  <para>
    The 'j' in jlib stands for 'Java' - when the system was first created we were in two minds 
    whether it should be coded in Java (the first prototypes were) or C++, and one of the original 
    intentions for jlib was to make it easier for us to translate to Java if we ever wanted to 
    change back. That is also the reason why we adopted a 'Java-style' coding paradigm of writing
    member functions inline within class definitions.
  </para>

  <para>
    The core of jlib is the IInterface interface and the associated CInterface base implementation,
    which provides for reference-counted objects that are released when the last reference is
    released. Most of the jlib data structures expect to work with reference-counted objects, and
    most interfaces throughout the HPCC system will therefore be derived from IInterface.
  </para>

  <para>
    By convention, when a function returns a pointer or reference to an object and gives ownership 
    of it to the caller, the function name will be prefixed with get, and the function will have 
    called Link() on the object before returning it. The caller should then release the object when 
    it has finished with it. Conversely, functions that return pointers or references to objects 
    without granting ownership are prefixed query. Such objects should not be released by the caller
    but are guaranteed to remain alive for as long as the object providing the queryXXX() function.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    To ensure that objects are released properly, especially where exceptions are involved, the 
    Owned&lt;&gt; and Linked&lt;&gt; templates should be used wherever appropriate. Owned is 
    constructed from a pointer or reference whose link count has already beein incremented,
    such as that returned by a getXXX() function, while the Linked constructor will call Link() for
    the pointer it is managing. Thus Owned&lt;MyObjectType&gt; o = getXXX(); and Linked&lt;MyObjectYpe&gt;
    o2 = queryXXX(); are roughly equivalent (the former is generally preferred).
  </para>

  <para>
    Proper use of Link and Release is crucial for the proper operation of the system. If you Link an
    object but forget to Release, you will create a memory leak. If you Release an object that you 
    did not Link(), you will end up with a "negative memory leak" resulting in the potential for 
    heap corruption, dangling pointers and other generally bad news.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Key jlib classes, interfaces and templates</title>
    <section>
      <title>Array classes</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Strings and Memory Buffers</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Hash tables</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Mutexes and other synchronization primitives</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Threads and thread pools</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>File IO</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sockets</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Property Trees and XML support</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Compiler support</title>
      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
