<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Nagios_in_ECLWatch">
  <title>Nagios in ECL Watch</title>

  <para>ECL Watch is set up for monitoring your system with Nagios. ECL Watch
  has an API that can interface with Nagios and provide Nagios monitoring
  right in ECL Watch. Nagios escalations can be pointed to any ECL Watch
  version 5.4 (and later) and are viewable directly in ECL Watch.</para>

  <para>By default all ECL Watch services defined in the environment.xml will
  receive notifications generated using
  <emphasis>hpcc-nagios-tools</emphasis>. You can override that if not
  desired. The ECL Watch instances need not be in the cluster that is being
  monitored. <figure>
      <title>Nagios in ECL Watch</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../images/NAG010.jpg" vendor="VM_welcome" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure></para>

  <para>Once you have Nagios configured for your environment, you can see at a
  glance if there are any alerts. Along the top banner of the ECL Watch
  window, you will see a small indicator light. The light is darkend (gray) if
  there is no system data being reported, typically indicative that your
  system is not yet configured for monitoring.</para>

  <para>The light is green when all systems are reporting normal. The light is
  yellow when there is warning. The light turns red when there is an alert.
  All the alerts are configurable through the Nagios configuration.</para>

  <para>By default ECL Watch monitoring maintains the latest update for 30
  minutes. This means that once Nagios stops escalations to ECL Watch any
  status, including Normal will expire from the list. Nagios escalations
  notification behavior and frequency is configurable, refer to the Nagios
  documentation for more information. An empty list could indicate 'no data'
  or 'no outages', by default no alerts generate when everything is up and
  running.</para>

  <para>To delve further into any warnings or alerts, you can press the
  indicator light at the top. You can also access the <emphasis>Primary
  Monitoring</emphasis> page by pressing the <emphasis
  role="bold">Operations</emphasis> link, then press the <emphasis
  role="bold">Monitoring</emphasis> link in the navigation sub-menu. <figure>
      <title>Nagios in ECL Watch</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../images/NAG011.jpg" vendor="VM_welcome" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure></para>

  <para>This displays the all the messages and alerts reported to the
  monitoring system. For more information on a specific message, press the
  arrow next to the message you want.</para>
</sect1>
