<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="likely">
  <title>LIKELY and UNLIKELY</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">LIKELY<indexterm>
      <primary>LIKELY</primary>
    </indexterm>(</emphasis><emphasis>filtercondition</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">, [</emphasis><emphasis> likelihood </emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">] </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">);</emphasis></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">UNLIKELY<indexterm>
      <primary>UNLIKELY</primary>
    </indexterm>(</emphasis><emphasis>filtercondition</emphasis><emphasis
  role="bold">);</emphasis><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="79.05pt" />

        <colspec colwidth="309.75pt" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>filtercondition</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>A filter condition for the hint.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis>likelihood</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>The probability value expressed in a decimal value between
            0 and 1.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para>The LIKELY/UNLIKELY hint can be wrapped around a filter condition to
  indicate to the code generator the likelihood that the filter condition will
  filter the record.</para>

  <para>LIKELY specifies that the filter condition is likely to match most
  records. UNLIKELY specifies that very few records are likely to be
  matched.</para>

  <para>Specific probability value may be provided for LIKELY. The probability
  value is decimal value greater than 0 and less than 1. The closer this value
  is to 1.0 the more likely that the filter condition is likely to match a
  record. The closer the value is to 0.0 the less likely the filter condition
  is to match records. The code generator makes use of the likelihood
  information to produce better code.</para>

  <para>The code generator uses the LIKELY/UNLIKELY hint together with the
  count of usage, to determine the cost of spilling and the cost of
  re-filtering the dataset every time it is used. Spills are only be generated
  when the cost of spilling is lower than the cost of re-filtering the dataset
  every time.</para>

  <para>For example, say there is a dataset of people with millions of
  records. A filter is created to retain all records where the age is less
  than 100. The filter is expected to retain 99.9% of records. This filter
  result is used by 3 different activities. The cost of spilling the results
  of the filter is likely to be significantly higher than the simply
  re-filtering the input dataset every time it used. LIKELY can be used to
  share this likelihood information with the code generator so that it may
  make sensible decisions regarding when to spill.</para>

  <para>Example:</para>

  <programlisting>PeopleYoungerThan100 := AllPeople( LIKELY(age &lt; 100, 0.999) );
// Probably not worth spilling PeopleYoungerThan100

PeopleOlderThan100 := AllPeople( UNLIKELY(age&gt;100) );
// Probably worth spilling even if PeopleOlderThan100 is used by only a couple of activities</programlisting>

  <para></para>
</sect1>
