<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect2 id="SA_SupportUtilities">
  <title>Support Utilities</title>

  <para>There are a few additional components which are neither system servers
  nor client interfaces but nonetheless important in supporting HPCC
  tasks.</para>

  <sect3 id="DAFilesrv">
    <title>dafilesrv</title>

    <para>The dafilesrv is a daemon that runs on system servers or physical
    locations on the HPCC system. This daemon enables the HPCC components to
    have file access to physical file locations. File access could be
    spraying, despraying, copying, accessing logs, etc. Anything that requires
    a file from another node, must have dafilesrv running on that node. The
    dafilesrv daemon can be configured to allow SSL connections only, which
    secures remote access to physical files.</para>

    <para>The dafilesrv daemon runs as a process on every HPCC node. The
    daemon will typically keep running even if your system is stopped. That is
    an important fact to keep in mind if you are stopping your system for
    maintenance, installations, or upgrades. Even if you issue the HPCC system
    stop command, you would still need to stop the dafilesrv daemon.</para>

    <para>One way to check and see if dafilesrv is running, is to issue a
    command such as the following:</para>

    <para><programlisting>ps -eaf | grep dafilesrv</programlisting> Even if
    your HPCC System is stopped, you should still see that the dafilesrv is
    running.</para>

    <para>Issue the following command to stop the dafilesrv daemon on a System
    V based system.</para>

    <programlisting>sudo /opt/HPCCSystems/sbin/hpcc-run.sh -a dafilesrv stop</programlisting>

    <para>Issue the following command to stop the dafiilesrv daemon on a
    Systemd based system. </para>

    <programlisting>hpcc-run.sh -c dafilesrv@mydafilesrv.service stop</programlisting>

    <para>You must have sudo permission level access in order to start or stop
    any of the HPCC components, including dafilesrv.</para>

    <para>After you verify that dafilesrv is not running you can then proceed
    with the installation.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>ftslave</title>

    <para>The ftslave is a process used when spraying data by dfuserver. The
    ftslave process is launched on demand as part of the spray process. There
    may be mutliple ftslave processes running on any given node at any given
    time, depending on the number of active sprays.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
