<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Dali-LDAP">
  <title>Dali and LDAP</title>

  <para>This section contains additional information about Dali and LDAP
  security settings.</para>

  <sect2 id="LDAP-Dali">
    <title>LDAP and Dali Security settings</title>

    <para>There are a few Dali security settings that impact the way that Dali
    performs. The following configurations further explain the impact of some
    common security settings.</para>

    <sect3 id="DaliNoLDAP">
      <title>Dali without LDAP</title>

      <para>If you configure Dali without any LDAP server bound:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Anyone can access any file and any workunit. Essentially, you
          have no security.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Without an LDAP server configured, the CheckScopeScan
          attribute in the configuration is ignored. This means that any user
          can see the entire list of logical files and can access any
          file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Anyone can see, access, or even run any workunit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Dali with LDAP Server and CheckScopeScans setting
      disabled</title>

      <para>In this scenario, you have your Dali bound to a LDAP server, and
      the CheckScopeScans attribute is set to false</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The CheckScopeScans setting only impacts the listing of
          logical files.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All file access calls are authorized by ensuring the caller
          has access to the given file scope.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>FilesDefaultUser credentials are injected if none provided.
          The <emphasis>filesDefaultUser</emphasis> is an LDAP account used to
          access files when no user credentials are supplied. This is similar
          to a guest account, so it should be an account with very limited
          access, if used at all. To disable access without credentials, leave
          filesDefaultUser attribute blank.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Since the CheckScopeScans setting is disabled, users can see
          the entire list of logical files, even if user does not have access
          to view a file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Dali with LDAP Server and CheckScopeScans setting enabled</title>

      <para>In this scenario, you have your Dali bound to a LDAP server, and
      the CheckScopeScans attribute is set to true.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All file access calls are authorized by ensuring the caller
          has access to the given file scope.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Users can see files listed for all files within file scopes
          for which they have read access permission.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You should keep in mind since the system must make an external
      LDAP call to check every level in the scope, from the top to the bottom,
      that the depth of file scopes can have a performance cost in systems
      with File Scope Security enabled.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
