<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="IntroHPCC4J" role="nobrk">
  <title>Introduction to HPCC4J</title>

  <para>The hpcc4j project is a collection Java based APIs which help
  developers interact with HPCC in a relatively simple, and standardized
  fashion.</para>

  <para>The project houses multiple HPCC centric Java based API/tools. Each
  API set has some useful capabilities.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
    <title>HPCC4J Projects</title>

    <para>The projects contained in the hpcc4j repository:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.hpccsystems.ws.client</title>

      <para>The API which standardizes and facilitates interaction with HPCC
      Web based Services.</para>

      <para>The project is based on stub code generated from WSDL using
      Eclipse tools based on Apache Axis.</para>

      <para>Provides a mechanism for activating HPCC web service
      methods.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.hpccsystems.clienttools</title>

      <para>Java based interface to HPCC client tools. Currently only
      interfaces with the ECLCC Server.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.hpccsystems.rdf.rdf2hpcc</title>

      <para>RDF data ingestion tool to HPCC. Based on Apache Jena and is
      dependent on org.hpccsystems.ws.client.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.hpccsystems.ws.client.legacy</title>

      <para>The legacy HPCC Web based services interfaces used in conjunction
      with the org.hpccsystems.ws.client project.</para>

      <para>Dependent on org.hpccsystems.ws.client.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Use Cases</title>

    <para>The following use cases depict how you can work with the hpcc4j
    projects. </para>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.hpccsystems.ws.client</title>

      <para>If you have some ECL code that you would want to submit and
      execute from a Java client. Use the <emphasis
      role="bold">org.hpccsystems.ws.client </emphasis>package to connect to
      the target HPCC system. Create a workunit object with your ECL code and
      submit that object to the WECL workunit web services. With the ws.client
      package you can do this in less than 5 lines of code.</para>

      <programlisting>{
 //Fetch platform object based on connection settings
 //Provide the connection type, http|https, the ecl watch ip, and port, 
 //your ESP username and password (if required)
  
 Platform platform = Platform.get("http", "ip", 8010, "username", "password");

 //platform the platform provides a ws client

 HPCCWSClient connector = platform.getHPCCWSClient();

 //This connector can be used to actuate various HPCC WebService methods
 //For example, the client can request a list of available Target cluster names
 //List&lt;String&gt; clusters = connector.getAvailableTargetClusterNames();
 //or cluster groups 
 //String[] clusterGroups = connector.getAvailableClusterGroups();
 //which can then be used as one of the required parameters for other ws actions
 //such as spraying a file:
 //connector.sprayFlatHPCCFile
 //("persons", "mythor::persons", 155, clusters.get(0), true);

 //The WorkunitInfo object contains all the information needed by HPCC to compile 
 //and execute an ECL query correctly

   WorkunitInfo wu=new WorkunitInfo();
   wu.setECL("output('Hello World');"); // the ECL to execute
   wu.setCluster("mythor");             // can be hardcoded to a known cluster, 
                                        // or can be selected from 
                                        // valid cluster names clusterGroups[0] (above) 
            
 //this is just one way to submitECL, you can also submit ecl, 
 //and receive the WUID, which can later be used to fetch results
 //The results (if successful) are returned as a List of Object Lists 

   List&lt;List&lt;Object&gt;&gt; results = connector.submitECLandGetResultsList(wu);

  //logic to analyze results would need to be implemented.
    int currentrs = 1;

    for (List&lt;Object&gt; list : results)
     {
     Utils.print(System.out, "Resultset " + currentrs +":", false, true);
         for (Object object : list)
          {
            System.out.print("[ " + object.toString() +" ]");
          }
         currentrs++;
         System.out.println("");
     }
 }
        catch (Exception e)
        {
            System.out.println( e.getLocalizedMessage());
        }
</programlisting>

      <para>The above is just a sample of how to code for this interface. You
      can create other modules and interfaces with the appropriate
      packages.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Builds</title>

    <para>Each individual hpcc4j project has been set up as an Eclipse Java
    project (you may use other IDEs as well).</para>

    <para>The project has also been configured to be built using Maven.</para>

    <para>To build the projects using Maven, navigate to the base directory of
    the project and issue the following command:</para>

    <programlisting>mvn install</programlisting>

    <para>For more information on how to use Maven see <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org">http://maven.apache.org</ulink></para>

    <para>Each Web Service has multiple methods.</para>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>JAVA Source</title>

    <para>The source can be found under the HPCC Platform github account in
    the hpcc4j repo. </para>

    <para><ulink
    url="https://github.com/hpcc-systems/hpcc4j">https://github.com/hpcc-systems/hpcc4j</ulink></para>

    <para>To utilize the API(s) you can either import the pertinent hpcc4j
    project into your workspace and access the API source directly, or you can
    build the library and subsequently import into the client project. </para>

    <para>Contributions to source are accepted and encouraged. All
    contributions must follow the JAVA source format described in the
    HPCC-JAVA-Formatter.xml file which can be found in /eclipse. This
    formatter can be used by the Eclipse IDE to automatically format JAVA
    source code.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From eclipse, choose Window-&gt;Preferences-&gt;Java-&gt;Code
          Stype-&gt;Formatter.</para>

          <para>Import the HPCC-JAVA-Formatter.xml file and set it as the
          Active profile.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the JAVA editor, choose Source-&gt;Format</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
