<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="IntroHPCC4J" role="nobrk">
  <title>Introduction to HPCC4J</title>

  <para>The HPCC Systems for Java is a collection of Java based APIs and tools
  which help developers interact with HPCC Systems servers and tools in a
  relatively simple, and standardized fashion.</para>

  <para>The project houses multiple HPCC Systems centric Java based APIs and
  tools.</para>

  <para>The project is available on Github in the hpcc4j repository.</para>

  <para><ulink
  url="https://github.com/hpcc-systems/hpcc4j">https://github.com/hpcc-systems/hpcc4j</ulink></para>

  <sect2>
    <title>wsclient</title>

    <para>The API which standardizes and facilitates interaction with HPCC
    Systems Web based Services (ESP Web services).</para>

    <para>The project is based on stub code generated from WSDL using Eclipse
    tools based on Apache Axis.</para>

    <para>Provides a mechanism for actuating HPCC Systems web service
    methods.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>clienttools</title>

    <para>Java based interface to HPCC Systems client tools. Currently only
    interfaces with the ECLCC Server.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>rdf2hpcc</title>

    <para>RDF data ingestion tool to HPCC.Systems Based on Apache Jena and is
    dependent on wsclient.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>dfsclient</title>

    <para>Distributed data ingestion &amp; extraction library. Uses internal
    HPCC Systems binaries to efficiently read and write data remotely in
    parallel. Supports generic and custom dataset creation and translation
    through <emphasis>IRecordBuilder</emphasis> &amp;
    <emphasis>IRecordAccessor</emphasis> interfaces</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>commons-hpcc</title>

    <para>Set of common use libraries used in conjunction with a wide array of
    HPCC Systems related java clients.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>NOTE:</title>

    <informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
      <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

        <colspec />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><graphic fileref="../../images/tip.jpg" /></entry>

            <entry><para>As is common in Java client communication over TLS,
            HPCC4J based clients targeting an HPCC cluster over TLS will need
            to import the appropriate certificates to its local Java
            keystore.</para><para> </para><para>*One way to accomplish this is
            to use the keytool packaged with Java installations. Refer to the
            keytool documentation for usage. </para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para> </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
