<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
################################################################################
#    HPCC SYSTEMS software Copyright (C) 2012 HPCC Systems®.
#
#    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
#    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
#    You may obtain a copy of the License at
#
#       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
#
#    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
#    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
#    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
#    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
#    limitations under the License.
################################################################################
-->
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
    <title>rtl/eclrtl</title>

    <para>
        The rtl/eclrtl directory contains the sources for the eclrtl.so library.
    </para>
    <para>
        The eclrtl library is primarily the runtime support library for the code generator.  Many of the functions it contains
        are related to processing the different datatypes (e.g., string/int/unicode/datasets/dictionaries).  It also contains
        the functions for regular expressions.
    </para>
    <para>
        Eclrtl should only contain code that is needed by the code generator - it is not a library for sharing code between the engines.
        In particular it should not have any activity related code (that should go in thorhelper).  All the functions assume that
        the roxiemem memory manager is being used for allocating rows.  This library also shouldn't contain any dependence on dali.
    </para>
    <para>
        The library is also used by many other libraries in the system primarily for the functions for the system functions and the
        functions for converting between different datatypes.
    </para>
    <para>
        One of its goals is to isolate the generated code from other parts of the system and minimize the dependencies.  There
        are two reasons for this -
        <itemizedlist override="bullet">
            <listitem>
                It allows compiled workunits to remain compatible with future revisions of the platform.  This allows the
                platform to be upgraded withut having to recompile any deployed queries.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                It reduces the include file dependencies for the generated code.  In particular the header files should
                not include jlib, icu, boost or any other complex set of includes.  It is fine for the implementation to use those libraries,
                but there should be no direct references in the headers.  This reduces the dependencies required on a system
                and also reduces the compile time.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        The following is a summary of the different files, and yes they could do with being rationalized.
        <itemizedlist override="bullet">
            <listitem>
                eclrtl.cpp - datatype conversion functions, regular expression wrappers, various system functions, hash functions, helper functions for searching tables,
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtldistr.cpp - support classes for DISTRIBUTION
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlds.cpp - support classes for datasets and dictionaries
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlfield.cpp - classes for representing the format of fields within records.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlint.cpp - functions for reading and writing integers of different lengths
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlkey.cpp - functions and classes that are used to create keyed filters for the index reads.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlqstr.cpp - qstring helper functions.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlrank.cpp - support functions for RANK/RANKED
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlread.cpp - helper functions for creating/reading/accessing serialized rows.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlsize.cpp - unused - should possibly be deleted.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtltype.cpp
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                rtlxml.cpp - helper functions for generating xml from rows.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>
