<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book xml:base="../">
  <title>Using ECL Watch</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>Using ECL Watch</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email></para>

      <para>Please include <emphasis role="bold">Documentation
      Feedback</emphasis> in the subject line and reference the document name,
      page numbers, and current Version Number in the text of the
      message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license.</para>

      <para>HPCC Systems<superscript>®</superscript> is a registered trademark
      of LexisNexis Risk Data Management Inc.</para>

      <para>Other products, logos, and services may be trademarks or
      registered trademarks of their respective companies.</para>

      <para>All names and example data used in this manual are fictitious. Any
      similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para />
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="../common/Version.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='FooterInfo'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../common/Version.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='DateVer'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <corpname>HPCC Systems<superscript>®</superscript></corpname>

    <xi:include href="../common/Version.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Copyright'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_Intro">
    <title>Introducing ECL Watch</title>

    <para>ECL Watch is a service that runs on the Enterprise Services Platform
    (ESP), a middleware component on the HPCC Systems platform.</para>

    <para>ECL Watch provides an interface to the HPCC Systems platform and
    allows you to view information and interrogate nodes to confirm all
    expected processes are running. It is a plugin that is useful for Systems
    Administrators to check processes, examine topology, and view logs. It is
    useful to ECL Programmers to monitor the status of jobs and files, and
    other pertinent information. This provides a simple view into the system
    and a means to perform Workunit and data files maintenance.</para>

    <para>The ECL Watch interface is a browser based set of pages where you
    can access and interface with the HPCC Systems platform. To Run <emphasis
    role="bold">ECL Watch</emphasis> using you browser, go to the node on your
    system running <emphasis role="bold">ESP/ECL Watch</emphasis> on port
    8010. For example, http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:8010, where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is
    your ESP/ECL Watch node's IP address. This will launch ECL Watch.</para>

    <para>ECL Watch is organized by categories based on several system
    functions. These functions or actions are accessible through the links
    along the top of the main home page. However there are several ECL Watch
    items with common functionality universally across pages of ECL
    Watch.</para>

    <sect1 id="Common_Elements">
      <title>Common Elements</title>

      <para>There are common elements that are useful anywhere within ECL
      Watch.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>User Login</title>

        <para>When you open ECL Watch a log in window displays. <figure>
            <title>Login</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWAlogin.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>You login with the credentials supplied by your Systems
        Administrator. After a configurable period of inactivity your ECL
        Watch session locks and you need to enter your credentials to unlock
        and resume your session. The session remains active for as long as
        there is regular keyboard or mouse interaction.</para>

        <para>Additionally, there is a Logout menu item available you can
        select to close your session when you complete your work.</para>

        <!--The following \/\/ is temporary and can probably be deleted after Session Management has been fully integrated.-->

        <para>For more information and frequently asked questions about
        session management, please refer to <link
        linkend="SessMgmtFAQ">Appendix A</link>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="OpenInNewPage">
        <title>Open in New Page</title>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Open in New Page</emphasis> link
        allows you to open a new window directly to the item which you are
        viewing. <figure>
            <title>Open in New Page</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA500.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Opening a new page of the current view is useful in several
        ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open in New Page</emphasis> is a
            shareable link. Right-click on <emphasis role="bold">Open in New
            Page</emphasis> and select <emphasis>Copy link address</emphasis>
            from the context menu. You can now save, share, or send that link
            and the recipient can open a window directly to the (new)
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>New pages maintain filter states. If you have set a filter
            and share that link, the new page has the same filter set.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The new page is live. (If that page has auto-refresh
            enabled) The recipient doesn't need to reset the page or refresh
            to see current state.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect3>
          <title>Maximize Pane</title>

          <para><graphic fileref="images/ECLWAMax01.jpg" /></para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Maximize/Restore</emphasis> icon
          appears throughout ECL Watch. Press the button to maximize the
          corresponding window pane. Press the button again to restore the
          pane to its original size.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ListWidgets">
        <title>List widgets</title>

        <para><figure>
            <title>List Widgets</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA-Comm.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>ECL Watch commonly displays items in the forms of a list. Lists
        of workunits, lists of logical files, lists of Roxie queries, etc. The
        following elements in ECL Watch work on any list widget:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Download as CSV (Workunits, DFU Workunits, Logical files,
              and Roxie queries)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Column check box. Select all rows by selecting the check
              box at top (Use Shift+Click to select a range)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sort by column header. Click on the column header to sort
              that column according to that column's contents.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Resize Column Widths by dragging the borders.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Filters that allow you to set criteria for the items to
              display in the list.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <sect3>
          <title>List Filters</title>

          <para>Filter options on a list allow you to use specified criteria
          to set what you display in the list. Press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Filter</emphasis> action button to display the filter
          options. When you specify any Filter options, the Filter action
          button changes and then displays <emphasis role="bold">Filter
          Set</emphasis> and the filter indicator image lights up. When you
          then copy an <emphasis role="bold">Open in New Page</emphasis> link
          with the filter set, the filter condition persists. Filter
          conditions limit the results displayed until you clear the
          filter.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 role="brk">
          <title>The Mine Button</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Mine</emphasis> button appears along
          the top of every list page. Check the Mine box to filter for only
          items that you own. <figure>
              <title>Mine button</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWAMine00.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>Uncheck the Mine button to display all jobs.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECLWA_BannerItems">
        <title>Banner Items</title>

        <para>The banner area of ECL Watch appears at the top of all
        pages.</para>

        <sect3 id="ECLWAtchHomeButton">
          <title>Home Button</title>

          <para>The HPCC Systems home button is also the main Activity menu
          link. More than just a decoration the home ECL Watch button actually
          opens up the Activity page, discussed in more detail in the ensuing
          chapter.</para>

          <para>The icons to the left of the home button are links to
          different areas of ECL Watch. Each of the link areas are discussed
          in subsequent chapters.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="MonitorIndicatorLight">
          <title>Monitor indicator light</title>

          <para>The Monitor indicator light is used to provide an at a glance
          snapshot of your overall system health. If you have monitoring and
          reporting configured (see <emphasis>HPCC Systems Monitoring and
          Reporting</emphasis>) then this light will display a color based on
          the the overall (configurable) system health. The light is black if
          there is no monitoring or reporting configured for your
          system.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="DownloadAsCSV">
          <title>Download as CSV</title>

          <para>With most lists in ECL Watch you have the ability to download
          selected rows as a CSV formatted file. You can then open the CSV
          file in any spreadsheet application which supports CSV
          format.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECLWatch_GlobalSearch">
        <title>Global Search</title>

        <para>The global search box can be found on the navigation bar at the
        top of the ECL Watch page.<figure>
            <title>Global Search box</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA008.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>You can search DFU Workunits, ECL Workunits, Logical Files, and
        Queries using the global search box. The global search excludes ECL
        code by default. To search for ECL code within workunits, use the
        <emphasis role="bold">ecl: </emphasis>keyword. For example,
        ecl:SOAPCALL. To limit or filter your search results you can use
        keywords as displayed in the empty search box.</para>

        <para><variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>file:</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Preface the search string with
                <emphasis>file:</emphasis> to search Logical Files.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>wuid:.</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Preface the search string with
                <emphasis>wuid:</emphasis> to search only Workunit ids.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>ecl:</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Preface the search string with <emphasis>ecl:</emphasis>
                to search ECL code in the workunits.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>dfu:</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Preface the search string with <emphasis>dfu:</emphasis>
                to search only DFU workunits.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>query:</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Preface the search string with
                <emphasis>query:</emphasis> to search only published
                queries.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>

        <para>The global search box also supports using wildcards.</para>

        <para>Examples of using the global search:</para>

        <para>Enter <emphasis>W201510*</emphasis> into the search box, and it
        will return all of the workunits from October 2015.</para>

        <para>Enter <emphasis>file:keys</emphasis> into the search box, and it
        will return all of the logical files that contain "keys". <figure>
            <title>Global Search Example</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA015.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <!-- Enter <i>ecl:output</i> into the global search box and it will return all of the workunits that contain "output" in the ECL page of ECL Watch-->
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Advanced Menu</title>

        <para>There is a section at the top right on the navigation bar with
        some useful information and features. This section shows you who you
        are logged in as (if your system has authentication enabled). The
        Advanced menu is located on the right hand side of the navigation bar.
        There are several items that you can access from the advanced
        menu.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Advanced menu</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA007b.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>There may be a number displayed on the menu link. A number
        displayed next to it indicates how many errors and warnings have been
        generated during your session. Click on the advanced menu to display a
        list of features.</para>

        <sect3 id="ECLWatch_AdvancedMenuAccess">
          <title>Access the Advanced menu</title>

          <para>You access the advanced menu items from the advanced menu link
          at the top right corner of ECL Watch.<!--Removed some content stashed in GitStash : ECLWA-1115.xml others culled stored in git-br H8872-NewestECLfor50 **--></para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Set Banner</emphasis> link allows
          you to set a custom banner message at the top of your browser window
          when you open ECL Watch. Check the <emphasis
          role="bold">Enable</emphasis> box to enable a banner. You can use
          the banner to deliver a short message about the environment to
          users. Customize the appearance of the message banner with the other
          controls. Banner settings persist until the ESP Server
          restarts.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Set Toolbar</emphasis> link allows
          you to customize the toolbar at the top of the ECL Watch page. Check
          the <emphasis role="bold">Enable Environment Text </emphasis>box to
          display the<emphasis role="bold"> Name of Environment</emphasis>
          text at the top of the page and in the browser tab. Labeling browser
          tabs is helpful when working with multiple environments. Toolbar
          settings persist through restarts of the ESP Server.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Error/Warning(s)</emphasis> link
          displays a tab showing you Errors, Warnings, and Information
          messages. You can filter this page by checking the boxes at the
          bottom of the tab. A copy facility is also provided.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Release Notes</emphasis> link opens
          a new browser tab to the HPCC Systems release notes page where you
          can find more release specific information about the contents of
          each version of HPCC.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Documentation</emphasis> link opens
          a new browser tab to the HPCC Systems documentation page, where you
          can view and download the HPCC Systems platform
          documentation.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Downloads</emphasis> link opens a
          new browser tab to the HPCC Systems downloads page, where you can
          find and download the HPCC Systems platform, client tools, and
          plugins.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Additional Resources</emphasis> link
          opens a submenu that provides links to areas on the HPCC Systems web
          site where you can find additional resources, such as the <emphasis
          role="bold">Red Book</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">User
          Forums</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Issue Reporting</emphasis>,
          and the <emphasis role="bold">Transition Guide</emphasis>.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Configuration</emphasis> link opens
          for viewing the XML version of the configuration file in use on your
          system.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">About</emphasis> link opens a dialog
          to display information about the version of the HPCC Systems
          platform installed on your server.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="ECLWatch_AdvancedMenuLoggedInAs" role="nobrk">
          <title>Logged In As</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Logged In As:</emphasis> links at
          the top of the ECL Watch page display information about the current
          user logged onto a cluster configured for authentication. <figure>
              <title>Logged In As</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWMyAccount.jpg"
                             vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para><orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click on your username link and the User Details window
                opens.</para>

                <para><figure>
                    <title>User Details window</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWUserDetails.jpg" />
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>From The User Details page, you can Confirm the User
                Name that you are logged in as.</para>

                <para>You can change your password.</para>

                <para>Note that Administrator rights are needed to manage
                users and permissions.</para>

                <para>Ensure you are using an account with Administrator
                rights if you intend to manage users or permissions.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Verify the password expiration date, or if password is
                set to expire.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>

          <sect4 id="ECLWatch_AdvancedMenuChangePassword" role="nobrk">
            <title>Change Password</title>

            <para>If authentication is enabled on your HPCC Systems platform,
            you can change your password, right from the User Details window.
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Click on your username link under the <emphasis
                  role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">LOGGED IN
                  AS:</emphasis></emphasis></para>

                  <para>The User Details window opens. There are fields where
                  you can change your password.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Enter your Old Password.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Enter your desired new password.</para>

                  <para>Make sure it meets whatever criteria your system may
                  have for passwords.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Confirm your new password.</para>

                  <para>Make sure that it matches the password you entered in
                  the previous field.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Press the Save button. It is in the upper left portion
                  of the window.</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist></para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4>
            <title>Lock</title>

            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Lock</emphasis> link next to
            the username link to lock your session. You would then need to
            enter your credentials to unlock your session.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_Home_Chapter">
    <title>ECL Watch Home Page</title>

    <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">ECL Watch</emphasis> home page
    link in the navigation bar at the top of the ECL Watch page to find the
    <emphasis role="bold">Activity</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">Scheduler</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">Search
    Results</emphasis> links. You can access the respective pages from the
    links or tabs along the top of the ECL Watch home page.</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>ECL Watch home page link</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA010.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>There are several icons used throughout ECL Watch. The following
    table describes most of the icons that you will encounter.</para>

    <para><informaltable colsep="1" frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="46pt" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Icon</emphasis></entry>

              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ECLWaCluster.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>System cluster</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ECLWaClustPaused.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>System cluster paused</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ECLWaClustNotFound.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>System cluster not found</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_complete.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Compiled, Completed</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_running.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Running, Compiling, Debug Running</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_fail.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Failed, Aborted</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_warn.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Blocked, Scheduled, Wait, Uploading Files, Debug
              Paused, Paused</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_archived.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Archived</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_abort.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Aborting</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_submit.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Submitted</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/wu_deleted.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Deleted.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/workunit.png"
              vendor="eclwatchSS" /></entry>

              <entry>Workunit Unknown State</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable></para>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Activity" role="nobrk">
      <title>Activity</title>

      <para>The Activity tab displays activity on all clusters in the
      environment. The Activity page provides access to Cluster Job Queue
      administration tasks such as: monitoring progress, setting priority,
      moving a job up or down in the queue, pausing a job, aborting a job, and
      pausing or resuming a queue.</para>

      <!--***Note specific Activity task details have been REMOVED (to DocShare/WKSPCE/ECLWa400)***-->

      <para>When you access the ECL Watch URL, the ECL Watch Home Page
      displays the Activity tab. To access the Activity tab from any other
      page in ECL Watch click on the <emphasis role="bold">ECL
      Watch</emphasis> image at the top of any page, as shown above.</para>

      <sect2 id="ClusterDiskUsageGraphs">
        <title>Cluster Disk Usage Graphs</title>

        <para>The Cluster Activity page displays graphs along the top showing
        cluster disk usage. These graphs can give you a quick glance at the
        capacity of your clusters. Clicking on each of the images displays
        more information about the individual cluster's disk usage
        activity.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Cluster Activity Page Graphs</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWaGage01.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>The graphs show the amount of available storage, the
        average amount of storage in use, and the maximum amount of storage in
        use across all nodes. The dark indicator line displays the average in
        use across the disks in that cluster. The colored doughnut portion
        shows the maximum amount of storage in use by any single node. If this
        differs greatly, it could affect performance.</para>

        <para>The color of the graphs change as the storage capacity changes.
        Green indicates low utilization, yellow indicates higher utilization,
        and red indicates very high utilization.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Cluster Graph Detail</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWaGage02.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>The graphs provide an indication of available capacity
        across your nodes. This can help identify any potential disk space
        issues.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECLWatch_ClusterActivity">
        <title>Cluster Activity</title>

        <para>Information about your systems' clusters, and any activity on
        those clusters can be accessed from the ECL Watch Activity tab. Select
        the <emphasis role="bold">Activity</emphasis> tab link below the
        <emphasis role="bold">ECL Watch</emphasis> image in the navigation
        sub-menu. This displays the Cluster Activity tab.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Clusters Activity</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA1002b.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>All the system clusters display. If there is any activity on a
        cluster there is an icon next to the cluster to indicate some
        activity. In the above example the icon to expand the Thor cluster
        indicates there is some activity on the Thor cluster. Click the icon
        to expand the cluster to see the activity on that cluster.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 role="brk">
        <title>Cluster Action Buttons</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Cluster Action Buttons</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA1005.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Check the box next to a cluster to enable the Cluster Action
        buttons. The Cluster Action buttons will then allow you to perform the
        following actions on the selected cluster's job queue.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Pause</title>

          <para>Pauses the cluster's job queue. The currently running job will
          complete, but no other jobs will execute until the queue is
          resumed.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Resume</title>

          <para>Resumes a paused job queue. Any waiting jobs will resume
          execution in order.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Clear</title>

          <para>Removes all workunits from the job queue. The removed
          workunits' state is then set to aborted. Any workunits that were
          waiting in the queue can be resubmitted manually later, if
          desired.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="WorkUnitActivityTab">
        <title>Cluster Workunit Activity</title>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Workunit Activity Buttons</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA1002c.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Workunit Action Buttons</title>

        <para>Check the box next to a Workunit to select it and enable the
        Workunit Action buttons.</para>

        <para>The enabled Workunit Action buttons will then allow you to
        perform the following actions on the selected Workunit(s).</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Open</title>

          <para>Opens a (workunit) tab for the selected workunit.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Pause</title>

          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Pause</emphasis> button to
          complete the current subgraph and then put the job into a paused
          state.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Pause Now</title>

          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Pause Now</emphasis> button to
          interrupt the current subgraph (abort it) and put the job into a
          paused state.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Resume</title>

          <para>Resumes processing of any paused job.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Abort</title>

          <para>Aborts a running job. An aborted job cannot be resumed.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>High, Normal, Low</title>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Priority</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA1003b.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>You can raise or lower the priority of the job in the
          queue. Select the job, then press one of the appropriate buttons,
          <emphasis role="bold">High</emphasis> or <emphasis
          role="bold">Low</emphasis>. Typically all jobs are Normal priority
          by default.</para>

          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">High</emphasis> button to
          raise the priority of the select job to High. Press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Low</emphasis> button to lower the priority of the
          processing job.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Top, Bottom, Up, Down</title>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Queue Position</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA1003c.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>You can change the position of a job in the queue using
          the Top, Bottom, Up, and Down buttons.</para>

          <para>Select the workunit to move, that will enable the action
          buttons.</para>

          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Top</emphasis> button to move
          the select job to the top of the processing queue. Press the
          <emphasis role="bold">Up</emphasis> button to move the job up one
          position in the queue. Press the <emphasis
          role="bold">Down</emphasis> button to move the job down one position
          in the queue. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Bottom</emphasis>
          button to move the job down to the bottom of the queue.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="cluster_Info" role="brk">
        <title>Cluster Information</title>

        <para>You can access more information about your Thor clusters from
        the main Activity tab.</para>

        <para>Select the target cluster from the main <emphasis
        role="bold">Activity</emphasis> tab, by checking the box next to it.
        <figure>
            <title>Open Cluster</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA002.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>This enables the <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis> action
        button. Press the Open action button to open a new tab for that
        cluster.</para>

        <para>The cluster tab displays the groups on that cluster. Check the
        box next to the cluster group, and press the open button. <figure>
            <title>Open Cluster Groups</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA003.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Open up the cluster group tab (for example, mythor), and select
        the group from the Groups tab to see the activity information on that
        cluster group. <figure>
            <title>Cluster Activity tabs</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA004.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>On that cluster group tab, you can access the information about
        that cluster. There are three tabs on that cluster group tab. The
        <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> tab provides a snapshot of
        that group.</para>

        <para>Alternatively, you can click the link on the cluster name to
        examine.</para>

        <sect3 id="ClusterUsageTab">
          <title>The Cluster Usage Tab</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Usage</emphasis> tab provides access
          to a usage graph. The usage tab provides information about the
          cluster usage. <figure>
              <title>Usage Graph</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA0UG01.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>To display the usage graph, you can enter some values in the
          in the fields displayed on the initial usage tab. Optionally, you
          can just accept the default, the values for the last 30 days. Then
          press the <emphasis role="bold">Get Usage Graph</emphasis> button to
          display the graph.</para>

          <para>The Graph shows the cluster usage over time. More information
          about the cluster usage is specified using a color code. The column
          on the right breaks down the overall usage as well as the percentage
          during standard business hours and non-business hours. You can
          change these values using the fields above the chart, then press the
          <emphasis role="bold">Get Usage Graph</emphasis> button
          again.</para>

          <sect4>
            <title id="ClusterLogFile">Cluster Log File</title>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Log File</emphasis> tab is where
            you can view that cluster group's log. <figure>
                <title>Cluster Log File</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA005.jpg" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure></para>

            <para>There are several log display options that you can use to
            filter the log file. You can filter by rows, pages, or by time.
            Use the filter options on the Log File tab to filter the displayed
            log. You can also download the log file to view offline.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECLWatch_AutoRefresh">
        <title>Auto Refresh</title>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Auto Refresh</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA011.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>The <emphasis role="bold">Activity</emphasis> page displays
        active ECL or DFU workunits either running or in the queue on your
        cluster. To refresh the list, press the <emphasis
        role="bold">Refresh</emphasis> button. Auto Refresh shows the list in
        real-time, but this feature is disabled by default.</para>

        <para>To enable Auto Refresh, toggle the Auto Refresh button.</para>

        <para>In an environment with a large number of active users, Auto
        Refresh could impact performance of your ESP server.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_EventScheduler">
      <title>ECL Event Scheduler</title>

      <para>The Event Scheduler page provides an interface to the ECL
      Scheduler. The ECL Scheduler interface allows you to see a list of
      scheduled workunits. It can also trigger an event. An Event is a
      case-insensitive string constant naming the event to trap.</para>

      <para>ECL Scheduling provides a means of automating processes within ECL
      code or to chain processes together to work in sequence. For example,
      you can write ECL code that watches a landing zone for the arrival of a
      file, and when it arrives, sprays it to Thor, processes it, builds an
      index, and then adds it to a superfile.</para>

      <para>ECL Scheduling is event-based. The ECL Scheduler monitors a
      Schedule list containing registered Workunits and Events and executes
      any Workunits associated with an Event when that Event is
      triggered.</para>

      <para>Your ECL Code can execute when an Event is triggered, or can
      trigger an Event. If you submit code containing a <emphasis
      role="bold">WHEN </emphasis>clause, the Event and Workunit registers in
      the Schedule list. When that Event triggers, the Workunit compiles and
      executes. When the Workunit completes, ECL Scheduler removes it from the
      Schedule list.</para>

      <para>For example, if you submit a Workunit using <emphasis
      role="bold">WHEN('Event1','MyEvent', COUNT(2)) </emphasis>in the
      appropriate place, it will execute twice (the value of <emphasis
      role="bold">COUNT</emphasis>) before the ECL Scheduler removes it from
      the Schedule list and the Workunit is marked as completed.</para>

      <para>For more details about both <emphasis id="WHEN"
      role="bold">WHEN</emphasis> or <emphasis id="NOTIFY"
      role="bold">NOTIFY</emphasis> or any ECL Language functions or keywords
      please see the ECL Language reference. A copy of which can be found
      online at <ulink
      url="http://hpccsystems.com/download/docs/learning-ecl">http://hpccsystems.com/download/docs/learning-ecl</ulink>
      on the HPCC Systems<superscript>®</superscript> web site.</para>

      <!--***NOTE: Be sure to UPDATE these images when they find a home in ECLWATCH***-->
    </sect1>

    <xi:include href="ECLScheduler/ECLSched-Mods/ECLSchedComp.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='ECLSched_Interface'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_ECLWorkunits">
    <title>ECL Workunits</title>

    <para>ECL Watch provides information about ECL jobs and workunits. Links
    to pages that contain information about ECL workunits appear in the
    navigation bar along top of the ECL Watch page. There you will find links
    to ECL Workunits, simply labelled as Workunits, and you will also find the
    link to the ECL Playground. Not only can you find information about
    workunits there, but you can perform operations on workunits.</para>

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='ECLWorkunits'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLPlayground/ECLPlay-Mods/ECL_Playground.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='ECL_Playground'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_FilesChapter">
    <title>Files</title>

    <para>This chapter contains sections dealing with HPCC Systems platform
    Files, found on the <emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis> link in ECL
    Watch.</para>

    <para>In an HPCC Systems platform, data files are partitioned across
    nodes. The file parts, referenced using Logical Filenames, are stored in
    the Distributed File Utility. This allows the collection of file parts to
    be referenced as a single entity.</para>

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='ECLWatchLogicalFiles'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='DFUWorkunits'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchSrc.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Landing_Zones'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <sect1 id="spray_and_despray">
      <title>Spray/Despray</title>

      <para>This section details how to Spray and Despray a data file to your
      cluster using ECL Watch. The spray function is integrated into the
      Landing Zone page as detailed in the <link linkend="Upload_Files">Upload
      Files</link> section .</para>

      <para>In order to spray a file to your cluster you must first upload the
      file to your landing zone. The file upload steps are detailed in the
      preceding section.</para>

      <para>With the file successfully uploaded to the landing zone you can
      choose the file to spray from the Landing Zone page. Once selected the
      Spray buttons become enabled.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Landing Zone Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA440.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <sect2 id="Spray-to-cluster">
        <title>Spray Data to a Cluster</title>

        <para>With the <emphasis role="bold">Spray:</emphasis> Action buttons
        enabled, you press the appropriate button for the Spray you wish to
        perform. Fill in the appropriate values when prompted to complete the
        spray.</para>
      </sect2>

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='LZ_Spray'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_Fixed'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_Delimited'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_XML'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_JSON'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_Variable'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Spray_Blob'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Desprays'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Copy'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <xi:include href="HPCCDataHandling/DH-Mods/DH-Mod1.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Remote_Copy'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Xref">
      <title>XRef</title>

      <para>Under the <emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis> Icon on the
      navigation sub-menu there is a link for XRef. This link will take you to
      the XRef page. On the XRef page you can run the XREF utility.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>XRef page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA435.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <sect2 id="The_XREF_Utility">
        <title>The XRef Utility</title>

        <para>The XREF utility provides the ability to find "orphaned",
        "lost", and "found" files. These "orphan" are files which are found on
        the nodes but not registered in the Distributed File System.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Found File</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A found file has file parts on disk that are not
              referenced in the Dali server. All the file parts are accounted
              for so they can be added back to the Dali server. They can also
              be deleted from the cluster, if required.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Orphan File</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>An orphan file is a file without a Dali entry and without
              a complete set of physical files. Since some of the physical
              files are missing it is an incomplete file and it cannot be used
              to add a logical file entry back into the Dali server. These
              orphan file parts do not have a reference in the Dali
              server.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Lost File</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A logical file that is missing at least one file part on
              both the primary and replicated locations in storage. The
              logical file is still referenced in the Dali server. Deleting
              the file removes the reference from the Dali server and any
              remaining parts on disk.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
          <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

            <colspec />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/tip.jpg" /></entry>

                <entry><para>On a large system, we suggest limiting the number
                of users who can Generate XREF reports by setting
                DfuXrefAccess access to FULL for only those
                users.</para><para> </para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>To generate a list:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Generate</emphasis>
            button.</para>

            <informaltable colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
              <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>

              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colwidth="49.50pt" />

                <colspec />

                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/tip.jpg" /></entry>

                    <entry><para>Sasha Server typically runs Xref at the times
                    scheduled when deployed.</para><para> </para></entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To view results:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on one of the tabs (Found Files, Orphan Files, Lost
            Files, Directories, or Errors/Warnings).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect3 id="ECLWatchXREFMultiThor">
          <title>XREF with multiple Thor clusters</title>

          <para>XREF runs on the primary Thor cluster. For a configuration
          with more than one Thor cluster on the same physical node group, ECL
          Watch only displays the primary Thor and not any other Thor that
          shares the same node group. This is the Thor cluster whose name
          matches the <emphasis>nodeGroup</emphasis> in the
          configuration.</para>

          <para>To allow XREF to run in an environment with multiple Thor
          clusters, set the nodeGroup to the same value for all Thor
          clusters.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="ECLWatch_WorkingWithXref">
          <title>Working with XREF results:</title>

          <para>After XRef completes you can see a list of available reports.
          Click on one of the tabs to see the results page of each
          type.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>XRef Errors</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA435b.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The Orphan and Lost Files pages list any Orphan or Lost files.
          Orphan and Lost files are difficult to recover, unless you have
          copies of missing parts needed to reconstruct the file (for example,
          if a missing part is on a hard drive that was replaced.)</para>

          <figure>
            <title>XRef: Delete Orphan Files</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA436.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Typically, these files will need to be deleted. To Delete,
          check the boxes next to files you want to delete, then press the
          <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis> button.</para>

          <para>Found files can and usually are reattached. <figure>
              <title>XRef: Attach Found Files</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA437.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para>Check the boxes next to files you want to reattach, then press
          the <emphasis role="bold">Attach</emphasis> button.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_Queries">
    <title>Queries</title>

    <para>The link for the Published Queries (icon) header provides more
    information and details about queries on available targets.</para>

    <!-- <para>Include ROXIE (RDDE). List of Clusters.</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; Thor</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; Roxie</para>

    <para>Queries &gt; Browse &gt; hThor</para>

    <para>I. Dynamic</para>

    <para>II. Clusters</para> -->

    <para>Click on the Published Queries (icon) hyperlink to display the
    published queries and package maps on that cluster.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Query Link</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA00Q.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/ECLWatchQueries.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Queries_Page'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ECLWatch_OperationsLink">
    <title>Operations</title>

    <para>The Operations link provides access to several components useful for
    the day-to-day operation of your system, and some system administration
    access as well. <figure>
        <title>Operations Menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA460.jpg" vendor="eclwatchSS" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>There are links to Target Clusters, Cluster Processes, and System
    Servers. These links open pages with more information about the specific
    topology for the selected clusters. These pages are helpful in certifying
    that your system is up and running properly.</para>

    <para>There are also some system administration type links such as, Users,
    Groups, Permissions, and Resources. These links allow you to perform some
    system administration tasks through ECL watch.</para>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Operations_Topology">
      <title>Topology</title>

      <para>The Topology page provides a visual tree display with information
      about your clusters, services, and nodes.</para>

      <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Topology</emphasis> link from
      the Operations navigation sub-menu to access the topology page.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Topology Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA463.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <sect2 id="TopologyTargets" role="brk">
        <title>Targets</title>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Targets</emphasis> Action button
        displays your clusters by type.</para>

        <para>Click on the arrow to the left of the Cluster folder/object to
        expand. The expanded view displays.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Expanded View</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA464.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>The expanded view displays the objects and nodes in the
        selected container. Select the node or object to display more
        information or to access the logs. The Summary, Configuration, and Log
        tabs on the left side of the page display the relevant information for
        the selected component.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="TopologyServices" role="brk">
        <title>Services</title>

        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Services</emphasis> Action
        button to display information on the various services running on your
        cluster.</para>

        <para>Click on the arrow to the left of the service you wish to
        expand. The expanded view displays.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Expanded Services</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA465.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>The services view provides a service oriented tree view that
        provides access to the services. Expand the tree, and select the
        component to view the Summary, Configuration, or Logs tabs for the
        selected component.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ECLWatch_Operations_TopologyMachines" role="brk">
        <title>Machines</title>

        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Machines</emphasis> Action
        button for more information on the various machines or nodes running
        in your cluster(s).</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Machines View</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA466.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Machines</emphasis> action button
        opens a node oriented view of the tree. Expand the nodes to see the
        services on each node. Select the component to view the Summary,
        Configuration, or Logs tabs for that selected component.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 role="brk">
        <title>Roxie File Copy Status</title>

        <para>In the Topology section for Roxie clusters, the <emphasis
        role="bold">Roxie Files Copy Status</emphasis> tab shows the number of
        files a cluster has left to copy.<figure>
            <title>File Copy Status</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA467.jpg" vendor="ECLWatchSS" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Operations_DiskUsage">
      <title>Disk Usage</title>

      <para>When you click on the Operations link, it opens the Disk Usage
      page by default. The Disk Usage page provides information about the
      available space on your system, and what is using that space. <figure>
          <title>Disk Usage</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA462.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>You can search or filter the results, using the <emphasis
      role="bold">Filter</emphasis> action button.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Operations_TargetClusters">
      <title>Operations: Target Clusters</title>

      <para>The Target Clusters link from the navigation sub-menu bar, on the
      Operations page, opens the link to the Target Clusters page. This page
      provides machine information on the clusters you have set up on your
      machine. <figure>
          <title>Target Clusters</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ECLWA461.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch-DynamicESDL">
      <title>Dynamic ESDL</title>

      <para>The Dynamic ESDL tab in ECL Watch displays the available ESP
      Services. You can explore the DESDL services and ESDL bindings, also
      known as service configurations.</para>

      <para>To access Dynamic ESDL through ECL Watch, click on the <emphasis
      role="bold">Operations</emphasis> link, then click on <emphasis
      role="bold">Dynamic ESDL</emphasis> from the navigation sub-menu
      bar.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Dynamic ESDL sub-menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL03.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Dynamic ESDL</emphasis> tab contains a
      list of all DESDL based ESP Services and their ESDL Binding information.
      The DESDL-based ESP services available are listed in the navigator pane
      on the left as children of their parent ESP process.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Definitions</emphasis> tab, also
      accessible from the <emphasis role="bold">Dynamic ESDL</emphasis>
      button's sub-menu, lists all available ESDL definitions and provides a
      view into any of the definitions. These definitions are used to
      dynamically define interfaces for existing ESP web services.</para>

      <para>For more information about Dynamic ESDL refer to the
      documentation; <emphasis>Dynamic ESDL</emphasis> available from the HPCC
      Systems portal: <ulink
      url="https://hpccsystems.com/training/documentation/learning-ecl/">https://hpccsystems.com/training/documentation/learning-ecl/dynamic-esdl</ulink></para>

      <sect2 id="USING_Dynamic_ESDL">
        <title>Using Dynamic ESDL</title>

        <para>In order to use this interface choose an ESP service from the
        service list. Click on the triangle icon next to the ESP process
        (myesp) to expand and display the DESDL services. Check the box to
        select the desired DESDL service, then press the Open button.</para>

        <para>The selected service's information opens and displays the
        <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> tab.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Dynamic ESDL Summary</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL08.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Viewing the binding information</title>

          <para>If the selected service contains an ESDL binding, you can
          select the binding tabs to view the binding definition (the service
          interface) or the configuration information.</para>

          <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Binding Definition</emphasis>
          to display the ESDL definition in XML format.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Dynamic ESDL Binding Definition</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL02.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="Configure_ESDL_Bindings">
          <title>Configuring ESDL Bindings</title>

          <para>You can select a service and if there is a binding for it you
          can review, delete, or modify the configuration of that
          binding.</para>

          <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Binding
          Configuration</emphasis> tab to view or edit the <emphasis
          role="bold">Methods</emphasis>. Press <emphasis
          role="bold">Save</emphasis> when finished. <figure>
              <title>Dynamic EDSL Binding Configuration</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL04.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Add a Binding</title>

          <para>If a configuration does not have a binding, you can add a
          binding. To add a service binding to an
          <emphasis>unconfigured</emphasis> ESP Service. Select the
          unconfigured ESP service, then press the enabled <emphasis
          role="bold">Add Binding</emphasis> button.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Adding a service binding</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL05.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>This will open a dialog listing the available interfaces.
          Provide the information requested, an ESP Process Name and a Port.
          Select a Definition and then provide a Service Name.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Adding the definition</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL06.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Apply</emphasis> button
          to apply the definition.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Delete a Binding</title>

          <para>To delete a service binding for a
          <emphasis>configured</emphasis> ESP Service. Expand the Process list
          as necessary and select the ESP service that contains the binding to
          delete.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Deleting service binding</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/DESDL07.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Delete Binding</emphasis>
          button. Confirm that you want to delete the binding by pressing OK
          on the confirmation dialog.</para>

          <para>The binding is deleted.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <xi:include href="HPCCCertify/Cert-Mods/CertPreflight.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Preflight_system_servers'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="HPCCCertify/Cert-Mods/CertPreflight.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Preflight_Data_Refinery'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <!--
    /*commented whole sect out*/
    <sect1 role="nobrk">
      <title>Users</title>
      /*PROBABLY NOT NEEDED - AND CAN BE DELETED*/
      <para>There are User Administration features available through ECL
      Watch. Common system administration tasks are accessible through the
      Operations menu in ECL Watch. The links to Users, Groups, Permissions,
      and Resources allow you to manage these components of your HPCC Systems platform
      from the ECL Watch interface.</para>

      <xi:include href="Installing_and_RunningTheHPCCPlatform/Inst-Mods/UserSecurityMaint.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Sec_Adm_w_ECLWatch'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1> 
 -->
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="User_Permissions_Chapter">
    <title>Users Permissions</title>

    <sect1 id="ECLWatch_Operations_UserAdministrations" role="nobrk">
      <title>User Administration</title>

      <para>There are User Administration features available through ECL
      Watch.</para>

      <xi:include href="Installing_and_RunningTheHPCCPlatform/Inst-Mods/UserSecurityMaint.xml"
                  xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='Sec_Adm_w_ECLWatch'])"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="Resources">
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>The resources link can be found under the Operations Icon link. The
    resources link in ECL Watch provides a link to the HPCC
    Systems<superscript>®</superscript> web portal. Visit the HPCC
    Systems<superscript>®</superscript> Web Portal at <ulink
    url="http://hpccsystems.com/">http://hpccsystems.com/</ulink> for software
    updates, plugins, support, documentation, and more. This is where you can
    find resources useful for running and maintaining HPCC Systems on the web
    portal.</para>

    <para>You can also get to the resources link on the HPCC
    Systems<superscript>®</superscript> web portal page, by clicking on the
    <emphasis role="bold">Additional Resources</emphasis> link found on the
    sub-menu of at the top right hand side of navigation bar.</para>

    <para>ECL Watch provides a link to the HPCC Systems download page: <ulink
    url="http://hpccsystems.com/download">http://hpccsystems.com/download</ulink>.
    This is the page where you can download Installation packages, virtual
    images, source code, documentation, and tutorials.</para>
  </chapter>

  <appendix id="SessMgmtFAQ">
    <title>HPCC Systems Session Management</title>

    <xi:include href="ECLWatch/ECLWa_mods/SessFaq.xml"
                xpointer="xpointer(//*[@id='session-management'])"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </appendix>
</book>
