<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
################################################################################
#    HPCC SYSTEMS software Copyright (C) 2012 HPCC Systems®.
#
#    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
#    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
#    You may obtain a copy of the License at
#
#       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
#
#    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
#    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
#    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
#    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
#    limitations under the License.
################################################################################
-->
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
    <title>common/thorhelper</title>

    <para>
        The common/thorhelper directory contains the sources for the thorhelper.so library.
    </para>
    <para>
        This library contains code that is shared between the different engines.  It contains common code for activties -
        e.g., SOAPCALL, PARSE, stepped joins.  It also contains internal code that would be shared between engines - e.g.,
        row allocators, csv reading classes, debug helper classes.
    </para>
    <para>
        The library is dependent on roxiemem (the memory manager is assumed), and can also include dependencies on dali if
        necesary.
    </para>
    <para>
        Although thorhelper primarily exists to share code between the engines, it is also used by the code generator since it
        contains some classes for the PARSE implementation which are created and then serialized.  They are then deserialized
        at runtime.
    </para>
    <para>
        The following is a summary of the different files:
        <itemizedlist override="bullet">
            <listitem>
                commonext.cpp - Mappings from an activity kind to a text string.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                csvsplitter.cpp - Helper classes for processing csv files - dealing with quotes, escape characters and different terminators.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                layouttrans.cpp - Classes for supporting dynamic translation of files from one format to another.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                roxiedebug.cpp - Debugger support classes.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                roxiehelper.cpp - Various implementation classes (could do with rationalizing)
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                roxierow.cpp - Implementation of an IEngineRowAllocator.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorcommon.cpp - Shared implementation classes for hash aggregation, merging, and building rows
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorfile.cpp - helpers for accessing workunit results written to disk.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorparse.cpp - classes shared between both PARSE implementations
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorpipe.cpp - classes for implementing read/write to external PIPE program.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorrparse.cpp - regular expression implementation of PARSE
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorsoapcall.cpp - support classes for SOAPCALL
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorstep.cpp - implementation of the stepped join logic.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorstep2.cpp - classes for optimizing a tree of stepped joins.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thortalgo.cpp - classes to represent a tomita PARSE
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thortlex.cpp - lexer used by the tomita implementation of PARSE.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thortparse.cpp - run time tomita implementation of PARSE
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorxmlread.cpp - xml reading helpers
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                thorxmlwrite.cpp - xml output helpers
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>
