<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1>
  <title>ZAP Utility</title>

  <sect2 id="ZAP">
    <title>Z.A.P. Utility</title>

    <para>The Zipped Analysis Package (Z.A.P.) button is a utility for
    collecting system information and encapsulating it into a shareable
    package. It is a useful tool for reporting errors, inconsistencies, or
    other unexpected behavior. When there is such an occurrence, this utility
    packages up information to send for further analysis.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z.A.P. Button</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWAZ00.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To use the Z.A.P. utility, press the Z.A.P. button on the workunit
    details page from the appropriate workunit. The button opens the Zipped
    Analysis Package dialog.</para>

    <para>Some of the required fields are populated. Fill in the corresponding
    values under Description, History, and the other fields. Optionally, you
    can password protect the ZAP package and choose to include worker logs.
    Worker logs are not included by default. If there are worker logs, the
    option to include them is available. You must check that field when
    available to include the worker logs.</para>

    <para>If your data contains sensitive information, such as personally
    identifiable information (PII), save the ZAP package, sanitize the data,
    then email it manually. If appropriate to share your data, you can take
    advantage of the Send Email field.</para>

    <para>The Send Email field is only available if email is configured for
    the ESP service in the Configuration Manager. If available, check the Send
    Email box to email the ZAP report. Only an Administrator can configure the
    email. The (To) Email Address is also set by the Administrator and can
    only be changed in the configuration. The (From) Email Address can be set
    in the Configuration Manager, but can be changed if desired. The Email
    Subject is required, but the Email Body is optional.</para>

    <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Apply </emphasis>button when all the
    dialog fields are completed. At that point if you checked the Send Email
    box, the Z.A.P. report gets sent. If email is not configured, the Z.A.P.
    utility generates a zip file with all the appropriate information for
    troubleshooting.</para>

    <para>You can find the generated zip file in your browser's designated
    download directory. You can now manually send this file to the person
    handling your support request, or you can upload the file into the issue
    tracking system. Remember, you should only use the email feature if
    appropriate to share your data.</para>

    <sect3 id="ZAP_Config_Options">
      <title>Configuration Options</title>

      <para>The component logs are some of the most important artifacts
      included in these ZAP reports.</para>

      <para>The logging behavior differs on bare metal and containerized
      deployments. In bare metal, some logs are always slated to be included
      (Thor Manager, ECLCC Server, and ECL Agent). The UI checkbox “Include
      worker logs” controls the inclusion of the Thor Worker log files.</para>

      <para>In a containerized environment, you can choose to exclude all the
      logs. Deselect the UI check boxes for the inclusion of the logs.
      Containerized deployments allow this flexibility because logs require a
      remote log reader component which may not be configured on your system.
      Cloud-based logging can lead to additional expenses for data collection
      and downloads compared to traditional bare metal systems, which is why
      some cloud deployments may have logging disabled.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="ZAP-IncludeLogs">
      <title>Including the Logs</title>

      <para>To include the logs check the two UI check boxes:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Include related logs</emphasis> : Controls
      inclusion of the &lt;wuid&gt;.log file.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Include per-component logs</emphasis>:
      Controls inclusion of logs generated from at least these components (the
      list may be vary based on your deployment): ECLCC Server, Thor-ECL
      Agent, Thor Manager, Thor Agent, and Thor Worker.</para>

      <para>In order for these logs to be included in the Z.A.P. the bare
      metal deployments require the ESP feature permission <emphasis
      role="bold">Cluster Topology Access</emphasis> value to be set to
      <emphasis role="bold">READ</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>ClusterTopologyAccess:READ</programlisting>

      <para>A containerized deployment must have logging properly configured
      to be able to include logs. Additionally the user must have the feature
      permission <emphasis>WsLogAccess:Read</emphasis> or the logs will be
      excluded and instead contain an error message indicating which
      permission is required.</para>

      <para>If a "no access" message is present in the ZAP file and there are
      no log files, the permission value specified in the error message must
      be set to ensure the logs are included in the ZAP report.</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="Containerized_Logging">Containerized
      Logging</link> section in the <ulink
      url="https://hpccsystems.com/training/documentation/all/">Containerized
      HPCC Systems Platform</ulink> documentation for more information about
      configuring log processing.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
