<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1>
  <title>ZAP Utility</title>

  <sect2 id="ZAP">
    <title>Z.A.P. Utility</title>

    <para>The Zipped Analysis Package (Z.A.P.) button is a utility for
    collecting system information and encapsulating it into a shareable
    package. It is a useful tool for reporting errors, inconsistencies, or
    other unexpected behavior. When there is such an occurrence, this utility
    packages up information to send for further analysis.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z.A.P. Button</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWAZ00.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To use the Z.A.P. utility, press the Z.A.P. button on the workunit
    details page from the appropriate workunit. The button opens the Zipped
    Analysis Package dialog.</para>

    <para>Some of the required fields are populated. Fill in the corresponding
    values under Description, History, and the other fields. Optionally, you
    can password protect the ZAP package and choose to include worker logs.
    Worker logs are not included by default. If there are worker logs, the
    option to include them is available. You must check that field when
    available to include the worker logs.</para>

    <para>If your data contains sensitive information, such as personally
    identifiable information (PII), save the ZAP package, sanitize the data,
    then email it manually. If appropriate to share your data, you can take
    advantage of the Send Email field.</para>

    <para>The Send Email field is only available if email is configured for
    the ESP service in the Configuration Manager. If available, check the Send
    Email box to email the ZAP report. Only an Administrator can configure the
    email. The (To) Email Address is also set by the Administrator and can
    only be changed in the configuration. The (From) Email Address can be set
    in the Configuration Manager, but can be changed if desired. The Email
    Subject is required, but the Email Body is optional.</para>

    <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Apply </emphasis>button when all the
    dialog fields are completed. At that point if you checked the Send Email
    box, the Z.A.P. report gets sent. If email is not configured, the Z.A.P.
    utility generates a zip file with all the appropriate information for
    troubleshooting.</para>

    <para>You can find the generated zip file in your browser's designated
    download directory. You can now manually send this file to the person
    handling your support request, or you can upload the file into the issue
    tracking system. Remember, you should only use the email feature if
    appropriate to share your data.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

