<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>ZAP Utility</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>ZAP Utility</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../../images/redswooshWithLogo3.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <author>
      <surname>Boca Raton Documentation Team</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>We welcome your comments and feedback about this document via
      email to <email>docfeedback@hpccsystems.com</email> Please include
      <emphasis role="bold">Documentation Feedback</emphasis> in the subject
      line and reference the document name, page numbers, and current Version
      Number in the text of the message.</para>

      <para>LexisNexis and the Knowledge Burst logo are registered trademarks
      of Reed Elsevier Properties Inc., used under license. Other products,
      logos, and services may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their
      respective companies. All names and example data used in this manual are
      fictitious. Any similarity to actual persons, living or dead, is purely
      coincidental.</para>

      <para />
    </legalnotice>

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="FooterInfo"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
      <xi:fallback>
        <para>
          <emphasis>FooterInfo Failed to load</emphasis>
        </para>
      </xi:fallback>
    </xi:include>

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="DateVer"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
      <xi:fallback>
        <para>
          <emphasis>DateVer Failed to load</emphasis>
        </para>
      </xi:fallback>
    </xi:include>

    <corpname>HPCC Systems<superscript>®</superscript></corpname>

    <xi:include href="../../common/Version.xml" xpointer="Copyright"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
      <xi:fallback>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Copyright Failed to load</emphasis>
        </para>
      </xi:fallback>
    </xi:include>

    <mediaobject role="logo">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../../images/LN_Rightjustified.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </bookinfo>

        <sect2 id="ZAP">
          <title>Z.A.P. Utility</title>

          <para>The Zipped Analysis Package (Z.A.P.) button is a utility for
          collecting system information and encapsulating it into a shareable
          package. It is a useful tool for reporting errors, inconsistencies,
          or other unexpected behavior. When there is such an occurrence, this
          utility packages up information to send for further analysis.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Z.A.P. Button</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWAZ00.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>To use the Z.A.P. utility, press the Z.A.P. button on the
          workunit details page from the appropriate workunit. The button
          opens the Zipped Analysis Package dialog.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>The Zipped Analysis Package Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/ECLWAZ01.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Some of the required fields are populated. Fill in the
          corresponding values under Description, History, and Timings fields.
          Optionally, you can password protect the ZAP package and choose to
          include slave logs. Slave logs are not included by default. If there
          are slave logs, the option to include them is available. You must
          check that field when available to include the slave logs.</para>

          <para>If your data contains sensitive information, such as
          personally identifiable information (PII), save the ZAP package,
          sanitize the data, then email it manually. If appropriate to share
          your data, you can take advantage of the Send Email field.</para>

          <para>The Send Email field is only available if email is configured
          for the ESP service in the Configuration Manager. If available,
          check the Send Email box to email the ZAP report. Only an
          Administrator can configure the email. The (To) Email Address is
          also set by the Administrator and can only be changed in the
          configuration. The (From) Email Address can be set in the
          Configuration Manager, but can be changed if desired. The Email
          Subject is required, but the Email Body is optional.</para>

          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Apply </emphasis>button when
          all the dialog fields are completed. At that point if you checked
          the Send Email box, the Z.A.P. report gets sent. If email is not
          configured, the Z.A.P. utility generates a zip file with all the
          appropriate information for troubleshooting.</para>

          <para>You can find the generated zip file in your browser's
          designated download directory. You can now manually send this file
          to the person handling your support request, or you can upload the
          file into the issue tracking system. Remember, you should only use
          the email feature if appropriate to share your data.</para>
        </sect2>
        </book>
        