<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="DPinECLWatch">
  <title><emphasis>Data Patterns In ECL Watch </emphasis></title>

  <para>In this example, we'll use a file created by GenData.ecl from the
  Programmer's Guide.</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Have a running HPCC Platform. This can be a single or multinode
      HPCC Systems platform deployment.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Open ECL Watch in your browser using the following URL:
      http://nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn:pppp (where nnn.nnn.nnn.nnn is your ESP Server's
      IP Address and pppp is the port. The default port is 8010).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Open the Logical Files list by clicking on the third icon on the
      left-hand side.</para>

      <graphic fileref="../../images/DP007.jpg"/>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find the file you want, then click it to open the Logical Files
      Details page.</para>

      <graphic fileref="../../images/DP005.jpg"/>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: Within ECL Watch, only
      datasets with known record definitions are supported. This is solely an
      ECL Watch limitation. You can invoke DataPatterns.Profile()
      programmatically on any kind of valid dataset, including an index
      file.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The first time you open the Data Patterns tab, a notification
      tells you that an analysis is not available. Press the Analyze button to
      generate a Profile analysis. Once complete, the analysis
      displays.</para>

      <graphic fileref="../../images/DP003.jpg"/>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click on the title “Data Patterns” on the bar located near the top
      of the page. Clicking on the Data Patterns title will generate a report
      of the data file.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>Several columns organize each row of information, and each row of
  information represents every attribute in the Profile result.</para>

  <para>Here is a short description of each column:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Type information, Cardinality Count &amp; Filled Count.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Min, Avg, Max Length (for string attributes) or Mean, Std.
      Deviation, Quartiles (for numeric attributes).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Quartile bell curve and candlestick</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>only shown for numeric attributes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>this column is not displayed if there are no numeric
          attributes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Cardinality Breakdown listed by count descending</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>This column is shown for all data scalar data types. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>this column is not displayed if there are no numeric
          attributes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Popular Patterns</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>This column is shown for all data scalar data types. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>this column is not displayed if there are no numeric
          attributes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>For example:</para>

  <graphic fileref="../../images/DP004.jpg"/>

  <para>As seen in the “state” section, the cardinality of each state is
  displayed. The cardinality breakdown is shown for attributes with a low
  number of unique, non-nil values, showing each value and the number of
  records that contain the value.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: The lcbLimit parameter governs
  what “low number” means</para>

  <para>In this example, the cardinality for “NY” is 7%, meaning that 7% of
  records contain the value “NY”.</para>

  <para>The “Min Length'' displays the shortest length of a value, where null
  values are ignored. In SET datatypes, however, “Min Length'' may display the
  fewest number of elements in the set.</para>

  <para>The “Max Length'' displays the longest length of a value, where null
  values are also ignored. SET datatypes displays the largest number of
  elements in the set.</para>

  <para>For the “state” section, the Min and Max Lengths both have a value of
  “2”, since all state abbreviations all consist of 2 letters in the
  string.</para>

  <para>The “Avg Length'' displays the average length of a value when
  expressed. In SET datatypes, it is the average number of elements found in
  the set.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Optimize Results</emphasis></para>

  <para>Optimizing results assigns the string the most efficient value based
  on the Maximum Length contained in the specific section of the dataset by
  rewriting the ECL code. The result is a reduced file size.</para>

  <para>To optimize results, follow the steps below:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Choose a file to run Data Patterns with.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click the “Optimize” button located near the top of the page.
      Clicking the optimize button will make a pop-up appear.</para>

      <graphic fileref="../../images/DP009.jpg"/>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Select a target from the drop-down menu.</para>

      <graphic fileref="../../images/DP006.jpg"/>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click the button labeled "Optimize".</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Check the optimized data file, the original file name with a
      suffix of " :optimized ". Notice that the file size is smaller.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click on the tab labeled "Data Patterns". The strings now have a
      new and optimized value.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</chapter>
