<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Attribute_Creation" role="nobrk">
  <title>Attribute Creation</title>

  <sect2 id="Similarities_and_Differences">
    <title>Similarities and Differences</title>

    <para>The similarities come from the fundamental requirement of solving
    any data processing problem: First, understand the problem.</para>

    <para>After that, in many programming environments, you use a “top-down”
    approach to map out the most direct line of logic to get your input
    transformed into the desired output. This is where the process diverges in
    ECL, because the tool itself requires a different way of thinking about
    forming the solution, and the direct route is not always the fastest. ECL
    requires a “bottom-up” approach to problem solving.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Atomic_Programming">
    <title>“Atomic” Programming</title>

    <para>In ECL, once you understand what the end result needs to be, you
    ignore the direct line from problem input to end result and instead start
    by breaking the issue into as many pieces as possible—the smaller the
    better. By creating “atomic” bits of ECL code, you've done all the known
    and easy bits of the problem. This usually gets you 80% of the way to the
    solution without having to do anything terribly difficult.</para>

    <para>Once you've taken all the bits and made them as atomic as possible,
    you can then start combining them to go the other 20% of the way to
    produce your final solution. In other words, you start by doing the little
    bits that you know you can easily do, then use those bits in combination
    to produce increasingly complex logic that builds the solution
    organically.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Growing_Solutions">
    <title>Growing Solutions</title>

    <para>The basic Attribute building blocks in ECL are the Set, Boolean,
    Recordset, and Value Attribute types. Each of these can be made as
    “atomic” as needed so that they may be used in combination to produce
    “molecules” of more complex logic that may then be further combined to
    produce a complete “organism” that produces the final result.</para>

    <para>For example, assume you have a problem that requires you to produce
    a set of records wherein a particular field in your output must contain
    one of several specified values (say, 1, 3, 4, or 7). In many programming
    languages, the pseudo-code to produce that output would look something
    like this:</para>

    <programlisting>Start at top of MyFile
Loop through MyFile records
 If MyField = 1 or MyField = 3 or MyField = 4 or MyField = 7 
  Include record in output set
 Else
  Throw out record and go back to top of loop
end if and loop
</programlisting>

    <para>While in ECL, the actual code would be:</para>

    <programlisting>SetValidValues := [1,3,4,7];                    //Set Definition
IsValidRec := MyFile.MyField IN SetValidValues; //Boolean
ValRecsMyFile := MyFile(IsValidRec);            //filtered Recordset 
OUTPUT(ValRecsMyFile);
</programlisting>

    <para>The thought process behind writing this code is:</para>

    <para>“I know I have a set of constant values in the spec, so I can start
    by creating a Set attribute of the valid values...</para>

    <para>“And now that I have a Set defined, I can use that Set to create a
    Boolean Attribute to test whether the field I'm interested in contains one
    of the valid values...</para>

    <para>“And now that I have a Boolean defined, I can use that Boolean as
    the filter condition to produce the Recordset I need to output.”</para>

    <para>The process starts with creating the Set Attribute “atom,” then
    using it to build the Boolean “molecule,” then using the Boolean to grow
    the “organism”—the final solution.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Ugly_ECL_is_Possible_Too">
    <title>“Ugly” ECL is Possible, Too</title>

    <para>Of course, that particular set of ECL could have been written like
    this (following a more top down thinking process):</para>

    <programlisting>OUTPUT(MyFile(MyField IN [1,3,4,7]));</programlisting>

    <para>The end result, in this case, would be the same.</para>

    <para>However, the overall usefulness of this code is drastically reduced
    because, in the first form, all the “atomic” bits are available for re-use
    elsewhere when similar problems come along. In this second form, they are
    not. And in all programming styles, code re-use is considered to be a good
    thing.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Easy_Optimization">
    <title>Easy Optimization</title>

    <para>Most importantly, by breaking your ECL code into its smallest
    possible components, you allow ECL’s optimizing compiler to do the best
    job possible of determining how to accomplish your desired result. This
    leads to another dichotomy between ECL and other programming languages:
    usually, the less code you write, the more “elegant” the solution; but in
    ECL, the <emphasis role="underline">more</emphasis> code you write, the
    better and more elegant the solution is generated for you. Remember, your
    Attributes are just <emphasis role="bold">definitions</emphasis> telling
    the compiler <emphasis role="underline">what</emphasis> to do, not
    <emphasis role="underline">how</emphasis> to do it. The more you break
    down the problem into its component pieces, the more leeway you give the
    optimizer to produce the fastest, most efficient executable code.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
