<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Src-code-git">
  <title>The Git Repository</title>

  <para>Git is free open source software for distributed version control. Git
  tracks changes for any set of files. With Git every Git directory on every
  computer is a full-fledged repository with complete history and full
  version-tracking abilities.</para>

  <para>Refer to <ulink
  url="https://git-scm.com/">https://git-scm.com/</ulink> for more
  information.</para>

  <para>HPCC Systems has support for the ECLCC Server to compile ECL code
  directly from Git repositories. The repositories (and optional
  branches/users) are configured using environment variables on the server.
  You can submit a query from a repository branch, and the ECLCC Server will
  pull the source code from a Git repository and compile it. This allows you
  to deploy a specific version of a query without needing to perform any work
  on the client.</para>

  <sect2 id="TheGitImprovements">
    <title>The Git Improvements</title>

    <para>Starting with version 8.4, the platform code for Git support
    significantly improved. Some of these improvements have been backported to
    older support releases such, as 7.12. However, You still need to update to
    a recent point release to ensure you get any of these improvements. While
    the later releases such as 8.6 will include all of these
    improvements.</para>

    <sect3 id="TheSpeedImprovements">
      <title>Speed Improvements</title>

      <para>The platform code has been upgraded for significant improvements
      to the speed. Featuring faster compiling from Git repositories without
      the added overhead when compared with compiling from checked out
      sources.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="GitResourcesAndManifests">
      <title>Git Resources and Manifests</title>

      <para>The HPCC Systems platform now supports Git manifests and resources
      when compiling.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="GitLFs_Support">
      <title>Git-lfs Support</title>

      <para>Git-lfs is an extension to Git that improves support for large
      files and is supported by both GitHub and GitLab. This extension is
      particularly useful for large resources. For example, if you have java
      packages included as part of the manifest.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="MultipleRepositorySupprt">
      <title>Multiple Repository Support</title>

      <para>The HPCC Systems platform code includes support for using multiple
      Git repositories. With this multiple repository support the HPCC Systems
      platform now allows each Git repository to be treated as a separate
      independent package. Dependencies between the repositories are specified
      in a package file which is checked into the repository and versioned
      along with the ECL code. The package file indicates what the
      dependencies are and which versions should be used.</para>

      <para>This approach resolves concerns such as when merging changes from
      multiple sources into a single repository. In that context it solves
      issues with incompatible changes, dependencies, or clashes if there are
      modules with the same name and ensures that the dependencies between
      repositories are versioned.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="UsingGitWithHPCC">
    <title>Using Git with HPCC</title>

    <para>The --main syntax has been extended to allow compiling directly from
    the repository.</para>

    <para>Consider the following command :</para>

    <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@https://github.com/gituser/gch-demo-d#version1 --server=... </programlisting>

    <para>This command submits a query to Thor via ESP. It retrieves ECL code
    from the 'version1' branch in the https://hithub.com/gituser/gch-demo-d
    repository. Compiles the code in the demo/main.ecl file and then runs the
    query on Thor. The checkout will be done on the remote ECLCC Server rather
    than on the client machine.</para>

    <sect3 id="RepoReferenceSyntax">
      <title>Repository Reference Syntax</title>

      <para>The syntax for the reference to the repository is as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;protocol:&gt;//&lt;urn&gt;/&lt;user&gt;/&lt;repository&gt;#version</programlisting>

      <para>The protocol and urn can be omitted and a default will be used.
      Such as in the following example:</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version1 --server=...</programlisting>

      <para>This command also submits a query to Thor, retrieves ECL code from
      the 'version1' branch in the gch-demo-d repository. Compiles the code in
      the demo.main.ecl file and then runs the query on Thor.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="HashVersionText">
      <title>Version-Text</title>

      <para>The version text that follows the hash (#) in the repository
      reference can take any of the following forms:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of a branch</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of a tag</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> Currently only
          lightweight tags are supported. Annotated tags are not yet
          supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The secure hash algorithm (SHA) of a commit</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To illustrate consider the following commands:</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version1 --server=...</programlisting>

      <para>This command will retrieve the demo.main ECL code from the
      'version1' branch of the gch-ecldemo-d repository.</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#3c23ca0 --server=...</programlisting>

      <para>This command will retrieve the demo.main ECL code from the commit
      with the SHA of '3c23ca0'.</para>

      <para>You can also specify the name of a tag utilizing this same
      syntax.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Checking ECL Syntax</title>

      <para>You can use the --syntax option to check the syntax of your
      code.</para>

      <para>The following command checks the syntax of the code in the commit
      with the SHA of '3c23ca0' of the gch-ecldemo-d repository.</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@ghalliday/gch-ecldemo-d#3c23ca0 --syntax </programlisting>

      <para>While the following command would check the syntax of the code in
      the 'version1' branch of the gch-ecldemo-d repository.</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run thor --main demo.main@ghalliday/gch-ecldemo-d#version1 --syntax </programlisting>

      <para>Since the code in a branch could possibly get updated and change -
      it is a good idea to always check the syntax.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="PrGIT-ThePkgJSON">
      <title>The Package JSON</title>

      <para>Consider this package.json file:</para>

      <programlisting>{
 "name": "demoRepoC",
 "version": "1.0.0", 
 "dependencies": { 
      "demoRepoD": "gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version1" 
 } 
} </programlisting>

      <para>The package file gives a name to the package and defines the
      dependencies. The dependencies property is a list of key-value pairs.
      The key (demoRepoD) provides the name of the ECL module that is used to
      access the external repository. The value is a repository reference
      which uses the same format as the previous examples using the --main
      syntax.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="ExternalGitRepoInECLCode">
      <title>Use the External Repository in your ECL Code</title>

      <para>To use the external repository in your ECL code you need to add an
      <emphasis>import</emphasis> definition.</para>

      <programlisting>IMPORT layout;
IMPORT demoRepoD AS demoD;
 
EXPORT personAsText(layout.person input) :=
    input.name + ': ‘ +
 demoD.format.maskPassword(input.password);
</programlisting>

      <para>The above example the name demoRepoD in the second IMPORT matches
      the key value in the package.json file. This code uses the attribute
      format.maskPassword from the version1 branch from the
      gituser/gch-ecldemo-d.</para>

      <para>Each package is processed independently of any others. The only
      connection is through explicit imports of the external packages. This is
      why packages can have modules or attributes with the same name and they
      will not clash.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="MultipleGitRepositoryExample">
      <title>Multiple Repository Examples</title>

      <para>The following is an example of a package.json file using multiple
      repositories.</para>

      <para><programlisting>IMPORT layout;
IMPORT demoRepoD_V1 AS demo1;
IMPORT demoRepoD_V2 AS demo2;
 
EXPORT personAsText(layout.person input) :=
'Was: ' + demo1.format.maskPassword(input.password) +
    ' Now: ' + demo2.format.maskPassword(input.password);
</programlisting>Note that the demoRepoD repository _V1 and _V2 are processed
      independently.</para>

      <para>Likewise consider the following example using Query ECL</para>

      <programlisting>{
  "name": "demoRepoC",
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "dependencies": {
    "demoRepoD_V1": "gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version1"
    "demoRepoD_V2": "gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version2"
  }
}
</programlisting>

      <para>Noting the dependencies of the branches 'version1' and 'version2'
      of the gch-ecldemo-d repository.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 lang="PrG_GitCommandLineOptions">
    <title>Command Line Options</title>

    <para>Command line options have been added to the ECL and ECLCC commands
    to leverage these improvements in working with Git repositories.</para>

    <sect3 id="GitLocalDevelopOptions">
      <title>Local Development Options</title>

      <para>The -R option has been added to the eclcc and ecl commands. Set
      the -R option instruct the compiler to use source from a local directory
      instead of using source from an external repository.</para>

      <para>Syntax:</para>

      <para><programlisting>-R&lt;repo&gt;[#version]=path </programlisting>For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>ecl run examples/main.ecl -Rgituser/gch-ecldemo-d=/home/myuser/source/demod </programlisting>

      <para>This command uses the ECL code for DemoRepoD from
      /home/myuser/source/demoD rather than
      https://github.com/gituser/gch-ecldemo-d#version1.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="PrGTheVerboseOption">
      <title>The Verbose Option</title>

      <para>The -v option has been improved to provide more verbose output
      including the details of the Git requests.</para>

      <para>You could use the -v option for debugging. For instance, if you
      have any issues of repositories not resolving. Issue the command as
      follows with the -v option to analyse the details of the Git
      requests.</para>

      <para><programlisting>ecl run examples/main.ecl -v -Rgituser/gch-ecldemo-d=/home/myuser/source/demod </programlisting></para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="ECLandECLCCGitOptions">
      <title>ECL and ECLCC Git Options</title>

      <para>These command line options have been added to the ECL and ECLCC
      commands.</para>

      <para>--<emphasis role="bold">defaultgitprefix</emphasis> This command
      line option changes the default prefix that is added to relative
      packages references. The default can also be configured using the
      environment variable ECLCC_DEFAULT_GITPREFIX. Otherwise It defaults to
      "https://github.com/".</para>

      <para>--<emphasis role="bold">fetchrepos</emphasis> Setting this option
      tells whether external repositories that have not been cloned locally
      should be fetched. This defaults to true in 8.6.x. It may be useful to
      set this option to false if all external repositories are mapped to
      local directories to verify if they are being redirected
      correctly.</para>

      <para>--<emphasis role="bold">updaterepos</emphasis> Updates external
      repositories that have previously been fetched locally. This option
      defaults to true. It is useful to set this option to false if you are
      working in a situation with no access to the external repositories, or
      to avoid the overhead of checking for changes if you know there aren't
      any.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">ECLCC_ECLREPO_PATH</emphasis> The directory
      the external repositories are cloned to. On a client machine this
      defaults to: &lt;home&gt;/.HPCCSystems/repos (or
      %APPDATA%\HPCCSystems\repos on windows). You can delete the contents of
      this directory to force a clean download of all repositories.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="GitHelmChartConfigurationOptions">
      <title>Helm Chart Configuration Options</title>

      <para>These are Helm chart options for configuring Git values for cloud
      deployments. The following values are now supported for configuring the
      use of Git within Helm charts for HPCC Systems cloud deployments.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">eclccserver.gitUsername</emphasis> -
      Provides the Git user name</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">secrets.git </emphasis>- Define the
      secrets.git to allow repositories to be shared between queries, to be
      able to cache and share the cloned packages between instances.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">eclccserver.gitPlane</emphasis> - This
      options defines the storage plane that external packages are checked out
      and cloned to.</para>

      <para>For example</para>

      <programlisting>eclccserver:
- name: myeclccserver
  #...
- gitPlane: git/sample/storage</programlisting>

      <para>If the gitPlane option is not supplied, the default is the first
      storage plane with a category of Git - otherwise ECLCC Server uses the
      first storage plane with a category of dll.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="PrGSecurityAndAuthentication">
    <title>Security and Authentication</title>

    <para>If external repositories are public, such as bundles, then there are
    no further requirements. Private repositories have the additional
    complication of requiring authentication information - either on the
    client or on the ECLCC Server depending on where the source is gathered.
    Git provides various methods for providing these credentials.</para>

    <sect3 id="PrG_ClientMachinesAuth">
      <title>Client Machine Authentication</title>

      <para>These are the recommended approaches for configuring the
      credentials on a local system that is interacting with a remote
      GitHub.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">github authentication</emphasis>
          Download the GitHub command line toolkit. You can then use it to
          authenticate all Git access with the following command:</para>

          <programlisting>gh auth login </programlisting>

          <para>This is probably your best option if you are using GitHub.
          More details can be found on:</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="https://cli.github.com/manual/gh_auth_login">https://cli.github.com/manual/gh_auth_login</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">ssh key</emphasis> In this scenario, the
          ssh key associated with a local developers machine is registered
          with the GitHub account. This is used when the GitHub reference is
          of the form of ssh://github.com.</para>

          <para>The sshkey can be protected with a passcode and there are
          various options to avoid having to enter the passcode each time. For
          more information see:</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh/about-ssh ">https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh/about-ssh</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Use a personal access token</emphasis>
          These are similar to a password, but with additional restrictions on
          their lifetime and the resources that can be accessed. Here are the
          details on how to to create them. They can then be used with the
          various git credential caching options.</para>

          <para>An example can be found here:</para>

          <para><ulink
          url="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Credential-Storage">https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Credential-Storage</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Generally, for authentication it is preferrable to use the
      https:// protocol instead of the ssh:// protocol for links in
      package-lock.json files. If the ssh:// is used it requires any machine
      that processes the dependency to have access to a registered ssh key.
      That can sometimes cause avoidable issues.</para>

      <para>All of these Authentication options are likely to involve some
      user interaction, such as passphrases for ssh keys, web interaction with
      GitHub authentication, and initial entry for cached access tokens. This
      is problematic for the ECLCC Server which cannot support user
      interaction, and since it is preferrable not to pass credentials around.
      The solution therefore is to use a personal access token securely stored
      as a secret. This token could then be associated with a special service
      account, which would then securely initiate these transactions. The
      secret then avoids the need to pass credentials and allows the keys to
      be rotated.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="PrgKubernetesSecrets">
      <title>Kubernetes Secrets</title>

      <para>This section describes secrets support in the Kubernetes (and bare
      metal) versions of the HPCC Systems platform.</para>

      <para>To add secrets support:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>. Add the gitUsername property to the eclccserver component of
          your customization yaml file:</para>

          <programlisting>   eclccserver:
   - name: myeclccserver
     gitUsername: <emphasis role="bold">gituser</emphasis>
</programlisting>

          <para>Note: the eclccserver.gitUsername value should match your git
          user name.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add a secret to the customization yaml file, with a key that
          matches the gitUsername</para>

          <programlisting>secrets:
     git: 
       gituser: <emphasis role="bold">my-git-secret</emphasis>
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add the secret to Kubernetes containing the personal access
          token:</para>

          <programlisting>apiVersion: v1
kind: Secret
metadata:
  name: <emphasis role="bold">my-git-secret</emphasis>
type: Opaque
stringData:
  password: ghp_eZLHeuoHxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxol3986sS=
</programlisting>

          <para>Note password contains the personal access token.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Apply the secret to your Kubernetes using the kubectl
          command:</para>

          <programlisting>kubectl apply -f ~/dev/hpcc/helm/secrets/my-git-secret</programlisting>

          <para>When a query is submitted to the ECLCC Server, any git
          repositories are then accessed using this configured user name and
          password.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Store the secret in a vault. You can also store the PAT
          (personal access token) inside a vault.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="CredentialsInBareMetal">
      <title>Bare Metal Credentials</title>

      <para>This section describes credentials for bare metal systems. Bare
      metal systems require some similar configuration steps.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add the gitUsername property to the EclCCServerProcess entry
          in the environment.xml file.</para>

          <programlisting>&lt;EclCCServerProcess daliServers="mydali"
                      ...
                      gitUsername="gitguser“
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Push out the environment.xml to all nodes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Either store the credentials as secrets or store in a
          vault.</para>

          <para>As <emphasis role="bold">secrets</emphasis>:</para>

          <para>Store the access token in:</para>

          <para>/opt/HPCCSystems/secrets/git/&lt;user-name&gt;/password</para>

          <para>For example:</para>

          <programlisting>cat /opt/HPCCSystems/secrets/git/gitusr/password
ghp_eZLHeuoHxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxol3986sS=
</programlisting>

          <para>Or for a <emphasis role="bold">vault</emphasis>:</para>

          <para>You can store inside a vault. You can now define a vault
          within the Software section of the environment. For example:</para>

          <programlisting>&lt;Environment&gt;
 &lt;Software&gt;
   ...
   &lt;vaults&gt;
    &lt;git name='my-storage-vault' url="http://127.0.0.1:8200/v1/secret/data/git/${secret}" 
kind="kv-v2" client-secret="myVaultSecret"/&gt;
    ...
   &lt;/vaults&gt;
   ...
</programlisting>

          <para>Note that the above entries have the same exact content as the
          corresponding entries in the kubernetes values.yaml file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
