<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="VizIntro">
  <title><emphasis>Visualization Introduction</emphasis></title>

  <para>The Visualization bundle is an open-source add-on to the HPCC platform
  to allow you to create visualizations from the results of queries written in
  ECL.</para>

  <para>Visualizations are an important means of conveying information from
  massive data. A good visual representation can help a human produce
  actionable analysis. A visually comprehensive representation of the
  information can help make the obscure more obvious.</para>

  <para>Pie Charts, Line graphs, Maps, and other visual graphs help us
  understand the answers found in data queries. Crunching big data is only
  part of a solution; we must be able to make sense of the data, too. Data
  visualizations simplify the complex.</para>

  <para>The Visualizer bundle extends the HPCC platform's functionality by
  allowing you to plot your data onto charts, graphs, and maps to add a visual
  representation that can be easily understood.</para>

  <para>In addition, the underlying visualization framework supports advanced
  features to allow you to combine graphs to make interactive
  dashboards.</para>

  <sect1 id="VizInstall">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>To install the Visualization bundle, use the ecl command line
    interface.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><programlisting>ecl bundle install https://github.com/hpcc-systems/Visualizer.git</programlisting></para>

    <para>To use the "ecl bundle install &lt;git url&gt;" command, you must
    have git installed and configured on your system. Git must be accessible
    to the user (in the path).</para>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="VizUsing">
    <title>Using the Visualization library</title>

    <para>Once installed, you merely IMPORT the library, then call any method
    that is appropriate for your data shape.</para>

    <para>Creating a basic visualization typically requires the following
    steps:</para>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Creation of a suitable dataset.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Output the dataset with a suitable name, so that visualization
          can locate the data.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create (and output) a the visualization, referencing the named
          output from step 2.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>To change the appearance of the visualization, dermatology
    properties can be provided while creating the visualization or can be
    applied at runtime via the live dermatology property editor.</para>

    <para>For Example:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">IMPORT Visualizer;
ds := DATASET([ {'English', 5},
                {'History', 17},
                {'Geography', 7},
                {'Chemistry', 16},
                {'Irish', 26},
                {'Spanish', 67},
                {'Bioligy', 66},
                {'Physics', 46},
                {'Math', 98}],
                {STRING subject, INTEGER4 year});
data_example := OUTPUT(ds, NAMED('Chart2D__test'));
data_example;
viz_bubble := Visualizer.TwoD.Bubble('bubble',, 'Chart2D__test');
viz_bubble;
</programlisting>

    <para>This code creates a Bubble chart as shown below:</para>

    <graphic fileref="../../images/viz10.jpg" />

    <para></para>

    <para>See <link linkend="VizMethods">Methods</link> for details about the
    categories of visualization methods and all available methods.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="VizViewing">
    <title>Viewing the Visualization</title>

    <para>After running a query with a visualization included, you can see the
    visualization in ECL Watch. Visualizations are appended to the workunit as
    additional <emphasis>resources</emphasis> and can be viewed from the
    <emphasis role="bold">Resources</emphasis> tab on the Workunit Details
    page.</para>

    <para>Open the workunit, then select the <emphasis
    role="bold">Resources</emphasis> tab.</para>

    <para><graphic fileref="../../images/viz07.jpg" /></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="VizDermProp">
    <title>Dermatology Properties</title>

    <para>The dermatology layer provides a means of setting properties for the
    manner in which a visualization appears. For example, you can change the
    palletteID to a new color scheme. After running a query with a
    visualization included, it can be viewed within ECL Watch.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Dermatology Editor</emphasis> lets you
    alter the appearance of the visualization after it has been executed. The
    same properties can also be specified in the ECL when creating the
    visualization.</para>

    <para>You can set properties in your ECL code or afterwards in ECL
    Watch:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open the workunit, then select the <emphasis
        role="bold">Resources</emphasis> tab.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Properties</emphasis>
        button.</para>

        <graphic fileref="../../images/viz08.jpg" />
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edit Properties as desired. <emphasis
        role="bold"></emphasis></para>

        <para><graphic fileref="../../images/viz09.jpg" /></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button.<emphasis
        role="bold"></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
