<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Attribute_Visibility">
  <title>Definition Visibility<indexterm>
      <primary>Definition Visibility</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>ECL definitions are organized into modules (directories or folders on
  disk). Within a module, you may define as many Definitions as needed. An
  IMPORT statement (see the <emphasis role="bold">IMPORT </emphasis>keyword)
  identifies any other modules whose visible Definitions will be available for
  use in the current definition.</para>

  <programlisting>IMPORT AnotherModule; //imports definitions from AnotherModule
Definition1 := 5;     //as many definitions as needed</programlisting>

  <para>The following fundamental definition visibility scopes are available
  in ECL: <emphasis role="bold">"Global," Module</emphasis>, and <emphasis
  role="bold">Local</emphasis>.</para>

  <sect2 id="Global_attribute_visibility">
    <title>"Global"</title>

    <para>Definitions defined as <emphasis
    role="bold">EXPORT</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>EXPORT</primary>
      </indexterm> (see the <emphasis role="bold">EXPORT</emphasis> keyword)
    are available throughout the module in which they are defined, and
    throughout any other module that IMPORTs the module (see the <emphasis
    role="bold">IMPORT</emphasis> keyword).</para>

    <programlisting>EXPORT Definition1 := 5;
//make Definition1 available to other modules and
//also available throughout its own module</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Module">
    <title>Module</title>

    <para>The scope of the Definitions defined as <emphasis
    role="bold">SHARED<indexterm>
        <primary>SHARED</primary>
      </indexterm></emphasis> (see the <emphasis role="bold">SHARED</emphasis>
    keyword) is limited to that one module, and are available throughout the
    module (unlike local Definitions). This allows you to keep private any
    definitions that are only needed to implement internal
    functionality.</para>

    <programlisting>SHARED Definition1 := 5;
//Definition1 available throughout its own module, only
EXPORT Definition2 := Definition1 + 5;
//make Definition2 available to other modules and
//also available throughout its own module</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Local">
    <title>Local</title>

    <para>A Definition defined without either EXPORT or SHARED (see the
    <emphasis role="bold">EXPORT </emphasis>and <emphasis
    role="bold">SHARED</emphasis> keywords) is available only to the
    subsequent Definitions until the next Definition definition with EXPORT or
    SHARED. This makes them private Definitions used only within the scope of
    that EXPORT or SHARED Definition. This allows you to keep private any
    definitions that are only needed to implement internal functionality.
    Local Definitions are referenced by the Definition name alone; no
    qualification is needed.</para>

    <programlisting>MODULE abc;
LocalAttr := 5;
//local -- available through the end of Definition1's definition, only
SHARED Definition1 := LocalAttr;
//SHARED terminates scope for LocalAttr
Definition2 := Definition1 + LocalAttr;
//INVALID SYNTAX -- LocalAttr is out of scope here</programlisting>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
