<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Attribute_Visibility">
  <title>Definition Visibility<indexterm>
      <primary>Definition Visibility</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>ECL code, definitions, are stored in .ECL files <indexterm>
      <primary>.ECL files</primary>
    </indexterm>in your code repository, which are organized into modules
  (directories or folders on disk). Each .ECL file may only contain a single
  EXPORT or SHARED definition (see below) along with any supporting local
  definitions required to fully define the definition's result. The name of
  the file and the name of its EXPORT or SHARED definition must exactly
  match.</para>

  <para>Within a module (directory or folder on disk), you may have as many
  EXPORT and/or SHARED definitions as needed. An IMPORT statement (see the
  <emphasis role="bold">IMPORT </emphasis>keyword) identifies any other
  modules whose visible definitions will be available for use in the current
  definition.</para>

  <para>The following fundamental definition visibility scopes are available
  in ECL: <emphasis role="bold">"Global," Module</emphasis>, and <emphasis
  role="bold">Local</emphasis>.</para>

  <sect2 id="Global_attribute_visibility">
    <title>"Global"</title>

    <para>Definitions defined as <emphasis
    role="bold">EXPORT</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>EXPORT</primary>
      </indexterm> (see the <emphasis role="bold">EXPORT</emphasis> keyword)
    are available throughout the module in which they are defined, and
    throughout any other module that IMPORTs that module (see the <emphasis
    role="bold">IMPORT</emphasis> keyword).</para>

    <programlisting>//inside the Definition1.ecl file (in AnotherModule folder) you have:
EXPORT Definition1 := 5;  
   //EXPORT makes Definition1 available to other modules and
   //also available throughout its own module</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Module">
    <title>Module</title>

    <para>The scope of the definitions defined as <emphasis
    role="bold">SHARED<indexterm>
        <primary>SHARED</primary>
      </indexterm></emphasis> (see the <emphasis role="bold">SHARED</emphasis>
    keyword) is limited to that one module, and are available throughout the
    module (unlike local definitions). This allows you to keep private any
    definitions that are only needed to implement internal functionality.
    SHARED definitions are used to support EXPORT definitions.</para>

    <programlisting>//inside the Definition2.ecl file you have:
IMPORT AnotherModule;
   //makes definitions from AnotherModule available to this code, as needed

SHARED Definition2 := AnotherModule.Definition1 + 5;  
   //Definition2 available throughout its own module, only

//*****************************************************************************
//then inside the Definition3.ecl file (in the sam efolder as Definition2) you have:
IMPORT $;  
   //makes definitions from the current module available to this code, as needed

EXPORT Definition3 := $.Definition2 + 5;
  //make Definition3 available to other modules and
  //also available throughout its own module</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Local">
    <title>Local</title>

    <para>A definition without either the EXPORT or SHARED keywords is
    available only to subsequent definitions, until the end of the next EXPORT
    or SHARED definition. This makes them private definitions used only within
    the scope of that one EXPORT or SHARED definition, which allows you to
    keep private any definitions that are only needed to implement internal
    functionality. Local definitions definitions are used to support the
    EXPORT or SHARED definition in whose file they reside. Local definitions
    are referenced by their definition name alone; no qualification is
    needed.</para>

    <programlisting>//then inside the Definition4.ecl file (in the same folder as Definition2) you have:
IMPORT $;  
   //makes definitions from the current module available to this code, as needed

LocalDef := 5;
  //local -- available through the end of Definition4's definition, only

EXPORT Definition4 := LocalDef + 5;
//EXPORT terminates scope for LocalDef

LocalDef2 := Definition4 + LocalDef;
  //INVALID SYNTAX -- LocalDef is out of scope here
  //and any local definitions following the EXPORT
  //or SHARED definition in the file are meaningless 
  //since they can never be used by anything
</programlisting>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">LOCAL</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>LOCAL</primary>
      </indexterm> keyword is valid for use only within a FUNCTIONMACRO
    structure to clearly identify that the scope of a definition is limited to
    the code generated within the FUNCTIONMACRO. Although you can use LOCAL
    outside of a FUNCTIONMACRO structure without generating a syntax error, it
    has no effect elsewhere.</para>

    <programlisting>AddOne(num) := FUNCTIONMACRO
  LOCAL numPlus := num + 1;
  RETURN numPlus;
ENDMACRO;

numPlus := 'this is a syntax error without LOCAL in the FUNCTIONMACRO';
numPlus;
AddOne(5);
</programlisting>

    <para>See Also: <link linkend="IMPORT">IMPORT</link>, <link
    linkend="EXPORT">EXPORT</link>, <link linkend="SHARED">SHARED</link>,
    <link linkend="MODULE_Structure">MODULE</link>, <link
    linkend="FUNCTIONMACRO_Structure">FUNCTIONMACRO</link></para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
