<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Actions_and_Attributes">
  <title>Actions and Attributes</title>

  <para>There are several built-in Actions in ECL (such as OUTPUT), but there
  are many more actions that you can execute as queries to the
  supercomputer.</para>

  <sect2 id="Functions_as_ActionsFunctions_as_Actions">
    <title>Functions as Actions<indexterm>
        <primary>Functions as Actions</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Fundamentally, all the built-in functions that return single values
    (such as COUNT) can be executed as Actions. For example,</para>

    <programlisting>Attr1 := COUNT(Trades);
Attr2 := MAX(Trades,trd_bal);
Attr3 := IF (1 = 0, 'A', 'B');</programlisting>

    <para>are all attribute definitions, but</para>

    <programlisting>COUNT(Trades); //execute these Function calls as Actions
MAX(Trades,trd_bal);
IF (1 = 0, 'A', 'B');</programlisting>

    <para>are also all valid actions, and as such, can directly generate
    result values by simply submitting them as queries to the supercomputer.
    Basically, any ECL expression that results in a scalar value can be used
    as an Action to instigate a workunit.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Attributes_as_ActionsAttributes_as_Actions">
    <title>Attributes as Actions<indexterm>
        <primary>Attributes as Actions</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Any Attribute that defines a single value of some sort (that is, it
    does not define a record set) can be executed as an Action. These same
    actions can be executed by submitting the names of the Attributes as
    queries, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>Attr1; //These all generate the same result values
Attr2; // as the previous examples
Attr3;</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Actions_as_Attributes">
    <title>Actions as Attributes<indexterm>
        <primary>Actions as Attributes</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Conversely, by simply giving any Action an Attribute name you turn
    it into an Attribute definition, therefore no longer a directly executable
    action. For example,</para>

    <programlisting>OUTPUT(Person);</programlisting>

    <para>is an action, but</para>

    <programlisting>Attr4 := OUTPUT(Person);</programlisting>

    <para>is an attribute definition and does not immediately execute when
    submitted as part of a query. To execute the action inherent in the
    attribute, you must execute the Attribute name you've given to the Action,
    like this:</para>

    <programlisting>Attr4; // run the OUTPUT(Person) action</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Debugging_Uses">
    <title>Debugging Uses</title>

    <para>This technique of directly executing an attribute as an Action is
    useful when debugging complex ECL code. You can send the attribute as a
    query to determine if intermediate values are correctly calculated before
    continuing on with more complex code.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
