<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="Actions_and_Attributes">
  <title>Actions and Definitions</title>

  <para>There are several built-in Actions in ECL (such as OUTPUT), but there
  are many more actions that you can execute as queries to the supercomputer.
  Fundamentally, an Action is simply an expression that produces a result that
  has not been given a definition name.</para>

  <sect2 id="Functions_as_ActionsFunctions_as_Actions">
    <title>Functions as Actions<indexterm>
        <primary>Functions as Actions</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Fundamentally, all the built-in functions that return single values
    (such as COUNT) can be executed as Actions. For example,</para>

    <programlisting>Attr1 := COUNT(Trades);
Attr2 := MAX(Trades,trd_bal);
Attr3 := IF (1 = 0, 'A', 'B');</programlisting>

    <para>are all definitions, but</para>

    <programlisting>COUNT(Trades);       //execute these Function calls as Actions
MAX(Trades,trd_bal);
IF (1 = 0, 'A', 'B');</programlisting>

    <para>are also all valid actions, and as such, can directly generate
    result values by simply submitting them as queries to the supercomputer.
    Basically, any ECL expression can be used as an Action to instigate a
    workunit.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Attributes_as_ActionsAttributes_as_Actions">
    <title>Definitions as Actions<indexterm>
        <primary>Definitions as Actions</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Any definition that defines a single value or record set can be
    executed as an Action. These same actions can be executed by submitting
    the names of the Attributes as queries, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>Attr1; //These all generate the same result values
Attr2; // as the previous examples
Attr3;</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Actions_as_Attributes">
    <title>Actions as Definitions<indexterm>
        <primary>Actions as Definitions</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Conversely, by simply giving any Action a Definition name you turn
    it into a definition, therefore no longer a directly executable action.
    For example,</para>

    <programlisting>OUTPUT(Person);</programlisting>

    <para>is an action, but</para>

    <programlisting>Attr4 := OUTPUT(Person);</programlisting>

    <para>is a definition and does not immediately execute when submitted as
    part of a query. To execute the action inherent in the definition, you
    must execute the Definition name you've given to the Action, like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>Attr4; // run the OUTPUT(Person) action</programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="Debugging_Uses">
    <title>Debugging Uses</title>

    <para>This technique of directly executing a Definition as an Action is
    useful when debugging complex ECL code. You can send the Definition as a
    query to determine if intermediate values are correctly calculated before
    continuing on with more complex code.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
